<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Praiers of holi fathers, patryarches, prophetes, iudges, kynges, and renowmed men and wemen of eyther testamente</title>
            <title>Bible. English. Selections.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1544</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 203 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 113 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09942</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20200</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105486</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841214</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841214</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5778</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09942)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5778)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 140:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Praiers of holi fathers, patryarches, prophetes, iudges, kynges, and renowmed men and wemen of eyther testamente</title>
                  <title>Bible. English. Selections.</title>
                  <author>Brunfels, Otto, 1488-1534. Precationes Biblicae.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>108, [8] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Richard Grafton .. These bookes are to bee solde at the weste doore of P[aule]s in London. By Wyllyam Tylotson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted in London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1544?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Extracts from the Bible, based on: Brunfels, Otto. Precationes Biblicae.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Printer's and bookseller's names from colophon; publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Prayers of the Bible.</note>
                  <note>With 17 final contents pages.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prayers.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="prayers">
            <pb facs="tcp:5778:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5778:1"/>
            <head>PRAIERS OF HOLI FA<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers, Patryarches, Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, Iudges, Kynges, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowmed men and wemen of eyther teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente.</head>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ The praier of Moſes to the Lorde, for the ſynnes of the people. <bibl>Exod. 32.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>ORD, why waxeth thy wrath hote againſt thi peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple, which y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſte brought forthe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lande of Egipt with a greate power, and with a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghtie hande? wherfore ſhould the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giptyans ſpeake and ſaie, he worketh craftelye with theim, euen to rydde theim oute of the worlde? Tourne awaye thy fyerce wrathe, and haue compaſſion ouer the wyckedneſſe of the people. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ An other prayer of Moſes vnto the ſame. <bibl>Exodi. 32.</bibl>
               </head>
               <pb facs="tcp:5778:2"/>
               <p>OH, this people hath ſynned an heinouſe ſinne, &amp; haue made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> golden goddes, Either forgeue theim this offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, or els wype me oute of this boke, which y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt wryte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Am<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ For the ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of the people what time they murmured, a prayer of Moſes. <bibl>Nume. 14.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>THe Lord is longe er he be angry and is full of mercy, ſufferyng ſynne and treſpaſſe, and leauing no manne innocente, whiche viſiteſt the vnrighteouſneſſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fathers v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyldren, euen vpon the third &amp; fourth generacion. Be merciful I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſech the therfore vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſinne of this thy people, according vnto thy greate mercye, &amp; according as thou haſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geuen this people, comming from E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gipte euen vnto this place.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ An other of Moſes and Aaro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the people. <bibl>Nume. 16.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Moſte myghtie God of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites of all fleſhe, one ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne hath
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:5778:2"/> ſynned, &amp; wylte thou bee wroth with all the multitude?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ For the ſtubbernes of the people: the true preacher on this wyſe as Moſes dyd, maie make his prayer vnto God. <bibl>Deute. 9.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>O Lord God, deſtroy not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people and thine inheritau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce whiche y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt deliuered through thy great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes and which thou haſt brought out of the Egypte of this worlde. Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre thy ſeruauntes, Abraham, Iſaac, and Iacob, and loke not vnto the ſtub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bernes of this people, neither conſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der yet theyr wickednes and greuous offence, for it is thyne owne people &amp; thyne enheritaunce whiche thou haſt chalenged for thine owne in thy great might &amp; in thy ſtretched out arme. Am<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ The prayer of Salomon in the dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacion of the temple of Hieruſalem. <bibl>3. Kyng. 8.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>BLeſſed be the Lorde God of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell, which hath fulfilled with
<pb facs="tcp:5778:3"/> his hande that he ſpake w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his mouth vnto Dauid my father, Lord God of Iſrael, there is no God lyke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen aboue, or in the earth beneth, that kepeſt appointment &amp; mercy with thy ſeruauntes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> walke before thee with al their hertes, which alſo haſt kept co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenaunte w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy ſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aunt Dauyd my father that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> promiſedeſt hym. Now then O Lorde God of Iſraell, let thy worde bee ſtable, whiche thou ſpakeſt vnto thy ſeruaunte Dauid my father But in dede can God dwel on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth Beholde neyther heauen, nor heauen aboue all the heauens are able to con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teyn thee, howe muche leſſe then this houſe that I haue buylte: but looke to the prayer of thy ſeruaunte &amp; his ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicacion. O Lorde my God, geue an eare vnto the voice and praier, which thy ſeruaunt praieth afore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> this daie And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy people ſhal haue ſynned agaynſte the (for there is no man that ſynneth not) thou ſhalte bee angrye
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:5778:3"/> with theim, yet yf they tourne agayn with all theyr heart, and dooe repente in theyr hearte, makyng theyr prayer vnto thee, ſaiyng, we haue ſinned, we haue dealte vniuſtely, we haue dooen wyckedly, and ſo retourne again vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the with all theyr hert and all their ſoule, &amp; make ſupplicacyon vnto the: then thou ſhalte heare from Heauen, euen from the firmament of thy ſeate theyr prayers and peticions, and ſhalt bee mercyfull vnto the ſynnes of thy people, whiche haue offended the, and ſhalte ſhewe theim iuſtyce and mercie for they bee thy people and thine enhe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rytaunce, whiche thou broughteſt out of Egypte from the fourneſſe of yern and lette thyne eyes bee opened to the prayer of thy ſeruaunt, and vnto the praier of thy people Iſrael, to herken vnto theim in all that they call vnto thee for. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ A prayer of Eſdras for the ſynnes of the people. <bibl>1. Eſd. 9.</bibl>
               </head>
               <pb facs="tcp:5778:4"/>
               <p>MI God I am aſhamed, and dare not lift vp mine eyes vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> my God for our wyckedneſſe is gro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wen ouer oure head, and oure treſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are waxen great vnto the Heauen euen from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme of our fathers, yea: and oureſelues alſo haue greuouſlye ſynned vnto this daie, and becauſe of oure wyckedneſſe, haue we, and both oure kynges, and our preeſtes bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuered into the hande of the Kynges of the nacions, into the ſweard, into captiuitie, into ſpoile, and into confu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion of face, as it is come to paſſe this daie. But nowe is there a lytle and ſo dayne graciouſneſſe, come frome the Lorde oure God, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſome of vs are eſcaped, that he maye geue vs a nayle in his holie place, that oure God may lyghte oure eyes, and geue vs a lytle lyfe in our bondage. For we are bond menne, and our God hathe not forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vs in oure bondage, but hathe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined mercy vnto vs in the ſyghte of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:5778:4"/> the kynges of the Perſyans, that he ſhoulde geue vs lyfe, and promote the houſe of oure God, and to ſet vp the deſolacion therof, and to geue vs an hedge in Iuda and Ieruſalem. And nowe o oure God, what ſhal we ſaye after this, for we haue forſaken thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes, whiche thou haſte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded by thy ſeruauntes &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes, and ſayde. The lande wherun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to ye goo to poſſeſſe it, is an vncleane lande, throughe the fylthyneſſe of the people of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> landes, in theyr abhomina<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cions, wherewith they haue made it full of vncleannes on euery ſyde. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore ſhall ye not geue your doughters vnto theyr ſonnes, and theyr dough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſhall ye not take vnto youre ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and ſeke not theyr peace &amp; welthe for euer that ye maye bee ſtronge, and enioye the good in the lande, and that ye and youre chyldren maye haue the inheritaunce of it for euermore. And after all this that is come vpon vs,
<pb facs="tcp:5778:5"/> becauſe of our moſte naughtie dedes and oure greate treſpace: thou oure God haſte ſpared oure wickedneſſe &amp; haſte geuen vs a delyueraunce as it is come to paſſe this daye, to the intente we ſhould not tourne backe, and lette gooe thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes: neither be ioined in matrimony with the people of theſe abhominacyons, wilte thou then bee wroth at vs, tyl we bee vtter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye conſumed, ſo that nothing remain and tyll there bee no delyueraunce? O Lorde of Iſrael thou arte ryghteous, for wee remayne yet eſcaped, as it is this daie. Beholde in thy preſence are wee in oure treſpace, for hereupon is there no ſtandyng before the.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ The praier of Nehemias for the ſin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of the people before the Lorde. <bibl>Nehem. 1.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>O Lorde God of Heauen, thou greate and terrible God, thou that kepeſt couenaunt and mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cye
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:5778:5"/> with theim that loue thee, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes: let thyne eares harken, and thyne eyes bee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, that thou mayeſt heare the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of thy ſeruaunte, whiche I praye nowe before thee day and nyghte for the children of Iſrael thy ſeruauntes and knowlage the ſynnes of the chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael, whiche we haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted againſt the. And I and my fathers haue ſynned alſo, we haue been cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt vnto thee, in that wee haue not kepte thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes, ſtatutes: and lawes, whiche thou co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeſt thy ſeruaunte Moſes. And they are thy ſeruauntes and thy people whom thou haſt deliuered through thy great power and mightye hande. I beſeche the Lorde let thyne eares bowe doune to the prayer of thy ſeruaunt: and the prayer of thy ſeruauntes: whoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre is to feare thy name. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ A confeſſyon and ſolemne prayer of the Leuites and of the churche for ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes
<pb facs="tcp:5778:6"/> with a reherſall of the benefites of God. 2. <bibl>Eſd. 9.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>LOrde, thou alone haſte made Heauen, and the Heauen of all heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, with all theyr hooſt, the earth and all that is therupon, the ſea and all that is conteyned therin: thou geueſt lyfe vnto all, and the hooſt of Heauen bowe theimſelues vnto the. Thou arte the Lorde God that haſte choſen Abram &amp; broughteſt hym oute of Vr in chaldea and calledſt hym A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham, and foundeſt his heart faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full before thee, &amp; madeſt a couenaunte with hym: to geue vnto hym and his ſede the lande of the Cananites, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thytes, Amorites, Phereſites, Iebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſytes, and Gergeſites. Thou haſte made good thy wordes, for thou arte ryghteous, and haſte conſydered the myſerye of oure fathers in Egypte, and hearde theyr complaynte by the red ſea: and ſhewedſt tokens and won<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ders vpon Pharao: and on all his ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uauntes:
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:5778:6"/> &amp; on all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of his lande For thou knoweſt that they were pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſumptuous and cruel againſt theim: &amp; ſo madeſt thou y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> a name: as it is this daye. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> red ſea dideſt thou deuide before theim: ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they went thorowe the middes of the ſea drye ſhodde. As touching theyr perſecuters thou thre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt theim into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> depe as a ſtone: in the myghtye waters, and leddeſt thy people on the daye tyme in a clowdye pyller: &amp; on the nyght ſeaſon in a pyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of fyre: to ſhewe theim lyght in the waye that they wente. Thou cameſt downe alſo vpon mounte Sinai: and ſpakeſt vnto theim from heauen: and gaueſt theim ryght iudgementes: true lawes: good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes and ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes: &amp; declaredſt vnto theim thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye Sabboth and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundedſt theim preceptes: ordynaunces and lawes: by Moſes thy ſeruaunte: &amp; gaueſt theim bread from heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> when they were hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gry: &amp; broughteſt forth water for them
<pb facs="tcp:5778:7"/> out of the rocke when thei were thyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie and promiſedſt theim, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei ſhuld gooe in, and take poſſeſſyon of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> land ouer whiche thou haddeſt lyfte vp thyne hande, for to geue theim. But they and oure fathers were proude &amp; hardnecked, ſo that they folowed not thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes, and refuſed to heare, and dyd not rem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mbre the won<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ders that thou dyddeſt for theim, but became obſtinat and heddy: inſomuch that they tourned backe to theyr bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage in theyr diſobedience. But thou my God forgaueſt, and walle graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, mercyfull, pacient, and of greate goodnes &amp; forſokeſt theim not. And though they made a molten calfe and ſayde: this is thy god, that brought y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> oute of the lande of Egypte, and dyd great blaſphemies, yet forſokeſt thou theim not in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wylderneſſe, according to thy greate mercye. And the cloudy piller departed not from theim, on the daye tyme: to leade theim the waye,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:5778:7"/> neyther the pyller of fyre in the nyght ſeaſon, to ſhewe theim lyghte in the waie that they went And thou gaueſt theim thy good ſpyryte to enfourme theim, and with helpeſt not thy Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na from theyr mouthe, &amp; gaueſt theim water when they were thurſty. Four<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie yeres longe madeſt thou prouiſion for theim in the wylderneſſe, ſo that they lacked nothynge, theyr clothes wared not olde, and theyr fete ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led not, and thou gaueſt theim kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and nacyons, and thou diuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt theim accordynge to theyr porcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſo that they poſſeſſed the lande of Sehon kyng of Eſebon, and the land of Og the kyng of Baſan. And theyr chyldren multiplyedſt thou as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of heauen, and broughteſt theim into the lande: whereof thou haddeſt ſpoken vnto theyr fathers, that they ſhoulde gooe into it, and haue it in poſſeſſyon. And the chyldrenne wente in and poſſeſſed the lande, and thou
<pb facs="tcp:5778:8"/> ſubduedſt before theim the inhaby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tauntes of the lande, euen the Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nytes, and gaueſt theim into theyr hande, and theyr kynges and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the lande, that they myght dooe with theim what they wold. So they wanne theyr ſtronge cities: and the fatte lande, and tooke poſſeſſyon of houſes that were full of all maner of gooddes, weiles dygged oute, vyne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yardes, oylegardens, and many fruct<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full trees, and they dyd eate and wer fylled, and became fatte, and lyued in welth thorough thy greate goodneſſe neuertheleſſe they were diſobedyente and rebelled againſt thee, and did caſt thy lawe behynde theyr backes, and ſlewe thy prophetes (whiche exhorted theim ſo earneſtlye that they ſhoulde conuerte vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>) and dyd great blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies, therfore thou gaueſt theim ouer, into the hande of theyr enemyes that vexed theim. And in the tyme of their trouble they cried vnto thee, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:5778:8"/> thou heardeſt theim from heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and through thy great mercy thou gaueſt theim ſauyours, whiche helped theim out of the hand of theyr enemies. But when they came to reſt, they tourned backe agayde to doo euyll before the. Therfore lefteſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> theim in the hande of theyr enemyes, ſo that they had the dominion ouer theim. So they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted and cryed vnto thee, and thou herdeſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im from heauen, and many tymes haſte y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> delyuered theim accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy greate mercy, &amp; teſtytiedſt vnto theim, that they ſhould turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne vnto thy lawe. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng thei were proude &amp; herkened not vnto thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes, but ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in thy lawes (which a man ſhould doo and liue in theim) and turned the ſhulder a waye, and were ſtyfnecked and woulde not heare. And many ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res dyddeſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> forbeare theim: and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifiedſt vnto theim through thy ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, euen by the office of the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,
<pb facs="tcp:5778:9"/> and yet woulde they not heare. Therfore gaueſt thou theim into the hande of the nacyons in the landes. But for thy great mercies ſake thou haſt not vtterly conſumed theim, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theim for thou art a gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyous and a merciful God. Now our God, thou greate God, mightye and terrible, thou that kepeſt couenaunte and mercye, regarde not a litle all the trauaile that hath happened vnto vs, and our kinges, princes, preeſtes, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes, fathers and all thy people ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens the tyme of the Kynges of Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur vnto this daye. Thou art ryghte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ouſe in all that thou haſte brought v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon vs, for y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſte dooen righte. And we on our behalfe haue been vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, our kinges, princes preeſtes and fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers haue not doone after thy lawe: nor regarded thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes and thy earneſt exhortacions, wherewith thou hacte exhorted theim, &amp; haue not ſerued thee in theyr kyngdome, and in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:5778:9"/> thy greate goodnes that thou gaueſt them, and in the large and plenteous la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de whiche y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> gaueſt them &amp; thei haue not conuerted fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their wicked woor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes. Beholde, therfore are we in bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage this daie yea euen in the lande y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou gaueſt vnto our fathers to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy the fructes and gooddes therof, behold there are we bonde me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne. And great is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> increaſe of it vnto the kyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, whom thou haſt ſet ouer vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of our ſinnes &amp; thei haue domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion ouer our bodies and cattell and wee are in greate trouble. And in all this make we a ſure couenaunt, and write it, and let our princes, Leuites and preeſtes ſeale it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ A praier of the churche for ſynnes <bibl>Sapi. 15.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>THou (O oure God) art ſwete long ſuffering and true, &amp; with mercy ordreſt thou all thynges Though wee ſynne, yet are we thyne for we knowe thy greatenes. If wee
<pb facs="tcp:5778:10"/> ſynne not, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are wee ſure that with thee wee bee allowed. For to knowe thee is perfecte righteouſnes, yea to nowe thy righteouſnes and power, is the rote of immortalite.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ An other for ſynnes. <bibl>Hiere. 3.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>LO wee are thyne, for thou art the Lorde our God, the hilles fall, &amp; all the high pride of the mountaines, but the helth of Iſraell ſtandeth vpon God our Lorde. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion hath deuoured the laboure of our fathers from our youth vp, yea their ſhepe and bullockes their ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; doughters. So dooe wee alſo ſlepe in our confuſion, and ſhame co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereth vs, for wee and our fathers e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen from our youthe vnto this daie haue ſynned againſte the Lorde oure God, and haue not obeyed the voyce the lorde of our GOD.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ The lamentacion of Hieremie for the ſynnes of the people. <bibl>Hiere. 13.</bibl>
               </head>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:5778:10"/>
               <p>PIteouſly lette me wepe, and lette the teares guſſhe oute of myne iyes. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes flocke is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, tell therfore the kyng and the rulers, humble your ſelues, ſette you doune on the earthe, for the croune of your glory ſhall fall from your hedde The citees of the ſouthe bee ſhut vp, and there is no manne to open theim All Iuda is caried awaie captiue, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> none remaineth, lift vp your iyes, and behold theim that come from the North, where is the flocke that was gyuen thee, thy noble catell, to whom wilte y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> make thy mone, when he cum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meth vpon thee for y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt taught the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thyſelf againſt thyſelf and made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maſters ouer thee. Shall not ſorowe come vpon thee, as on a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> traua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyng w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> childe? And if thou wouldeſt ſaie in thyne hearte, wherefore come theſe thynges vpon me? Surely euen for the multitude of thy wyckednes thy hynder partes and thy fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e be diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>couered.
<pb facs="tcp:5778:11"/> If the manne of Inde can chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge his ſkynne, and the cat of the mountayne her ſpottes, then maie ye that bee exerciſed in eiuill dooe good. Therfore will I ſcatter you like as the ſtouble that is taken a waie with the ſouth wynde. This ſhall bee your lot and the porcion of your meaſure, where with ye ſhall bee rewarded of me, ſaeith the Lorde, becauſe ye haue forgotten me, and putte your truſt in diſcritfull thynges. Therfore haue I turned thy clothes ouer thy hedde &amp; diſcouered thy thighes that thy priui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties might bee ſene, thy adueutry, thy deddely malice, thy beaſtlynes, &amp; thy ſhamefull horedome For vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> feldes and hilles I haue ſene thy abhomina<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cions, wo bee to thee O Hieruſalem, wilt thou not bee clenſen ſythe thou arte yet vncleane?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ The praier that Baruch preſcribed vnto the captiues in Babilon for their ſynnes. <bibl>Batuch. 23.</bibl>
               </head>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:5778:11"/>
               <p>THE Lorde our God is righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and we with our fathers are brought to open ſhame, as it is to ſee this daie. And as for theſe plages that are come vpon vs alredy the Lorde had deuiſed theim for vs yet would we not praie vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord our God, that we might euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne turne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his naughty waies. So the Lorde hath cauſed ſuche plages to come vpon vs, for he is righteous in all his woorkes, that he hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vs, whiche we alſo haue not dooe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nor herkened vnto his voyce, for to walke in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes of the Lorde, that he had giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vs. And now O Lorde God of Iſraell thou that haſt broughte thy people out of the lande of Egypte with a mightye hande, with tokens &amp; wonders with thy great power &amp; out ſtretched arme and haſt gotten thyſelf a name, as it is come to paſſe this daie. O lord our God we haue ſynned, we haue dooen
<pb facs="tcp:5778:12"/> wickedly, wee haue behaued our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues vngodly in all thy righteouſnes. Turne thy wrath fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs (we beſeche thee) for we are but a few left emong the Heathen, where thou haſt ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vs. Heare our prayers (O Lorde) &amp; our peticions, bryng vs out of cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuite for thyne owne ſake, get vs fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure in the ſight of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whiche haue led vs a waye, that all landes maye knowe, thou art the Lorde our God, and that Iſraell and his generation calleth vpon thy name, O Lorde loke doune from thy holy houſe vpon vs, encline thyne eare and heare vs. For the dedde that bee gone doune to their graues, and whoſe ſoules are out of their bodyes, geue vnto the Lord nei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther prayſe nor righteouſ makynge, but the ſoule that is vexed for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of her ſynnes, whiche walketh heuenly and weakely, whoſe iyes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynne to fayle, ſuche a ſoule gyueth the praiſe and righteouſnes vnto the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:5778:12"/> Lorde. O Lorde wee power out oure praiers before thee, and require mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye in thy ſight, O Lorde oure God, not for any godlynes of oure forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but becauſe thou haſt ſent out thy warthe and indignation vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs accordyng as thou diddeſt threaten vs by thy ſeruauntes the Prophetes ſaiyng. Thus ſaieth the Lorde, bowe doune your ſhulders and neckes, and ſerue the kynge of Babylon, and ſo ſhall ye remaine ſtill in the lande that I gaue youre fathers, if ye will not dooe this, nor heare the voyce of the Lorde your God, to ſerue the kyng of Babylon. I ſhall deſtroye you in the citees of Iuda within Hieruſalem and without, I ſhall alſo take frome you the voice of myrthe and the voice of ioye, the voyce of the brydegrome and the voyce of the bryde, and there ſhall no manne dwell any more in the lande, but thei woulde not herken vnto the voyce to dooe the kyng of
<pb facs="tcp:5778:13"/> Babylon ſeruice, &amp; therfore haſt thou performed thy wordes, that thou ſpa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keſt by thy ſeruauntes the prophetes namely that the bones of our kynges and the bones of our fathers ſhould bee tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlated forth of their place. And lo nowe are thei laide out in the hete of the ſoone, and in the colde of the night, and thei bee dedde in great my<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſery, with honger, with ſwerde with peſtile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and are cleane caſt forth. As for the temple, wherin thy name was called vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, thou haſt laied it waſt, as it is to ſee this daie, and that for the wickednes of the houſe of Iſraell &amp; the houſe of Iuda, O Lord our God thou haſte entreated vs after all thy goodnes &amp; accordyng to all thy great louing mercy, like as thou ſpakeſt by thy ſeruaunt Moſes in the daie whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou diddeſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde hym to write thy lawe before the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Iſraell ſaiyng. If ye will not harke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto my voyce, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall this greate multitude
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:5778:13"/> be turned into a very ſmal people for I will ſcatter theim abrode, notwith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtandyng I am ſure that this flocke wil not heare me, for it is an hardenec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked people but in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lande of their cap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiuite thei ſhal remembre them ſelues &amp; lerne to knowe, that I am the lorde their God. When I ſhall giue theim an hearte to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, and eares to heare: then ſhall thei praiſe me in the lande of their captiuite, and thynke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my name. Then ſhall thei turne theim from their harde backes, and from their vngodlynes. There ſhall thei remembre the thynges that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened vnto their fathers, whiche ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned againſt me. So will I bryng the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> again into the lande, whiche I promi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed with an othe vnto their fathers Abraham Iſaac and Iacob, and thei ſhalbe lordes of it, yea I will encreace theim, and not miniſhe theim. And I will make an other couenaunt with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: ſuche one as ſhall endure, namely
<pb facs="tcp:5778:14"/> that I will bee their God, and thei ſhalbe my people, and I will no more dryue my people the children of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ell out of the lande that I haue gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theim. And now O Lorde almightie: thou God of Iſraell, our ſoule that is in trouble and oure ſpirite that is vexed crie vnto thee. Heare vs (O Lorde) &amp; haue pitte vpon vs, for thou art a mercifull God, God bee graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous vnto vs for wee haue ſynned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee. Thou endureſte for euer, ſhould wee then vtterly periſhe? O Lorde almighty thou God of Iſraell heare now the praier of the dedde Iſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raelites and of their children, whiche haue ſinned before thee, and haue not harkened vnto the voyce of the Lord their God, for whiche cauſe theſe pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges hang now vpon vs Oh Lorde re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre not the wickednes of our fore<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fathers, but thynke vpon thy power and name now at this tyme, for thou art the Lorde our God, and thee (O
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:5778:14"/> Lorde) will wee praiſe. For thou haſt put thy feare in our heartes, to the in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tent wee ſhould call vpon thy name and praiſe thee in our captiuitie and that wee might turne from the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes of our forefathers that ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned before thee. Beholde wee are yet this daie in our captiuitie, where as thou haſt ſcattered vs to bee an abho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mination, curſe, and ſynne, like as it hath happened vnto our forefathers beecauſe of all their wyckednes and de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>partyng from thee, euen from thee y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> art the Lorde our GOD. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ The praier of Daniell the prophete for his owne ſynnes and for the ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the hole nacion. <bibl>Daniell. 9.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>O Lorde thou greate and feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full GOD, thou that kepeſt couenaunte and mercye with theim whiche loue thee and kepe thy commaundementes, wee haue ſynned wee haue offended, wee haue been
<pb facs="tcp:5778:15"/> diſobedient and haue gone backe, yea we haue departed from the preceptes and iudgementes, would neuer foloe thy ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes the prophetes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſpake in thy name to our kynges and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to our forefathers and to all the people of the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. O lorde righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe belongeth vnto thee, and to vs perteineth nothyng but open ſhame as it is come to paſſe this daie vnto e<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uery manne of Iuda &amp; to theim that dwell at Hieruſalem, yea vnto all Iſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raell whether thei bee farre or nighe, through out all landes, wherin thou haſt ſcatttered them becauſe of the of<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fences thei did againſt thee. O lorde vnto vs to our kynges and princes, to oure forefathers euen vnto vs all that haue offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded thee, belongeth ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhame. But vnto thee (O Lord God) pertaineth mercy &amp; forgeuenes wher as we on our behalfe are gone backe from thee, and haue not obeyed the voice of the Lord our God, to walke
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:5778:15"/> in his lawes whiche he laied before vs his ſeruauntes the prophetes, yea all Iſraell haue tranſgreſſed &amp; gone backe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy lawe, ſo that thei haue not herkened vnto thy voyce, where<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore the curſe &amp; the othe, that is writ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten in the law of Moſes the ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God, againſt whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e haue offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded, is poured vpon vs. And he hath performed his woordes, whiche he ſpake againſt vs, and againſt our iud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges that iudged vs, to bryng vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs ſuch a plage as neuer was vnder hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen, like as it is now come to paſſe in Ieruſalem, yea all this plage, as it is writen in the law of Moſes, is come vpon vs, yet we neuer made any ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before thee, O lorde, that we might tourne again fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp; thinke vpon thy trouth. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath the lord made haſt to bryng this plage vpon vs, for the lorde our God is righteous &amp; all his woorkes whiche he dooth, and the cauſe herof
<pb facs="tcp:5778:16"/> was that wee would not harken to his voice. And now O lorde our God thou that with a mightie hande haſt brought thy people out of Egypte to gette thyſelf a name (as thou haſt at this daie) wee haue ſynned O Lorde and dooen wickedly againſte all thy righteouſnes. Let thy wrothfull diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure bee tourned awaie I beſeche thee from the citee Hieruſalem thy holy hill, for through the haynous of<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fence of vs &amp; our forefathers, is Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem and thy people abhorred of all theim that are aboute vs. Nowe therfore O our God heare the praier of thy ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and let thy face ſhyne ouer thy Sanctuary that lieth waſte O my God encline thyne eare and harken, at leaſt for thyne owne ſake, open thyne iyes and ſee, how wee bee ſpoiled, and the citee deſolate, whiche is called after thy name, for wee dooe not caſt our praiers before thee in our owne righteouſnes, but onely in thy
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:5778:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> greate mercies, O lorde heare, O lord forgyue, O Lorde conſidre, tary not ouer longe but for thyne owne ſake dooe it O my God, for thy citee and thy people is called after thy name.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="prayers">
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>PRAIERS IN</hi> tyme of aduerſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and for a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes owne ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes.</head>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ The prayer of Iacob to bee delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from his brother Eſau. <bibl>Geneſis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, <add>32</add>
                  </bibl>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> GOD of my father A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham, and God of my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father Iſaac, Lorde whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che ſayde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te vnto me, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne vnto thy countrey &amp; thy kinred, and I will dooe all well with thee, I am worthy of the leaſte of all the mercies and truthe, whiche thou haſt ſhewed vnto thy ſeruaunt, for with my ſtaffe came I ouer this
<pb facs="tcp:5778:17"/> Iordane, &amp; now haue I gotten twoo droues. Deliuer me from the handes of my brother Eſau, for I feare hym leaſt he will come and ſmyte the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the children. Thou ſaideſt that thou wouldeſte ſuerly dooe me good, and wouldeſt make my ſede as the ſande of the ſea whiche cannot be numbred for multitude.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ The praier of Ioſua what tyme the people fled in the battaill. <bibl>Ioſua. 7.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>AH Lorde almightie wherefore haſt thou brought this people ouer Iordane, to deliuer vs in to the handes of the Amoretes, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroie vs. Would God we had adue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; dwelte on the other ſyde Ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan, O Lorde what ſhall I ſaie whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iſraell turneth their backes before their enemies. Moreouer the Canani<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes and all the inhabitaunces of the lande ſhall heare of it and ſhall come aboute vs to deſtroie the name of vs
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:5778:17"/> out of the world and then what wyle thou dooe vnto thy myghtie name?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ A prayer &amp; an open confeſſion of the people of Iſraell to bee delyuered from theyr enemyes. <bibl>Iudic. 10</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>WE haue ſynned agaynſt thee, for we haue forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our owne God and haue ſerued Baalim: Lorde wee haue ſynned: doo thou vnto vs, what ſoeuer pleaſe thee, and delyuer vs onlye at this tyme. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ The prayer of Samſon vnto God, that he mighte reuenge hym agaynſte the Hhiliſtines. <bibl>Iudic. 16.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>MI Lorde almighty thinke vpon me: and ſtrengthen me at this tyme one<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y O God that I may bee auenged of my enemyes, and for the loſſe of my two eyes: that I maye reuenge me ones. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ In warres againſte Turkes and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uadours, the prayer of kyng Aſa. <bibl>2. Paral. 14.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>LOrde, it is all one with thee to helpe theim that haue no power
<pb facs="tcp:5778:18"/> with few or with many. Helpe vs O Lord our God, for wee truſt to thee, &amp; in thy name be come agaynſt this mul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>titude. Thou art the Lorde our God: let no man preuail agaynſt thee. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ An other of kyng Ioſaphat. <bibl>2. Paral. 22.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>LOrde God of oure fathers, arte not thou God in heauen, &amp; ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gneſt not thou on all the kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of the heathen? And in thyne hande is power and myght, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no man can ſtande before thee. Art not y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> oure God which dydeſt caſt out y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> enhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tauntes of this lande, before thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Iſrael, and gaueſt it to the ſede of Abraham thy louer for euer? and they dwelt therin &amp; haue buylt the a temple therin vnto thy name, &amp; ſaied: when e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyl co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth vpon vs, as the ſweard of iudgement, peſtilence or honger: then yf wee ſtand before this houſe and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee (for thy name is in this hous<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and ſhal cry vnto thee in our tribulaci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:5778:18"/> thou ſhalt heare &amp; helpe. See ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore howe proudely oure aduerſaries nowe aſſaulte vs. O our God, wylt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> not iudge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? for wee haue no might agaynſt this company, that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt vs, neyther wote wee what to doo, but our eyes bee vnto thee.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ The praier of Nehemias what time the heathen defyed hym. <bibl>Nehem. 4.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>HEare O thou oure God, howe wee are deſpiſed, tourne theyr ſhame vpon theyr owne head, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou mayſt geue theim ouer vnto deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſyng in the lande of captiuitie. Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer not theyr wyckedneſſe, &amp; put not their ſynne from thy preſence, for they haue laughed to ſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>rne the buylders.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ If God ſend thee trouble either for a puniſhment of thy ſynnes, or to proue thy pacience therwith. Praye thus. <bibl>Tobia. 3.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>O Lorde thou arte ryghteous, and all thy iudgementes are trewe,
<pb facs="tcp:5778:19"/> yea all thy wayes are mercy, faythful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes &amp; iudgement. And nowe O Lorde bee myndfull of me: and take no ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geaunce of my ſynnes: neither remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber my myſdedes, neither the myſde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of my elders: for we haue not been obedyent vnto thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes therfore are wee ſpoiled brought into captiuitie: into deathe, into deriſion and ſhame vnto all nacions: amonge whome thou haſte ſcatered vs. And nowe O Lorde thy iudgementes are great: for we haue not done according to thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes: neither haue wee walked innocentlye before thee. And now O Lorde: deale with me ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng to thy wyll, and commaunde my ſpirite to bee receiued in peace: for more expedyent were it for me to dye: then to lyue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ The prayer of Manaſſes kyng of Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>da, when he was in pryſon, for remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſynnes, and for Goddes fauoure, and delyueraunce.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:5778:19"/>
                  <bibl>2. Paral. 36</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>O Lorde almyghtye, God of oure fathers Abraham, Iſaac, &amp; Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob: and of the ryghteouſe ſede of theim: whiche haſte made heauen &amp; earthe with all the ornamente therof: whiche haſte ordeyned the ſea by the worde of thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement, whiche haſt ſhut vp the depe, and haſt ſealed it for thy fearfull and laudable name: dread of all men and honorable before the face of thy vertue, the fearce an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of thy thretenyng is importunate heuy to ſynners. But the mercy of thy promeſſe is greate and vnſercheable: for thou arte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord God moſte hygh aboue all the earthe: longe ſufferyng and exceadyng mercyfull, and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunt for the malice of menne. Thou Lorde after thy goodnes haſt promy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed repentaunce of the remiſſion of ſynnes: and thou that art the God of the ryghteouſe: haſte not put repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce to the ryghteous Abraham, I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaac,
<pb facs="tcp:5778:20"/> and Iacob, vnto theim y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue not ſynned againſt thee, but becauſe I haue ſynned aboue the nombre of the ſandes of the ſea, &amp; that myne iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are multiplied. I am humblied w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> many bandes of yern. And there is in me no breathynge. I haue prouoked thine anger &amp; haue dooen euell before thee in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mittynge abhominacions &amp; multiplyeng offences, &amp; nowe I bowe the knees of my heart requiring good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of the Lord. I haue ſynned Lorde I haue ſynned and know mine iniqui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie, I deſyre thee by prayer O Lorde, forgeue me, &amp; deſtry me not with mine iniquities neither dooe thou alwayes remembre my euels to punyſhe theim, but ſaue me whiche am vnworthy af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thy great mercy and I wyl prayſe thee euerlaſtingly, all the dayes of my lyfe, for all the vertue of heauen pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth thee, and vnto thee belongeth glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie worlde withoute ende. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ The prayer of Iudith for the delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:5778:20"/> of her countrey from the tyrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <bibl>Iudith. 9.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>O Lorde God of my father Sime<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, which gaueſt hym a ſweard for a defence agaynſte the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes, that vſed violence &amp; wylfulnes and that rauyſhed thy virgin and put her to diſhoneſtye. Thou that gaueſt their wiues into a pray, &amp; theyr dough<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters into captiuitie, and all theyr pray for a ſpoyl vnto thy ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, which bare a zele vnto thee, helpe me a poore wydowe. O Lord my God, I beſeche thee, for y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt dooen all thinges euen from the begynnyng. And looke what thou haſt taken in hande and deuiſed, it euermore came to paſſe: for all thy wayes are prepared, &amp; thy iudgemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes are dooen in thy euerlaſtyng fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowlage. O looke nowe vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes of the Aſſirians, lyke as it was thy pleaſure ſometime to looke vpon the hooſt of the Egiptians, when they beyng weaponed, perſecuted thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes:
<pb facs="tcp:5778:21"/> and put theyr truſte in their charets, horſemenne, and in the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of theyr menne of warre. But thou lokedſt vpon their hooſt caſtyng a thycke darckeneſſe before theim: and when they came into the depe, the waters ouerwhelmed theim, Euen ſo Lorde let it goo with theiſe that truſt in the power and multitude of theyr menne of warre: in theyr charettes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, and ſpeares, and knowe not that thou onely arte oure God: which deſtroyeſt warres from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> begynning and that thou arte the Lorde, O lyfte vp thyne arme nowe: lyke as euer fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the begynning, &amp; in thy power bryng theyr power to noughte: cauſe theyr myghte to fall in thy wrathe. They make theyr boaſte that they wyll de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyle and vnhalowe thy Sanctuarie: waſte the tabernacle of thy name and caſte downe the horne of thyne altare with theyr ſwearde. Brynge to paſſe O Lorde: that the pryde of the enemy
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:5778:21"/> may be cut doune w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his owne ſwerd that he may bee taken with the ſnare of his eyes in me, and that thou maiſt ſmyte hym with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyppes of my loue: O geue me a ſtedfaſte mynde: that I may deſpyſe hym and his ſtrengthe, &amp; that I may deſtroye hym. This ſhall get the an euerlaſtyng memoryall: yf the hande of a womanne ouerthrowe hym, for thy power (O Lord) ſtandeth not in the powir of men: nether haſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> any pleaſure in the ſtrength of horſes There was neuer proud perſone that pleaſed thee, but in the prayer of the humble and meke hathe thy pleaſure been euermore. O y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> God of heauens: thou maker of waters: and Lorde of all creatures: heare me poore woman callyng vpon thee: and puttynge my truſte in thy mercy. Remembre thy co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenaunt, O Lorde: and miniſter wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des in my mouthe, and ſtablyſhe this deuice in my hearte, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy houſe may contynue ſtyll in holineſſe, and that al
<pb facs="tcp:5778:22"/> the heathen may knowe &amp; vnderſtand that thou arte God, and that there is none other but thou.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ An other prayer of Iudith whiles ſhe went about to ſlee the enemy Holofer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes <bibl>Iudith. 13.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>STrengthen me (God of Iſrael) and haue reſpect vnto the woor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes of my handes in this houre lyke as thou haſte promiſed, &amp; graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that by thee I may perfourme the thyng which I haue deuiſed thorowe the belefe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I haue in thee, Oh ſtren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then me I beſeche thee at this houre.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ The prayer of Mardocheus in the purſure of Haman for all the Iewes na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion. <bibl>Aeſter. 13.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>O Lord, thou valyaunt and migh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tye kyng (for all thynges are in thy power) yf thou wylte helpe and delyuer Iſrael, there is no manne can withſtande thee: for y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſte made both heauen and earth: thou art Lord of all and there is none can reſiſt thee O Lord. Thou knoweſt all, thou wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:5778:22"/> Lord it was neither of malice nor of preſumption, neither for any deſire of glori y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I would not how doune my<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe, and worſhyp the moſte proude Ha na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for I would gladly if it might haue tourned Iſraell to good, haue kyſte euen his footſteps, but I feared leaſt I ſhould haue geuen Gods glori vnto a man, &amp; becauſe I would wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyp none but only thee. And therfore O Lord, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> God and king haue mercy vpon thy people, for they ymage<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> how to bryng vs to naught, yee their deſire is ful ſet to deſtroy and ouerthrowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people that hath euer been thyne. Oh deſpiſe not thyne owne good which y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſte delyuered and brought forth of Egypte: euen for thyne owne cauſe. Heare my prayer, bee mercyful to thy people, whom thou haſt choſen for an heritage to thyſelfe. Tourne our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint &amp; ſorow into ioy, ſo as we may line. O Lord, and prayſe thy name, O Lord, ſuffer not the mouthes of theim
<pb facs="tcp:5778:23"/> that prayſe thee to bee deſtroyed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ The prayer of quene Heſter for her ſelfe and all her countrye menne. <bibl>Heſter. 13.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>O My Lorde: thou onely arte our Kyng, helpe me a deſolate wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man: which haue no helper but thee, for my miſerie and deſtruccion is harde at myne hande: of a chylde. I learned of my father, that thou tokeſt vp Iſrael out of all peoples and oure fathers out of all theyr progenitours: that they ſhuld bee thy perpetuall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritaunce: and loke what thou dyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt promyſe theim, thou haſt made it good vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Now Lorde wee haue ſynned before thee: therfore haſt thou geuen vs into the handes of our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes, becauſe wee worſhypped theyr goddes: Lorde thou are ryghteous, ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uertheleſſe, they are not ſatiſfied that they oppreſſe vs w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> moſte heuy thral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, but alſo imputing the ſtrength of theyr handes vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power of their
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:5778:23"/> ydols, they wyll chaunge thy promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: and deſtroye thyne enherytaunce and ſtoppe the mouthes of theim that prayſe thee, and quenche the glorie of thyne houſe: and thyne aulter, to open the mouthes of the heathen: that they may prayſe the power of ydols, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnifie the fleſhly kyng for euer. Lorde geue not thy ſcepter vnto theim that bee nothyng worthy: leaſt they laugh at our fall, but tourne theyr deuyce v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon theimſelues, and punyſhe hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath begoon to rage vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. Thinke vpon vs O Lord: and ſhewe thy ſelfe in the tyme of our diſtreſſe. Streng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then me O thou king of goddes, thou Lorde of all power geue me pleaſaunt ſpeche in my mouth before the Lyon. Tourne his heart to hate our enemy: to deſtroye hym &amp; all ſuche as conſent to hym. But delyuer vs w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy hande and helpe the forſaken woman which haue no helpe nor defence but onely the Lorde, thou knoweſt all: thou wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt
<pb facs="tcp:5778:24"/> I loue not the glori of the vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teous and hate the bed of the vncircu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyſed and of all heathen. Thou kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt my neceſſitie that I abhorre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken of my preeminence and worſhyp, whiche I beare vpon my heade what tyme I muſte ſhewe myſelfe &amp; bee ſeen and that I abhorre it as an vncleane clothe. Thou knoweſt alſo that I thy hande mayden haue not eaten at Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans table, and that I haue had no pleaſure in the Kynges feaſte, that I haue not dronke the drynke offrynges and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I thy handemayde haue had no ioye ſythens the day I was broughte hyther, vnto this daye but onely in thee. O Lorde, O thou God of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, O thou myghty God aboue all, heare the voyce of theim whiche haue none other hope, and delyuer vs oute of the hande of the wycked, and ryd me out of my feare. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ The oracion and bleſſynge of Iob in his moſte greuouſe aduerſytie and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:5778:24"/> loſſe of his goodes. <bibl>Iob. 1.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>IOb ſhaued his head, fell doune vpon the grounde, worſhypped God and ſaied. Naked came I oute of my mothers wombe, &amp; naked ſhall I retourne agayne. The Lorde gaue, and the Lorde hathe taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye, as it hathe pleaſed the Lorde: ſo it is dooen. Nowe bleſſed bee the name of the Lorde. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ A prayer that wee maye bee delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red frome oure aduerſaries. <bibl>Eſai. 37.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>O Lorde of Hooſtes, thou God of Iſrael which ſytteſt vpon Che<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rubin, Thou art y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> God alone of all the kyngdomes of the worlde, thou onely haſte created Heauen and earth. Encline thyne eare Lorde: and conſyder, open thyne eyes and ſee, delyuer vs frome the hande of oure aduerſaries, that all the kyngdomes
<pb facs="tcp:5778:25"/> of the earthe maye knowe, that thou onely art the Lorde. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ The prayer of Eſaye when the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were fore plaged. <bibl>Eſaye. 63.64.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>LOoke downe from heauen, &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde the dwellyng place of thy ſanctuari and thy glory, howe is it that thy gelouſye: thy ſtrengthe the multytude of thy mercyes and thy lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng kyndneſſe wyll not be entreated of vs? yet art thou oure father. Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham knoweth vs not neither was Iſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raell acquaynted with vs. But thou Lord art our father and redemer: &amp; thy name is euerlaſting. O lord wherfore haſte y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> led vs out of thy waye? wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore haſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> hardened our heartes that wee feare thee not? Bee at one w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs agayne for thy ſeruauntes ſake y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are of the generacion of thyne herytage. Thy people hath had but lytle of thy ſanctuarie in poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for our enemies haue take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it in. And we are become e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as wee were in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginning what
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:5778:25"/> time wee wer not vnder thy dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nor called not vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy name. O that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> wouldeſt cleaue the heauen in ſondre and come doune: that the mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taines might melt a waie at thy prece<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, like as an hote fyre, and that the malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous might boyle as the water dooth vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyre, wherby thy name might bee knowen emonges thyne enimies and that the Gentiles might tremble before thee. That thou mighteſt come doune with thy wounderous ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g woorkes, then ſhould thilles melte at thy precens, for ſithe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s the begynnyng of the worlde, was none (excepte thou O God) that hearde or perceiued, nei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther hath any iye ſene what y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> dooeſt for theim that put their truſte in thee Thou helpeſt hym that dooeth right with cherefulnes, and theim y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thinke vpon thy waies. But lo thou art an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie, for wee offende and haue been euer in ſynne, &amp; there is not one hole, we are all as an vncleane thyng, and
<pb facs="tcp:5778:26"/> all oure righteouſneſſes are as clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes ſtayned with the floures of a woman, wee fall euerychone as the leafe, for our ſynnes tary vs a waye as the wynde. There is no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne that calleth vpon thy name, that ſtandeth vp to take holde by thee. Therefore hydeſt thou thy face from vs, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſumeſte vs becauſe of oure ſynnes. But now O Lorde thou that are our father, wee are the claie and thou art our potter, and wee are all the worke of thyne hande. Bee not to ſore diſple<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aſed (O Lorde) and kepe not our of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences to long in thy remembraunce, but conſydre that wee all are thy peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple. The citees of the ſanctuarye lye waſte. Syon is a wyldernes and Hie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ruſalem a deſerte. Oure holye houſe whiche is our beutie, where our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers prayſed thee, is brente vp: yea all oure commodities and pleaſures are waſted awaye, wilte thou not bee entreated (LORDE) for all this?
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:5778:26"/> Wylte thou holde thy peace, and ſcourge vs ſo ſore?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ An other prayer of Hieremye. <bibl>Hieremie. 7.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>HEale me (O Lorde) and I ſhall bee hole, ſaue me and I ſhall bee ſaued, for thou arte my prayſe. Bee not thou terreble vnto me, O Lorde, for thou art he in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I hope when I am in parell, lette my perſecutors bee confounded, but not me, let theim bee afraied and not me, Thou ſhalte bryng vpon theim the tyme of their plage, and ſhall deſtroy theim right ſore. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ An other prayer of Hieremie. <bibl>Hieremie. 31.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>O LORDE thou haſt chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed me, &amp; thy chaſtenyng haue I receiued as an vntamed calf Conuerte thou me and I ſhall bee co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerted, for thou art my Lorde GOD for as ſone as thou tournedſt me I re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pented myſelf. And when I vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtode
<pb facs="tcp:5778:27"/> I ſmote vpon my thigh, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed and was, aſhamed, becauſe I ſuffered reproche of my youthe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ A prayre of Hieremie vnder the per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon of Chriſte, whiche euery Chriſten maie ſaie in tyme of aduerſite. <bibl>Lamenta. 5,</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou haſt hearde my voyce O Lorde and haſt not tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned awaie thyne eares fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my ſyngyng and criyng. Thou haſt approched vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, when I called vpon thee and haſt ſaied, feare not. Thou (O Lord) haſte mainteyned the quarell of my ſoule, and haſt redemed my life. O Lorde thou haſt ſene my blaſphemers take thou my quarel vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee. Thou haſt well conſidered how thei goo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute to dooe me harme, and that all their cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſailes are againſt me. Thou haſt hearde their deſpitefull woordes (O Lorde) yea and all their imagina<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cions
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:5778:27"/> againſt me, the lippes of myne enemies and other deuices that thei take agaynſte me, all the daie long. Thou ſeeſt alſo their ſittyng doune and their riſyng vp: thei make their ſonges of nothyng but of me. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde theim O Lorde accordyng to the woorkes of their handes. Geue theim the thyng, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their owne hearte is afraied of: euen the curſe. Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute theim, O Lorde: with thyne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignacion, and rote theim out from vnder the heauen. AMEN.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ A prayer of Hieremie in the daie of trouble, and in the deſtruccion of Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem. <bibl>Lament. 5.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>All to remembraunce O Lorde what wee haue ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fered, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider and ſee our confuſion. Oure enheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce is turned to the ſtraungers: and our houſes to foren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners wee are become carefull and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:5778:28"/> and our mothers are as the widowes. Our necke is vnder perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wee are werie and haue no reſt Oure fathers whiche now are gone haue ſynned, and wee muſt bear their wyckednes. Seruauntes haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rule of vs, and no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne deliuereth vs out of their handes. The wiues are raui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in Syon, and the maidens in the citees of Iuda. The princes are han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged vp with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hande of enemies, thei haue not ſpared the olde ſage menne Thei haue committed abhominable lecherie with young menne and the bodies are hanged vp vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> trees. The elders ſit no more to determine right and equitie, and the young me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne vſe no more plaiyng of muſyke. The ioy of our heart is gone, our merie quere is turned to mournyng. The garla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of our hedde is fallen, alas that euer wee ſynned ſo ſore. Therefore oure hearte is full of heuineſſe, and oure iyes dymme, becauſe the hill Syon is
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:5778:28"/> deſtroyed, ſo that now the foxes ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne vpon it. But thou O LORDE that remaineſt for euer more and thy ſeate worlde without ende. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wilte thou ſtill for gette vs and forſake vs ſo long? O Lorde turne thou vs vnto thee, and ſo ſhall wee bee turned. Renue our heartes as in olde tymes, naye thou haſt baniſhed vs vtterly, thou arte ſore diſpleaſed with vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ The prayer of Suſanna when ſhe was in daunger to bee rauiſhed of the twoo elders. <bibl>Daniell. 13.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Vſanna ſighed and ſaied Alas I am in diſtreſſe on euery ſyde, if I dooe this thyng it will bee my death and if I dooe it not I can<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not eſkape your handes, well: it is bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter for me to fall into youre handes withoute the deede dooyng, then to ſynne in the ſight of the Lorde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:5778:29"/>
               <head>¶ An other prayer that ſhe made, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che ſhould haue been led to deathe, <bibl>Daniell: 15,</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Euerlaſtyng God, thou ſercher of ſecretes, thou that knoweſt all thynges before thei come to paſſe, thou woteſte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei haue borne falſe witneſſe againſt me: and beholde I muſt die where as I neuer did any ſuche thynges, as theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne haue maliciouſly inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted againſt me.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ The prayer of Ionas when he was as yet in the fiſſhes bely,</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N my trouble called I vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the Lorde and he hearde me, out of the belye of hell I cried and thou heardeſte my voyce. Thou haſt caſte me doune into the depe, euen vnto the middes of the ſea and the floude com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>paſſed me aboute, yea all the waues and ſtreames of water went ouer me I thoughte I had been a caſte awaie
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:5778:29"/> out of thy ſight: but I will yet again looke towarde thy holy temple. The waters compaſſed me, euen to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very ſoule, the depe laie aboute me and the ſurges couered my hedde: I wente doune to the bottome of the hilles, &amp; was barred in with earthe for euer, but y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> O Lord my God haſt brought vp my life againe out of corrupcion. When my ſoule fainted within me, I thoughte vpon the Lorde and my prayer came vnto thee: euen vnto thy holy temple. Thei that holde of vain vanites will forſake his mercie But I will dooe ſacrifice vnto thee with the voyce of thankeſgeuyng and wil paie that I haue vooed for my ſaue garde vnto the Lorde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ The prayer of Iudas Machabeus when he ſhould encouetre with his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, <bibl>2. Macha: 4:</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>BLeſſed art thou O ſauiour of Iſrael: whiche diddeſt deſtroy
<pb facs="tcp:5778:30"/> the violente power of the gyaunt in the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of thy ſeruaunt Dauid and gaueſt the hooſte of the Heathen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hande of Ionathan the ſoonne of Saull, his weapon bearer. Putte this hooſt now into the hande of thy people Iſraell, and lette theim bee co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>founded in their multitude and horſe men. Make theim afrayed and diſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fite the boldeneſſe of their ſtrengthe that thei maie bee moued throughe their deſtruction. Caſte theim doune throughe the ſworde of thy louers, then ſhall all thei y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> knowe thy name prayſe thee for euer with thankeſge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ The prayer of the preeſtes againſte the tiraunt that he might not proſpere againſt the holines of God. <bibl>1. Macha. 7.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>FOraſmuche as thou lord God haſt choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this houſe that thy name mighte bee called vpon therein, &amp; that it ſhould bee an houſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:5778:30"/> of prayer and peticion to thy people bee auenged of this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne and of his hooſte, and lette theim bee ſlain with the ſwearde. Remembre the blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of theim, and ſuffre theim not to continue any longer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ The prayer of Nehemias and the preſtes for the people oppreſſed of the Heathen. <bibl>2. Machabe. 1.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>O Lorde God maker of all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, thou fearefull and ſtrong thou righteous and mercifull, thou that art onely a gracious kyng onely liberall, onely iuſte, almightie and euerlaſtyng, thou that deliuereſt Iſraell from all trouble, thou that haſt choſen the fathers and halowed theim: receiuyng the offeryng for the hole people of Iſraell, preſerue thine owne porcion and halowe it. Gather thoſe together that are ſcattered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade frome vs.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:5778:31"/>
               <p>Deliuer theim that are vnder the hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thens bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dage, looke vpon theim whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che are diſpiſed and abhorred, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Heathen maie knowe and ſee, how that thou art oure GOD. Puniſhe theim that oppreſſe and proudely put vs to diſhonoure. Set thy people a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in thy holy places lyke as Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes hath ſpoken. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ The prayer of Eleazar whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was drawen to execucion and redy to die, <bibl>2. Machab. 6.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>LOrde God whiche haſt the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knowelage, thou knoweſte full well y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> where as I mighte haue been deliuered from deathe, I ſuffer theſe ſore paynes of my body, but in my mynde I am well content to ſuffer theim be cauſe I fear thee.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="thanksgivings_and_praises">
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:5778:31"/>
            <head>¶ <hi>THANKESGYVYN<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges</hi> and prayſes vnto GOD, of the Fathers.</head>
            <div type="song_of_praise">
               <head>¶ The ſong of Moſes and the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Iſraell for their diliueraunce from Pharao. <bibl>Exodi. 15.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>ET VS SYNGE</hi> vnto the Lorde, for he is become glorious, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> horſe and the horſeman. The Lorde is my ſtrengthe and my ſong, and is become my ſaluacion, he is my God and I will glorifie hym, he is my fathers God and I will extolle hym vp on highe. The Lorde is as a ſtrong manne of warre, almightie is his name. Pharaos charettes &amp; his hooſte, hath he caſt in the ſea. His py<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked capitaines are drouned in the red ſea. the depe waters haue couered the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5778:32"/> thei ſounke to the botome as a ſtone. Thy hande Lorde is glorious in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, thyne hande hath all to daſſhed thyne enemies and with thy greate glory thou haſt deſtroyed thine aduer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaries. Thou ſenteſt forth thy wrath and it conſumed theim euen as ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with the brethe of thyne anger. The water gathered together and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fludes ſtode ſtill as a rocke, and the depe water congeled together in the middeſt of the ſea. The enemie ſaied I will foloe and ouer take theim and will deuide the ſpoyle, I will ſatiſfie my luſt vpon thiem, I will drawe my ſwearde, and my hande ſhall deſtroy theim. Thou blueſt with thy brethe, and the ſea couered theim, and thei ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke as lead in the mightie waters. Who is like vnto thee O Lorde emo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges the goddes? Who is like thee ſo glorious in holynes, fearefull, lauda<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble and that ſheweſt wonders?</p>
               <p>Thou ſtretchedeſt thy rightha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:5778:32"/> the earth ſwalowed theim, with mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cie thou cariedeſt this people whiche thou deliueredſt, and broughteſt thei with thy ſtrengthe vnto thyne holye habitacion. The nacions hearde, and were afraied, panges came vpon the Philiſtines. Then the Dukes the E<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>domites were amaſed, and tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blyng came vpon the mightieſt of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abites, all the enhabitauntes of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan wared fainte hearted. Let feare and dredde fall vpon theim, through thy greateneſſe of thyne arme, and let theim bee as ſtill as a ſtone, whyle thy people paſſe throughe. O Lorde, whyle thy people paſſe throughe, whiche thou haſte gotten. Brynge theim in and plante theim in the mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taines of thyne enheritaunce, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place Lorde whiche thou haſt made to dwel in, the ſanctuarye Lorde whiche thy handes haue prepared. The Lorde rai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gneth euer and alwaie. For Pharao went on horſebacke w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his charettes
<pb facs="tcp:5778:33"/> and horſemen into the ſea, &amp; the lorde broughte the waters of the ſea vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And the children of Iſraell went on drye lande through the ſea.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="blessing">
               <head>¶ The forme of bleſſyng the children of Iſraell. <bibl>Numeri. 6</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>ON this wyſe ſhall ye bleſſe the children of Iſraell and ſaie vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The Lorde bleſſe thee &amp; kepe thee. The Lorde make his face ſhine vpon thee, and bee mercifull vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to thee. The Lorde lift vp his counte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naunce vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee: and geue thee peace The preeſtes ſhall make inuocation to my name ouer Iſraell: that I may bleſſe theim.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="thanksgiving">
               <head>¶ Anna thankyng the Lord of his be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nefite, on this maner ſyngeth to God: <bibl>1. Kynges. 2.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>MY hearte reioyſeth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde myne horne is high in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde and my mouth is wyde open ouer myne enemies for I reioyſe in
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:5778:33"/> thy ſauyng. There is none ſo holy as the Lorde, no there is none ſaue thou. Neyther is there any ſtrengthe lyke vnto oure God Talke not ſo muche proudely, let olde thynges depart out of your mouthes, for the Lord is God of knowlage, and iudgeth the though<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes. The bowes of the ſtronge are bro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken and the weake endued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſtrength They that of late were full, haue let forth theim ſelues for breade, and the hungry bee ſatiſfyed, in ſo much that the baren hath borne ſeuen, and ſhe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> had many chyldren is waxed feble. The Lorde kylleth and quickeneth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, he bryngeth downe to hell, and fetteth vp agayn. The Lorde maketh poore and maketh eych, bryngeth low and heueth vp on hygh, he rayſeth vp the poore out of the duſte, and lyfteth vp the beggar frome the donge hyll, to ſette hym amongeſt Prynces, and make hym holde the ſeate of glorye. For the pyllers of the earthe are the
<pb facs="tcp:5778:34"/> Lordes, and he hathe ſette the rounde worlde vpon theim. He wyll kepe the fete of his ſainctes, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wycked ſhal kepe ſilence in darkeneſſe. For in his owne myghte ſhall no man bee ſtrong The Lordes aduerſaryes ſhall bee made to feare hym and oute of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſhal thunder vpon theim. The lord ſhall iudge the coaſtes of the worlde, and ſhall geue myght vnto his kyng, and exalte the horne of his Chriſt. Am<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ For benefytes receyued at Goddes hande, the prayer of Dauid. <bibl>2. Reg. 7.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>WHat am I Lorde almighty and what is my houſe: that thou ſhuldeſt thus auaunce me? And is this a ſmall thynge, in thy ſyghte? Lorde almyghty? but that thou woul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deſte ſpeake alſo of thy ſeruauntes houſe for a greate whyle to come? Is this a lawe amonge menne. Lorde al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myghty? And what can Dauyd ſaye more vnto thee, ſeynge thou knowe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:5778:34"/> thy ſeruaunt Lorde almyghty. Euen for thy woordes ſake, and a cordyng to thyne owne heart, haſte thou dooen all theſe great thynges to make theim knowen vnto thy ſeruaunt, wherfore thou arte greate: O Lorde God, and there is none lyke thee, nether is there any God ſaue thou, acordyng to all that wee haue heard with oure eares. And what one people in the earthe is lyke thy people Iſraell, whiche God went to delyuer to bee his people, and too make hym a name, and to ſhewe theim greate and terrible thynges in the earthe, before thy people: whiche thou redemedeſt to thee out of Egypt euen for the people and for theyr god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. And thou haſte ordeyned thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Iſraell to bee thy people for euer. And thou Lorde arte theyr God, and now Lord God, the thing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou haſt ſaied of thy ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and of his houſe make it good for euer, and dooe as thou haſte ſaied. And let thy name bee
<pb facs="tcp:5778:35"/> greate for euer, that men may ſay, the Lord of hooſtes is the God of Iſrael, and let the houſe of thy ſeruaunt Da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uid bee ſtablyſhed before thee. For y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> Lorde of hooſtes, God of Iſrael, haſt tolde in the eare of thy ſeruaunt ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I wyll buylde thee an houſe. And therfore hathe thy ſeruaunte founde in his hearte to praye this prayer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nowe Lorde almyghty, thou arte the God and thy woordes muſte bee true for thou haſt tolde this good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe vnto thy ſeruaunt, and now goo to: and bleſſe the houſholde of thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt, that it maye contynue for euer before thee. For thou Lorde almighty haſte ſaied that with thy bleſſyng the houſe of thy ſeruaunte ſhall bee bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for euer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="song_of_praise">
               <head>¶ A ſonge that Dauid ſaunge vnto the Lorde in the daye that the Lorde dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered hym our of the hande of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:5778:35"/>
                  <bibl>2. Reg. 22.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>THe Lord is my rocke, my caſtle and my delyuerer, God is my ſtrength and in him wyl I truſt my ſhylde, and the horne that defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth me, myne hygh helde and refuge O my ſauyour ſaue me from wronge I wyll prayſe and call on the Lorde, and ſo ſhall I bee ſaued from my ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes, for the waues of deathe haue cloſed me aboute, and the floudes of Belial haue feared me, the corde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of hell haue compaſſed me aboute, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſnares of death haue ouertaken me in my tribulacion. I called to the Lorde, and cryed to my God, and he hearde my voyce oute of his temple, and my cry entred into his eares. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth trymbled and quoke, and the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyons of Heauen moued and ſhooke: becauſe he was angrye. Smoke went oute of his noſethrylles, and conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng fyre out of his mouthe, that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les were kyndled of hym, and he bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed
<pb facs="tcp:5778:36"/> the heauen and came downe, and darkneſſe vnderneth his fete And he code vpon Cherub and flewe, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peered vpon the wynges of the wynd and he made darkeneſſe a tabernacle rounde about hym with water gathe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red together in thicke cloudes. Of the bryghtneſſe that was before hym, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les were ſet on fyre. The Lorde thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred from heauen, and the moſt highe put oute his voyce, &amp; he ſhot arrowes and ſcatered theim, and hurled lyghte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyng and turmoyled theim. The bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſea appeered, and the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacyons of the worlde were ſeen, by reaſon of the rebukyng of the Lorde, and through blaſtyng of the brethe of his noſethrylles, he ſente from aboue and fette me, and plucked me oute of myghty waters. He delyuered me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my myghty enemy &amp; from theim that hated me and were to ſtronge for me, when they had compaſſed me in the day of my tribulacion, the Lorde ſtay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:5778:36"/> me vp, and broughte me oute into roumth: and delyuered me becauſe he delyghted in me. The Lord rewarded me accordynge to my ryghteouſneſſe, and a cordyng to the pureneſſe of my handes he delte with me. For I kepte the wayes of the Lorde, &amp; dyd no wyc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kedneſſe forſakyng my God. But I had all his lawes in my ſyghte, and tourned my face from none of his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynaunces. I was pure vnto hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, and kepte myſelfe from wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe. And the Lorde dyd to me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine a cordyng to my ryghteouſneſſe and after my pureneſſe that I had in his ſyght, with the holy thou ſhalt bee holy, and with the man that is vncor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupte, thou ſhalt bee vncorrupt, with the pure, thou ſhalte bee pure, &amp; with the froward thou ſhalte bee froward alſo. Certaynly the people that are in aduerſitie thou ſhalt helpe, and on the proude ſhalte thou caſte thyne eyes. Thou art my light, o Lord: &amp; the Lord
<pb facs="tcp:5778:37"/> ſhall lyght my darkeneſſe, with thyne helpe. I wyll runne through an hooſt of men and by the ayde of my God, I wyll ſpryng ouer a wall. The way of God is vndefyled, and the woorde of the Lorde fyned as golde, &amp; he a ſhilde to all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> truſt in hym. Who is a God ſaue the Lorde, and who mighty ſaue our God? God is my ſtrength in war and ryddeth the way clere before me. He maketh my fete as ſwyfte as an hyndes, and ſetteth my fete faſt vpon my hygh holde. He teacheth my han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des to fyght, that a bowe of braſſe is to weake for myne armes. And thou haſt ſaued me with thy ſhylde, and ke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peſt me euer in mekeneſſe. Thou ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt me ſpace to walke in, that my fete ſhould not ſtumble. I folowed myne enemyes and deſtroyed theim: &amp; tour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned not againe vntyl I had conſumed theim. I waſted theim and ſo clouted theim, that they coulde not aryſe, but fell vnder my fete, and thou compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redeſt
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:5778:37"/> me aboute with myghte to bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayle, and madeſt theim that roſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt me: to ſtoupe vnder me. Thou madeſt myne enemyes to tourne their backes to me, and theim that hated me, and I deſtroyed theim: they loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for helpe, but none came to ſaue theim, vnto the Lorde they cryed, but he hearde theim not. And I wyll beat theim as ſmal as the duſt of the earth and wyll ſtampe theim as the durte in the ſtrete, and wyll ſprede theim a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade, Thou delyueredſt me frome the diſſencion of my people, and kepſt me to bee an heade ouer nacions, for the people whiche I knewe not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came my ſeruauntes, and the alientes crouched vnto me and obeyed me at a woorde and the alientes that ſhrynke awaye ſhall tremble for feare in theyr defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſed places. The Lord lyueth, and bleſſed be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he my ſtrengthe, and exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted bee God the ſtrengthe that ſaueth me. It is GOD that auengeth me,
<pb facs="tcp:5778:38"/> and that bryngeth downe the people vnder me, and delyuereth me frome my ennemyes, thou lyfteſt me vp on hyghe from theim that ryſe agaynſte me, and delyuereſt me frome the wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked menne. Therfore I wyll prayſe thee, O Lorde amonge the heathen, and wyll ſynge vnto thy name. For thy greate and manyfolde ſauyng of thy kyng, ſhewyng mercy vnto thyne annoynted, euen vnto Dauid and his ſede for euer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="blessing">
               <head>¶ A bleſſynge of Tobias the elder, wherewith he bleſſed the Lorde in the ende of his lyfe. <bibl>Tobi. 13.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>GReate arte thou, O Lorde, for euermore, and thy kyngedome worlde without ende. For thou ſcourgeſt and healeſt, thou leadeſt vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to hell and bryngeſt out agayne. And there is none that maye eſcape thyne hande. O ye chyldren of Iſrael: geue thankes vnto the Lorde, and prayſe
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:5778:38"/> hym in the ſyghte of the heathen. For among the heathen which know hym not, hath he ſcatered you, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye ſhould ſhewe forth his meruelous workes, &amp; cauſe theim to knowe, there is none other GOD almyghtie, but he. He hath chaſtened vs for our myſdedes: and for his owne mercyes ſake ſhall he ſaue vs. Conſyder then howe he hath dealt with you, and prayſe hym with feare and drede, and magnifie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euerlaſting kyng in your wordes. Cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes I wyll prayſe hym euen in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place of my captiuitie, for he hathe ſhewed his maieſtie, vnto a ſynfull people. Tourne you therfore, O ye ſynners, &amp; doo ye ryghteouſnes before God, tru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtyng verely he wyll ſhewe his mercy vpon you Certes I and my ſoule wyl reioyce in God, prayſe the Lorde all ye his choſen, holde the dayes of glad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, and bee thankeful vnto hym. Oh my ſoule bleſſe thou the Lorde. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="song_of_thanksgiving">
               <head>¶ The thankeſgeuing and ſonge of Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dith
<pb facs="tcp:5778:39"/> for the victory &amp; for the delyuery of the countrey from theyr enemies. <bibl>Iudith. 16.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>BEgyn vnto the Lorde vpon the tabrettes, ſynge vnto the Lorde vpon the Cymbales, ſynge vnto hym a newe ſonge of thankeſgeuyng bee ioyful and call vpon his name. It is the Lorde that deſtroyeth warres, euen the Lorde is his name, whiche hath pytched his tentes in the mydſt of his people, that he myghte delyuer vs from the hande of all our enemyes Aſſur came out of the mountaynes in the multitutde of his ſtrength, his peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple ſtopped the water brookes, &amp; theyr horſes couered the valleyes. He pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to haue brent vp my lande, and to ſley my yong men with the ſweard He would haue caried away my chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and virgines into captiuitie, but the almyghtye Lorde anneyed hym, and delyuered hym into the handes of a womanne, whiche broughte hym to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:5778:39"/> confuſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For theyr myghty was not deſtroyed of the yong menne It was not the ſonnes of Tiran that ſlewe hym, neyther haue the greate gyaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ſette theim ſelues agaynſte hym, but Iudith the doughter of Merari: with her fayre beawtye diſcomfyted hym and broughte hym to naughte. She layde downe her wydowes ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell, and decked herſelfe with the tyre of myrthe in the reioyſyng of the chyldren of Iſraell. She annoynted her face, ſhe bounde vp her heare to begyle hym, her ſlyppers rauyſſhed his eyes, her beawtye raptiuated his mynde, with the ſwearde ſmote ſhe of his necke. The Perſyans were aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed at her ſtedfaſtneſſe, and the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des at her boldneſſe. Lette vs ſyng a ſonge of thankeſgeuyng vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord A new ſonge of prayſe wyll wee ſyng vnto our God, Lorde Lorde: thou art a greate God, myghtye in power, whome no manne may ouercome. All
<pb facs="tcp:5778:40"/> thy creatures ſhoulde ſerue thee, for thou ſpeakeſt but a woorde, and they were made: thou ſenteſt thy ſpirite, and they were created, and no manne can withſtande thy voyce. The moun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taynes ſhall moue frome the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyons with the waters, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtony rocke ſhal melte before thee: lyke waxe. But they that feare thee ſhall bee great w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thee in all thynges, woo vnto the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple that ryſe vp agaynſte my genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion. For the almyghty Lorde wyll a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge hymſelfe of theim, and in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day of iudgement wyll he vyſet theim.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="blessing">
               <head>¶ The bleſſyng of Seraphin. <bibl>Eſay. 9.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>HOly arte thou, holy arte thou, holy art thou, thou art the Lord God of Hooſtes: all the earth is full of thy glorie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="thanksgiving">
               <head>¶ Thankynges. <bibl>Eſay. 25.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>O Lorde, thou art my God: I wyll prayſe thee: &amp; magnifie thy name
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:5778:40"/> for thou bryngeſt meruelouſe thinges to paſſe, a cordyng to thine olde coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayles truly and ſtedfaſtly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="thanksgiving">
               <head>¶ An other of the ſame. <bibl>Eſay. 26.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>O Lorde geue vs peace, for y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt in vs all oure woorkes. O Lorde our God, thoughe ſuche lordes haue dominacion vpon vs: as knowe not thee, yet graunte: that wee maye hope onely in thee: and kepe thy name in remembraunce.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="blessing">
               <head>¶ A bleſſing with an admiracion of the meruelouſe counſayles of God. <bibl>Iere. 32.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>O Lorde God, it is thou that haſte made heauen &amp; earthe with thy great power and hygh arme: and there is nothyng to hard for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>. Thou ſheweſt mercy vpon thouſandes: thou dooeſt recompenſe the wickednes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fathers: into the boſome of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> children that come after theim. Thou arte the great &amp; mighty God: whoſe name is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5778:41"/> Lorde of hooſtes great in councel, and infinite in thought. Thyne eyes looke vpon all the wayes of mens chyldren to reward euery one after his waye, and accordyng to the fructes of his in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uencions. Thou haſt dooen great to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens and wonders in the lande of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gipt vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of Iſrael: to make thy name great, as it is come to paſſe this day: Thou haſt brought thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Iſrael out of the land of Egipt with tokens, with wonders, with a myghtye hande, with a ſtretched oute arme, and with great terriblenes, and haſte geuen theim this lande: lyke as thou haddeſt promyſed vnto theyr fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Namely, that thou wouldeſt geue theim a lande, that floweth with mylke and honey. Nowe when they came therin and poſſeſſed it, they fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed not thy voyce, and walked not in thy lawe, but all that thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeſt theim to doo, that haue not they dooen. And therfore come all
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:5778:41"/> theſe plag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s vpon theim. Beholde there are bulwarkes now againſte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> citee to take it and it is wonne of the Caldes, that beſege it with ſwearde with honger and deathe, and what ſoeuer thou haſt ſpoken that ſame is come vpon theim.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="song_of_thanksgiving">
               <head>¶ The ſonge and thankeſgyuyng of Mary the virgyne. <bibl>Luke. 1.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>MI ſoule magnifieth the Lorde, &amp; my ſpirite reioyſeth in God my ſauiour For he hath loked vpon the poore degre of his hande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maide. Behold now from henſeforth ſhall all generacions call me bleſſed, for he that is mightie hath dooen to me greate thynges, and holy in his name And his mercie is on theim y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> feare hym throughout al generacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s He ſheweth ſtrengthe with his arme he ſcatereth theim that are proude in the imaginacion of their heartes. He putteth doune the mighty from their
<pb facs="tcp:5778:42"/> ſeates, he exalteth theim of lowe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree. He fillith the hungry with good thynges, and ſendeth a waie the riche emptie. He remembreth mercye: and helpeth his ſeruaunt Iſraell. Euen as he promiſed to our fathers: Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham and to his ſede for euer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prophecy_and_thanksgiving">
               <head>¶ The propheſie and gyuyng of than<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes of Zachary. <bibl>Luke. 1.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>BLeſſed bee the Lorde God of Iſraell, for he hath viſited &amp; redemed his people. And hath raiſed vp an horne of ſaluacion vnto vs in the houſe of his ſeruaunt Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid. Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as he promiſed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouth of his holy prophetes, whiche were ſythens the worlde begonne that wee ſhould bee ſaued from oure enemies and from the handes of all that hate vs. To fulfill the mercie promiſed to our fathers and to remembre his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye couenaunte. And to performe the othe whiche he ſware to oure father
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:5778:42"/> Abraham to geue vs, that wee dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered out of the handes of our enemi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es, mighte ſerue hym without feare, all the daies of our life, in ſuche holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and righteouſnes as is accepte before hym. And thou childe ſhalt bee called the prophete of the higheſt and thou ſhalte goo before the face of the Lorde to prepare his waies. And to geue knowelage of ſaluacion vnto his people for the forgeuenes of ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Throughe the tendre mercie of our God, wherby the daye ſpryngeth from an highe hath viſited vs. To geue light to theim that ſatte in dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keneſſe and in ſhadowe of death, and to guyde oure fete into the waye of peace.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="angelic_praises">
               <head>¶ The prayſes of the angelles at the birth of Chriſte. <bibl>Luke. 2.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>GLORI vnto God on highe and peace on the earthe, vnto menne reioyſyng.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="thanksgiving">
               <pb facs="tcp:5778:43"/>
               <head>¶ Gyuyng of thankes of Symeon. <bibl>Luke. 1.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>LORDE, now letteſte thou thy ſeruaunt departe in peace acordyng to thy promiſe, for myne iyes haue ſene the ſauiour ſent from thee, whiche thou haſt prepared before the race of all people. A lighte to lighten the Gentyles, and the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of thy people Iſraell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="thanksgiving">
               <head>¶ Thankes of Paull for his conuerſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on vnto Chriſte. <bibl>1. Timothi. 1.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>VNto GOD kyng euerlaſtyng immortall, inuiſible, and wyſe onely but honoure and prayſe for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="song_of_triumph">
               <head>¶ A ſong of the triumphers ouer the beaſte <bibl>Apoca. 15.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>GReate and meruelouſe are thy woorkes, Lorde God almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, iuſt and true are thy waies kyng of ſainctes. Who ſhall not fear O Lorde, and glorifie thy name? For
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:5778:43"/> thou onely art holy, and all Gentiles ſhall come and worſhippe before thee for thy iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes are made manifeſt</p>
            </div>
            <div type="blessing">
               <head>¶ A bleſſyng of the people by kyng Salomon. <bibl>3. Kynges. 8.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>BLeſſed bee the Lorde, that hath gyuen reſt vnto his people Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell accordyng to all that he promiſed, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is not one worde eſcaped of all the good promiſes whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che he promiſed by the hande of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes his ſeruaunt. And the Lorde oure God bee with vs as he was with our fathers and forſake vs not, neyther leue vs, but he may bowe our heartes vnto hym, to walke in al his waies &amp; to kepe his commaundementes, ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunces, and cuſtomes whiche he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded our fathers. And theſe my woordes whiche I haue prayed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lorde, bee nighe vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde our God daie and nighte, that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende the quarell of his ſeruaunt and
<pb facs="tcp:5778:44"/> of his people Iſraell euermore, that all nacions of the earth maie knowe that the Lorde he is God, and none o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther but he, and I praye God that youre heartes maie bee founde with the Lorde oure God, to walke in his ordinaunces and to kepe his lawes as wee dooe this daie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="canticle">
               <head>¶ The bleſſyng and prayſes of ſaincte Ambroſe and Auguſtyne. Te Deum laudamus.</head>
               <p>WE prayſe thee (Oh Lorde) wee knowelage thee to bee y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde All the earth mought worſhip thee whiche art y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father euerlaſtyng To thee crieth forth all angelles, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>auens and all the powers therin. To thee thus crieth Cherubin and Sera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phin continually, holy art thou, holy art thou, holy art thou. Thou art the Lorde God of hooſtes. Heauen and earthe are fulfilled with the glory of thy maieſti. The glorious compaigne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles praiſe thee. The good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:5778:44"/> feloſhippe of the propheies praiſe thee. The fayre felo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhippe of Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters prayſe thee. The holy congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of the faithefull throughout all the world magnifie thee. Thei know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lage thy honorable and verie onelye ſoonne. The knowelage the holye ghoſte to bee a conforter. Thou arte the kyng of glorie O Chriſte. Thou arte the euerlaſtyng ſoonne of the fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther. Thou (whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou ſhouldeſt take vpon thee oure nature, to delyuer manne) diddeſt not abhorre the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins wombe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou haddeſt ouer come the ſharpenes of deathe, thou o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peneddeſt the kyngdome of heauens to theim that beleued in thee. Thou ſitteſt on the righte hande of God in the glorie of the father. Wee beleue y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt come to bee our iudge, where<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore wee praye thee help thy ſeruaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou haſt redemed with thy precious bloud. Make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to bee no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy ſaintes in ioy euerlaſting
<pb facs="tcp:5778:45"/> O Lord ſaue thy people, &amp; bleſſe thine heritage. Gouerne and alſo lift theim vp into bleſſe euerlaſtyng, wee praiſe thee euery daie, and wee worſhippe thy name euer worlde without ende. O Lorde lette it bee thy pleaſure to kepe vs this daie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſynne. O Lorde haue mercie v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon vs, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as mee truſt in thee In thee O lorde dooe I truſt let me not bee confounded for euer Amen</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="prayers">
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:5778:45"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>PRAIERS FOR</hi> SVC<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cours and reliefes of life, for wyſedome, for hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mylitie and for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall gif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</head>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ The requeſt of Iacob for ſuſtentacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and reliefe of this preſent life. <bibl>Geneſis. 28.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F THE LORDE</hi> will bee with me and will kepe me in the waie that I ſhall walke in, &amp; will geue me breade to eate and clothe to weare and that I maie returne again vnto my fathers houſe in ſauerie: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall the Lorde bee my God, and this ſtone whiche I haue ſette vp an ende, ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bee godes houſe, and of all that thou ſhalte geue me, will I geue the tenth vnto thee.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:5778:46"/>
               <head>¶ Thus prayed Anna vnto the Lorde that ſhe might obtein a childe. <bibl>1. Kynges. 1.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>LORDE of hooſtes, if thou wilt looke on the wretchednes of thyne handmaide, and ſhalt remembre me, and not forgette thyne handmaide, and ſhall geue thyne ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d maide a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne childe: I will geue him vnto the Lorde all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daies of his life.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ The prayer of Salomon for wyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome well to gouerne his people, daie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to bee prayed of all princes &amp; other rulers. <bibl>3. Kynges. 3.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>THou haſt ſhewed vnto thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt Dauid my father great mercy, acording as he walked before thee in trouth, in righteouſnes and in playneſſe of hearte with thee, And thou haſte kepte for hym this greate mercie, that thou haſte geuen hym a ſoonne to ſit on his ſeate. And now Lorde my God, it is thou that haſte made thy ſeruaunte kyng in
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:5778:46"/> the rou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of Dauid my father, and I am a young lad and wote not how to ordre myſelf. And thy ſeruaunte is in the middeſt of thy people whiche thou haſt choſen, a people that are ſo many, that thei cannot bee nombred for multitude, geue therefore thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunte an vnderſtandyng hearte to iudge thy people &amp; to deſerue betwne good and bad, for who is able to iud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge this thyne ſo greate a people?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ A prayer of Salomon for a compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency of life. <bibl>Prouerbes. 30.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>TWo thynges I require of thee that thou wilt not denie me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I die. Remoue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie and lies, geue me nether pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie nor riche, onely graunt me a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarye liuyng, leaſt if I bee to full, I mought happely denie thee, and ſaie what feloe is the Lorde, or conſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned through pouertie, I mought fall vnto ſtealyng, &amp; forſweare the name of my God. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:5778:47"/>
               <head>¶ A prayer for obteinyng of Wiſedome <bibl>Sapienſe. 9.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>GOD of my fathers, and Lorde of mercies, thou haſt made all thynges with thy woorde, and ordained manne throught thy wyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, that he ſhould haue dominion ouer the creature whiche thou haſte made, that he ſhould ordre the worlde acordyng to equitie and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and execute iudgemente with a true hearte, geue me wyſedome, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is euer aboute thy ſeate, and put me not out from emong thy children. For I thy ſeruaunte and ſoonne of thy handemayde am a feble perſone, of a ſhort tyme, and to young to the vnderſtandyng of iudgement and of thy lawes. And thoughe a manne hee neuer ſo perfect emong the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of menne, yet if thy wyſedome bee not with hym, he ſhalbee nothyng worth Oh ſende her out of thy holy heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and from the trone of thy maieſtie, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:5778:47"/> ſhe maie bee with me &amp; laboure with me that I maie knowe what is accep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>table in thy ſighte. For ſhe knoweth and vnderſtandeth all thynges, and ſhe ſhall conducte me ſobrely in my woorkes, and preſerue me in her po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer. So ſhall my woorkes bee accep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>table. AMEN.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ A prayer for mekenes and the obtei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng of chaſtitie. <bibl>Eccle. 23.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>O LORDE thou father and God of my life, lette me not haue a proud loke. But tourne a waie all volupteouſnes from me. Take from me the luſtes of the body lett not the deſyres of vnclennes take holde vpon me, and geue me not ouer into an vnſhamefaſte and obſtinate mynde. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ The prayer of Ieſus the ſoonne of Syrache, in neceſſitie &amp; for wiſedome. <bibl>Eccle. the laſte.</bibl>
               </head>
               <pb facs="tcp:5778:48"/>
               <p>I Thanke thee O Lorde &amp; kyng and praiſe thee O God my ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour I will yelde prayſes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy name, for thou art my defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and helper from the ſnare of trai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tours tou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gues, and from theim that are occupied in lies. Thou haſte been my helper from ſuche as ſtode vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte me, and haſte deliuered me a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cordyng to the multitude of thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, &amp; for thy holy names ſake. Thou haſte deliuered me from the roaryng of theim that prepared theimſelues to deuoure me, out of thy handes of ſuche as ſoughte after my life from the multitude of theim that troubled me and wente aboute to ſette fyre v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon me on euery ſyde, ſo that I was not brente in the middes of the fyre. From the depe of hell, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an vnclene toungue, from liyng woordes from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked kyng, and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnrighteouſe toungue. My ſoule ſhall prayſe the Lorde vnto deathe, for my life drewe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nie
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:5778:48"/> vnto hell. Thei co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſed me rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de aboute on euery ſyde, and there was no manne to help me. I looked about me if there were any manne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> would ſuccoure me, but ther was none. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thought I vpon thy mercie O Lorde and vpon thy actes that thou haſte dooen euer of olde, namely that thou deliueredeſt ſuche as putte their truſt in thee, &amp; riddeſt theim out of the han<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des of the Heathen Thus lifted I vp my prayer from the earth, and praied for deliueraunce from deathe, I cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vpon the Lorde my father, that he would not leaue me without help in the daie of my trouble, and in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme of the proude. I prayſed thy name co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinually yeldyng honoure and than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes vnto it, and ſo my prayer was harde. Thou ſauedeſt me from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and deliueredeſt me from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnrighteouſe tyme. Therefore will I acknowelage, and prayſe thee, and magnifie the name of the LORDE
<pb facs="tcp:5778:49"/> When I was yet but young, or cun I went a ſtraye, I deſired wyſedome openly in my prayer. I came therfore before the temple and I ſoughte her verie buſyly. The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> floriſhed ſhe vnto me, as a grape that is ſone rype. My hearte reioyſed in her, then went my fote the right waie, yea fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my youth ſoughte I after her, I bowed doune myne eare &amp; receiued her. I tounde in my ſelf muche wyſedome and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red greately in her. Therefore will I aſcribe the glorye vnto hym that ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth me wyſedome, for I am aduiſed to dooe therafter, I will bee gelouſe to cleue vnto the thyng that is good ſo ſhall I not bee confounded. My ſoule hath wreſſtled with her, and I haue been di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igent to bee occupied in her I lifte vp myne handes on highe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was my ſoule lightened through wyſedome, that I knowelaged my fooliſhnes. I ordred my ſoule after her, ſhe and I were one hearte from
<pb facs="tcp:5778:49"/> the begynnyng, and I founde her in clenneſſe: and therfore ſhall I not bee forſaken. My hearte longed after her and I gat a good treaſure. Thorowe her the Lorde hathe geuen me a newe tongue: wherwith I wyll prayſe hym Oh come vnto me ye vnlearned, and dwell in the houſe of wyſdome, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawe not youreſelues from her, but talke and comen of theſe thynges: for your ſoules are very thurſtye. I ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned my mouthe and ſpake. Oh come and bye wyſdome withoute money, bowe downe youre necke vnder her yoke: and your ſoule ſhal receiue wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: ſhe is hard at hande and is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to bee found. Beholde with your eyes, howe I haue had but lytle la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure: and yet haue founde much reſt. Oh receyue wyſdom, and ye ſhal haue plenty of ſyluer and golde in poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Lette youre mynde reioyſe in his mercye: and bee not aſhamed of his prayſe: woorke his woorke by tymes
<pb facs="tcp:5778:50"/> and he ſhall geue you youre rewarde in due tyme.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ The prayer of Abacuc Prophete for ignorauncy. <bibl>Abacuc. 3.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>O Lorde when I heard ſpeake of thee, then I was afrayed. The woorke that thou haſt taken in hande, ſhalte thou perfourme in his tyme. Oh Lorde when thy tyme com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth: thou ſhalt declare it. In thy ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wrathe thou thynkeſt vpon mercy. The Lorde God is my ſtrengthe: he ſhall make my feate as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feete of har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and he whiche geueth the victorie ſhall bryng me to my hye places ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyng vpon my pſalmes. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Pater_Noster">
               <head>¶ The prayer of our Lord Ieſus which he taughte his diſcyples, <bibl>Math. 6.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>OVr father whiche art in heauen halowed bee thy name. Thy kyngdome come. Thy wyll bee doen in earth as it is in heauen. Geue
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:5778:50"/> vs this day our dayly bread. And for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geue vs our treſpaces, as we forgeue theim that treſpace againſte vs. And lette vs not bee led into temptacion. But delyuer vs from euell: for thyne is the kyngdome, and the power: and the glorie for euer. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ A prayer of the faythfull congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion that they maye ſpeake the woorde of God boldly. <bibl>Actes. 4.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>LOrd thou art God, which haſt made heauen &amp; earthe, the ſea &amp; all that in theim is, which by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouth of thy ſeruaunte Dauid haſte ſaied: why dyd the heathen rage, &amp; the people ymagyne vayne thynges? The kynges of the earth ſtoode vp &amp; the ru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lers came together agaynſt the Lorde and agaynſt Chriſte. For of a truthe agaynſt this holy chyld Ieſus, whom thou haſt anoynted: both Herode and alſo Pontius Pylate with the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyles &amp; the people of Iſrael gathered
<pb facs="tcp:5778:51"/> theim ſelues together, to dooe euen what ſoeuer thyne handes and thy counſayle determined before to bee dooen. And nowe Lorde beholde theyr threatenynges, and graunte vnto thy ſeruauntes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al confidence to ſpeake thy woorde, and that thou ſtretche forthe thyne hande to the intente that healyng: ſignes &amp; wonders maye bee dooen by the name of thy holy chylde Ieſus. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ A prayer of Chriſte vnto his father for his lytle ones whiche truſt and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe theimſelues vpon hym. <bibl>Iohan. 17.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>FAther the houre is come, glorifie thy ſonne: that thy ſonne maye glorifie thee: as thou haſt geuen hym power ouer all fleſhe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhould geue euerlaſtyng lyfe, to as many as thou haſte geuen hym. This is lyfe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtyng: that they myghte knowe thee that onely very God and whome thou haſte ſent Ieſus Chriſte. I haue glorified thee on the earthe. I haue
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:5778:51"/> finyſhed the woorke, whiche y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> gaueſt me to doo. And now glorifie me, thou father: w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thyne owne ſelfe, with the glorie which I had with thee eare the world was. I haue declared thy name vnto the menne whiche thou gaueſt me of the worlde. Thyne they were, and thou gaueſt theim me, and they haue kepte my ſayenges. Nowe they knowe that all thynges what ſoeuer thou gaueſt me, are of thee, for I haue geuen vnto theim the woordes which thou gaueſt me, &amp; they haue receyued theim, and know ſurely, that I came out from the, &amp; they beleued that thou dedeſt ſende me. I pray for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. I pray not for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde, but for theim which thou haſt geuen me, for they are thine and all myne are thyne, and thyne are myne, and I am glorified in theim. And nowe am I no more in the worlde but they are in the worlde: and come vnto thee. Holye father kepe in thyne owne name theim whiche thou haſte
<pb facs="tcp:5778:52"/> geuen me, that they maye bee one: as wee are, whyle I was with theim in the world. I kepte theim in thy name Thoſe that thou gaueſt me haue I kepte, and none of theim is loſte: but that loſte chylde, that the Scripture myghte bee fulfylled. Nowe come I to thee: and theſe woordes ſpake I in the worlde, that they myght haue my ioye full in theim. I haue geuen theim thy woordes, and the worlde hathe hated theim, euen as I am not of the worlde. I deſyre not that thou ſhouldeſt take theim out of the world but that thou kepe theim frome euell. They are not of the worlde: as I am not of the worlde. Sanctifie theim with thy trouthe. Thy ſayeng is true As thou ſenteſt me into the worlde, euen ſo haue I ſente theim into the worlde. And for theyr ſakes ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie I myſelfe, that they alſo myghte bee ſanctified: thorowe the truthe.</p>
               <p>I praye not for theim alone, but for
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:5778:52"/> theim alſo whiche ſhall beleue on me, throughe theyr preachynge, that they all maye bee one: as thou father arte in me, and I in thee: that they maye bee alſo one in vs, that the worlde maye beleue that thou haſte ſente me. And that glorie that thou gaueſt me, I haue geuen theim, that they maye bee one: as wee are one. I in theim and thou in me, that they maye bee made perfecte in one, and the worlde maye knowe that thou haſte ſent me, and haſte loued theim: as thou haſte loued me. Father, I wyll that they whiche thou haſte geuen me, bee with me where I am, that they maye ſee my glorie: whiche thou haſte geuen me. For thou louedeſt me, before the makynge of the worlde. Oh ryghte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe father, the verye worlde hathe not knowen thee, but I haue kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen thee, and theſe haue knowen that thou haſte ſente me. And I haue
<pb facs="tcp:5778:53"/> declared vnto theim thy name, and wyl declare it that the loue wherwith thou haſte loued me: bee in theim, and I in theim.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="Psalms">
            <head>
               <hi>CERTAINE PSAL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes</hi> picked forthe very mete for dayly pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers vnto God.</head>
            <p>¶ To bee delyuered from the vngodly that wee peryſhe not with theim, that endeuer theimſelues by all meanes; to withdraw vs frome the waye of truthe and that all good menne, maye conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuallye bee enuironued with Goddes proteccion.</p>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>The prayer of Dauid. <bibl>Pſal. 5.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>EARE my wordes (O Lord) conſidre my callyng oh marke the voyce of my peticion: my kyng and my God. For vnto thee, wyll I make my prayer. Heare my voyce
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:5778:53"/> by tymes (oh Lorde), for early in the mornyng, wyl I get me vnto thee: yea and that with diligence, for thou art not the GOD that haſt pleaſure in wyckedneſſe, there maye no vngodly perſone dwell with thee. Suche as bee cruell may not ſtande in thy ſyght thou arte an enemy vnto all wycked dooers. Thou deſtroyeſt the lyers, the Lorde abhorreth the bloudthurſtye: and the deceytefull. But I O Lorde wyll come into thy houſe, truſtyng v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the multitude of thy mercy. And reuerently wyll make my ſupplicaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in thy holy temple. Conduyſe me, Oh Lorde) in thy ryghteouſneſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of myne enemyes and make thy way playne before me. For there is no faythfulneſſe in theyr mouthes: they diſſemble in theyr heartes their throte is an open graue, with theyr tongues they practyſe deceytes. Punyſh theim (Oh God) that they maye peryſhe in theyr owne imaginacions, caſte theim
<pb facs="tcp:5778:54"/> oute becauſe of the multitude of theyr vngodlyneſſe: for they rebell agaynſte thee. Agayne, lette all theim that put theyr truſte in thee: reioyſe, yea, lette theim euer bee geuyng of thankes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou defendeſt theim, that they whiche loue thy name, maye bee ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in thee. For thou Lorde geueſt thy bleſſyng vnto the ryghteous, and with thy fauorable kyndneſſe thou de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fendeſt hym as with a ſhylde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>¶ To eſcape Goddes wrathe and to ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teyne his mercye, thus ſhalt thou pray with Dauid. <bibl>Pſal. 6.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>O Lorde, rebuke me not in thyne angre, chaſten me not in thy he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy diſpleaſure, haue mercye v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon me, Oh Lorde: for I am weake. Oh Lorde heale me: for my bones are all to ſhaken. My ſoule alſo is in greate trouble, but Lorde howe longe wylte thou tarye? Tourne thee (Oh
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:5778:54"/> Lorde) and deliuer my ſoule. Oh ſaue me for thy mercyes ſake, for in death no manne remebreth thee. Oh, who wyll geue thee thankes in the hell. I am wery of gronynge, euery nyghte waſhe I my bed and water my couch with my teares. My countenaunce is chaunged for very inwarde gryefe. I conſume awaye. I haue ſo many e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemyes. Awaye from me all ye wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked dooers, for the Lorde hath hearde the voyce of my wepynge, the Lorde hathe hearde myne humble peticyon, the Lord hath receyued my prayer. All myne ennemyes ſhall bee confounded and ſore vexed, yea they ſhall bee tour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned backe and put to ſhame, and that ryghte ſoone.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>¶ If thou bee falſely belyed, and ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligned of thyne aduerſarye, accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome thyſelfe vnto this prayer of Dauid, whiche he ſonge vnto the Lorde, vpon the woordes of the ſonne of Iemini.
<pb facs="tcp:5778:55"/>
                  <bibl>Pſal. 7.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>O Lorde my God: in thee dooe I truſte, ſaue me frome all theim that perſecute me, and delyuer me leaſte he catcheth vp my ſoule lyke a lyon: and teare it in peeces, whyle there is none to helpe. Oh Lorde my God, yf I haue dooen any ſuch thyng yf there bee any vnryghteouſneſſe in my handes: yf I haue rewarded euell vnto theim that hathe dealte frendly with me, or hurte theim that without any cauſe are myne ennemyes: then lette myne ennemy perſecute my ſoule and take me, yea lette hym treade my lyfe downe in the earth, and lay myne honoure in the duſte. Stande vp (O Lorde) in thy wrath: lyfte vp thy ſelfe ouer the furious indignacion of mine ennemyes, aryſe vp for me in the ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geaunce that thou haſt promiſed, that the aſſemblye of the people may come aboute thee: for theyr ſakes therfore lyfte vp thyſelfe agayne. The Lorde
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:5778:55"/> is iudge ouer the people: auenge me then (Oh Lord) a cordyng to my rygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teouſneſſe and innocencie. Oh lette the wyckedneſſe of the vngodly come to an ende, but maintayne the iuſte: thou ryghteous God that tryeſt the verye heartes and raynes: my helpe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of God: which preſerue theim that are true of heart. God is a rygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous iudge, and God is euer threate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng, yf menne wyll not tourne: he hathe whet his ſwearde: he hath bent his bowe, and made it ready. He hath prepared hym the weapons of deathe and ordeyned his arrowes to deſtroy. Beholde: this felowe trauayleth with miſchief, he hath conceiued vnhappe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and brought forth a lye. He hath grauen and dygged vp a pytte, but he ſhall fall hymſelfe into the hole that he hathe made. For his vnhappynes ſhall come vpon his owne heade, and his wyckednes ſhal fal vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his owne pate. As for me I wyll geue thankes
<pb facs="tcp:5778:56"/> vnto the Lorde, for his ryghteouſnes ſake, And wyll prayſe the name of the Lorde the moſte hyghe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>¶ A ſanctifieng for the mercye of God ſhewed vs in temptacions and aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities and for the meruelous ſubuerſion and deſtruccion of our aduerſaries. <bibl>Pſal. 9.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>Wyll geue thankes vnto thee, I (O Lorde) with my hole heart. I wyll ſpeake of all thy merue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous woorkes, I wyl bee glad and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce in thee, yea my ſonges wyll I make of thy name. Oh thou moſte hygheſt. Becauſe thou haſte dryuen myne enemyes a bake, they were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfyted, &amp; peryſhed at thy preſence For thou haſte mainteyned my ryght and my quarel, thou ſytteſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trone and arte the true iudge. Thou rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſte the Heathen and deſtroyeſt the vngodly: thou putteſt out theyr name for euer. The enemyes ſweardes are
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:5778:56"/> come to an ende, thou haſte ouerthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen theyr cities, theyr name is peryſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theim. But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde endureth for euer, he hathe prepared his ſeate vnto iudgemente. He gouerneth the worlde with ryghteouſnes, and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreth true iudgemente vnto the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. The Lorde is a defence, he is for the poore a defence in the tyme of trou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble. Therfore they that knowe thy name, put theyr truſt in thee. For thou (oh Lord) neuer fayleſt theim y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſeketh thee. Oh prayſe ye the Lorde whiche dwelleth in ſyon: ſhewe the people of his dooynges: and why, he maketh in quiſicion for theyr bloude, and remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>breth theim. He forgetteth not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playnte of the poore. Haue mercye v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon me (Oh Lorde) conſydre the trou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble, that I am in amonge myne ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes, thou that lyfteſt me vp frome the gates of death that I may ſhewe thy prayſes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in the portes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dough<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ghter of Syon &amp; reioyce in thy ſauing
<pb facs="tcp:5778:57"/> helth. As for the heathen: they are ſon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken downe in the pyt that they made yea in the ſame net whiche they ſpred oute pryuely is theyr owne feet taken Thus the Lorde is knowen to execute true iudgement, when the vngodly is trapped in the woorkes of his owne handes. So he is. The wycked bee tourned vnto hell, and all the heathen that forget God. But the poore ſhall neuer bee oute of remembraunce, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall the pacient abidyng of ſuch as bee in trouble, peryſhe for euer. Aryſe Lorde, lette no manne haue the vpper hande, lette the heathen bee con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demned before thee. Oh Lorde ſette a ſcolemaiſter ouer theim, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the heathen may know theimſelues to bee but me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>¶ A lamentacyon and waylinge vnto God, while Antechriſt triumpheth and ſleeth the holy ones of God, perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the Goſpell. <bibl>Pfal. 10.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>WHy arte thou gooen ſo farre of, O Lord, wilt thou hyde thyſelfe
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:5778:57"/> their hearte is ſure, that thyne eare herkeneth thereto, help the fatherles &amp; poore vnto their righte that the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly bee no more exalted vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>¶ That wee bee not wrapped in the blyndnes of the wycked, and that wee periſhe not for euer. <bibl>Pſal. 13.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>HOW long wilt thou forgette me. Oh Lorde, wilte thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gette me for euer? How long wilte thou hyde thy face fro me, O how long ſhall I toſſe counſailles in my mynde? how long ſhall I bee thus vexed in my hearte? How long ſhall myne enemie triumphe ouer me? Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidre and heare me Oh lorde my God lighten myne iyes, that I ſlepe not in death, leaſt myne enemie ſaie, I haue preuailed againſt him, for if I bee caſt doune, thei that trouble me will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce at it. But my truſt is in thy mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cie and my heart is ioyfull in thy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing helth. I wil ſyng praiſes of thee
<pb facs="tcp:5778:58"/> O Lorde, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dealeſt ſo louyngly w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> me</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>¶ That the heauenly father will not ſuffre vs to ſhrinke at ſo mighty aduer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaries and ſo cruelly purſuing whiche floue full of pleaſures of the worlde thus wee maie praye with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete praiyng in the perſon of Chriſt. <bibl>Pſalm. 17.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>HEARE myne innocencie (Oh Lorde) conſydre my complaine hearken vnto my prayer, that gooth not out of a fayned mouth, let my doome come forth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and looke vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thyng that is egail Thou haſt proued &amp; viſited my heart in the night ſeaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, thou haſt tried me in the fyre, and haſt found no wicked<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes in me, for I vtterly purpoſed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my mouth ſhould not offende. Becau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> woordes of thy lippes, I haue kept me from the workes of menne, from the waies of peruerſe perſones Direct my gooynges into thy pathes that my fotſteppes ſlippe not, for vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee I crie. Heare me oh God, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clyne
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:5778:58"/> thyne eares vnto me, and herke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto my woordes. Shewe thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelous louyng kyndenes, thou that ſaueſt ſuche as put their truſt in thee From ſuche as reſiſt thy righthande kepe me as the apple of an iye. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende me vnder the ſhadowe of thy wynges, from the vngodly that trou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble me, from myne enemies whiche co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſe my ſoule rounde aboute whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che maintein their owne welthyneſſe with oppreſſion, and their mouth ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aketh proude thynges. Thei lie way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng in our waie on euery ſyde, tour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyng their iyes doune to the grounde like as a lion y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is gredy of his praye, &amp; as it were a lions whelpe, lurkyng in his denne. Aryſe Lorde diſappoint hym, and caſt hym doune deliuer my ſoule with thy ſwearde from the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly with thy ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de O Lorde reſeue me from the menne of this worlde, whiche haue their porcion in this life whoſe bellies thou filleſt w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.
<pb facs="tcp:5778:59"/> Thei haue children at their deſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re &amp; leaue the reſt of their ſubſtaunce for their babes, well I will beholde thy preſence in righteouſnes, &amp; when thy glory appeareth, I ſhalbe ſatiſfied</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>¶ With muche affiaunce of hearte v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon God, a prayer for ſynnes and for the grauntyng of his holy ſpirite, for it is not poſſible but GOD will heare vs a cordyng to Chriſtes promiſe in the Goſpell. <bibl>Pſal. 25.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>VNto to thee (Oh Lorde) I lift vp my ſoule. My God I truſt in thee, lette me not bee confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded, leaſte myne enemies bragge ouer me. For no doubt all thei that hope in thee, ſhall not bee aſhamed, but ſuche as bee ſcornefull deſpiſers withoute a cauſe, thei ſhall bee putte to ſhame. Shew me thy waies, Lorde and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che me thy pathes. Leade me in thy trouth and teache me, for thou art the God of my helthe, and in thee is my hope all the daie long. Call to remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>braunce,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:5778:59"/> oh Lorde, thy tendre mercies &amp; thy louyng kyndnes, whiche haue been euer ſithens the begynnyng Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre not the ſinnes &amp; offences of my youthe but a cordyng to thy mercie thinke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me, oh lorde, for thy good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes. Oh how frendly &amp; righteous is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde, therfore will he bryng again ſynners into the waie, he leadeth the ſimple a right &amp; ſuche as bee meke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he inſtructeth his waies. All the wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of the Lorde, are verie mercy and faithfulneſſe, vnto ſuche as kepe his teſtament and couenaunt. For thy na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes ſake, oh lorde, bee mercifull vnto my ſynne, for it is greate. What ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he bee that fearethe the Lorde he ſhall ſhew hym the waie, that he hath choſen. His ſoule ſhall dwell at eaſe, &amp; his ſede ſhall poſſeſſe the lande. The ſecrete of the Lorde is emong theim that feare him, and he ſheweth theim his couenaunte. Myne iyes are euer lokyng vnto the Lorde, for he ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:5778:60"/> plucke my fete out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> net. Tourne thee vnto me and haue mercye vpon me, for I am deſolate and in miſery. The ſorowes of my hearte are great wherefore bryng me out of my trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, looke vpon myne aduerſite and miſerie and forgeue me all my ſinnes Conſidre how myne enemies are ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny, and beare malicious hate againſt me. O kepe my ſoule and deliuer me, let me not bee confounded for I haue putte my truſt in thee. Lette innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy and righteous dealyng wayte vpon me, for my hope is in thee. Deliuer Iſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raell, O God out of all his diſtreſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>¶ In the affliction or paſſion bothe of the ſpirite and of the fleſhe, thus maie wee praye with Chriſt &amp; with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godly <bibl>Pſalm. 31:</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>IN thee, O Lorde is my truſte, let me neuer bee put to ſhame, but deliuer me in thy righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe. Bowdoune thyne eare to me, make haſt to deliuer me, bee thou my
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:5778:60"/> ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g rocke, and a walled houſe, that thou maieſt ſaue me For thou art my ſtrong holde and my caſtle, wherfore bee thou my God, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ducte me for thy names ſake. Draw me out of the nette, that thei haue laied priuely for me, for thou arte my ſtrengthe. Into thine handes I commende my ſpirite thou haſt deliuered me oh Lorde thou God of truth I hate theim that hold of vanities, &amp; my truſt is in the Lorde I will bee glad &amp; reioyce in thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, for thou haſt conſidered my trou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble, thou haſt knowen my ſoule in ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſitie. Thou haſt not caſt me ouer, into the handes of the enemies, but haſte ſette my fete in a large roume. Haue mercie vpon me Oh Lorde for I am in trouble, myne iyes is cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for verie heuines, yea my ſoule &amp; my bodie. My life is conſumed with heueneſſe, and my yeres with mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng. My ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth faileth me becauſe of myne aduerſity, and my bones are
<pb facs="tcp:5778:61"/> dryed vp, I am become a verie repro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che emo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g all myne enemies my neigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>boures &amp; thei of myne owne acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce are afraied of me, thei that ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me in the ſtrete, conuey theimſelues from me, I am cleaue forgotten and out of mynde euen as a dedde manne. Lo I am become like a broken veſſell For I haue hearde the ſklenderous reapportes of the multitude, euerye manne abhorreth me, thei haue gathe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red a counſaill together againſte me, and are purpoſed to take awaie my life. But my hope is in the Lorde, and I ſaie thou arte my God. My dayes are in thy hande, deliuer me from the hande of myne enemies, and frome theim that perſecute me. Shewe thy ſeruaunt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> light of thy countinaunce help me for thy mercies ſake, lette me not bee confounded, O Lorde, for I call vpon thee, but lette the vngodly rather bee putte to confuſion, and brought vnto the pit, let the liyng lip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pes
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:5778:61"/> bee put to ſilence, whiche cruelly diſdainfully, and deſpitefully ſpeake againſt the righteous. O how greate and manifolde bee the good thynges whiche thou haſt laied vp for theim that feare thee? How greate thynges bryngeſt thou to paſſe for theim that put their truſt in thee, in the ſighte of the ſoonnes of menne? Thou hideſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecretes of thy countenaunce from the proude menne, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> kepeſt thei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſecretely in thy tabernacle from the ſtrief of toungues. Thankes bee ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the lorde who hath ſhewed me meruelous great kyndnes out of the ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g citee. For when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoudain feare came vpon me, I ſaied I am caſt out of thy ſighte. Neuertheles thou har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt myne hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble prayer, when I cried vnto thee. Wherefore loue the Lorde (all ye his ſainctes) for the Lorde pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerueth the faithfull &amp; plenteouſly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiteth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> proude dooers. Bee ſtrong therfore &amp; take a good heart vnto you
<pb facs="tcp:5778:62"/> all ye that putte your aſſiaunce in the LORDE.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>¶ A ſanctifiyng of GOD, for that the earthe is full of his mercie, and that by his mighty woorde he wrought all thyng. <bibl>Pſalme. 33.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>REioyſe in the Lorde O ye righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teous, for it becommeth well y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iuſte to bee thankefull. Prayſe the Lorde with harpe. Syng Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes vnto hym with the lute and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of ten ſtrynges. Syng hym a newe ſong, yea ſyng to hym with good courage. For the woorde of the Lorde is true, and all his workes are ſure. He loueth mercie and iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the earth is full of the Lordes good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. By the woorde of the Lorde wer the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s made, and all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> furniture of theim by the breth of his mouthe. He gathereth the waters togither as it were in a bottell and laied vp the depe in ſecrete. Let all the earth feare
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:5778:62"/> the Lorde, and let all theim that dwel in the worlde, ſtande in awe of hym. For what he ſaieth, is dooen &amp; what he commaundeth ſtandeth faſte. The Lorde diſperſeth the counſaill of the Heathen, and maketh fruſtrate the de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uices of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people. But his owne cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaill endureth for euer, &amp; the though<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of his hearte from generacion to generacion. Bleſſed are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people that holde the Lorde for their God, and bleſſed are the folke who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath cho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſen to bee his heritage. The Lorde lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth doune from heauen, and behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all the children of menne. From his ſtrong ſeate he conſidereth al the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that dwell in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde. He onely hath faſhioned all the heartes of theim &amp; knoweth all their woorkes. A kyng is not helped by his owne great hoſte neither is a gyaunte ſaued through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> might of his owne ſtrength. A horſe is but a vain thyng to ſaue a manne, it is not the power of his ſtrengthe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5778:63"/> that can deliuer hym. Beholde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iyes of the Lorde bee fixed vpon thei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that feare hym, and repoſe theimſelues in his mercie That he maie deliuer their ſoules from death, and fede theim in the deare tyme. Let our ſoule pacient<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly abyde the Lorde, for he is our help &amp; ſhylde. So ſhall our hearte reioyce in hym, becauſe wee haue hoped in his holy name Let thy merciful kynd<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, O Lorde, bee vpon vs like as wee haue repoſed our truſt in thee.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>¶ A ſtabliſheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the mynde againſt ſuche as ſlaunder vs that wee again vpbrayde not theim whiche thyng is the greate gift of God. <bibl>Pſal. 39.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>I Was determined to kepe my waies that I offend not in my toungue, &amp; ſo I ſhut my mouth Whyle the vngodly laie in a wayte for me, I helde my toungue, I was dome, I kept ſilence, for a good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, but it was pain and grief vnto me. My hearte was hote within me,
<gap reason="missing" extent="4 pages">
                     <desc>〈4 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:5778:63"/> myes, and in his truth ſhall he deſtroy theim. Wherfore I wyll offer vnto thee, and prayſe thy name. Oh Lorde, becauſe it is ſo comfortable, for thou haſt delyuered me oute of all my trou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble, ſo that myne eye ſeeth his deſyre vpon myne enemyes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>¶ That beyng lightened with Goddes grace wee may knowe here in erth the waye that leadeth to God whithe is a ſure confydence vpon God and charyte towardes the neyghboure. <bibl>Pſal. 67.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>GOD bee mercyfull vnto vs, bleſſe vs, and ſhewe the lyghte of his countenaunce vpon vs. That wee maye knowe thy waye v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon earthe, thy ſauyng health among all heathen. Let the people prayſe thee O God, yea let all people prayſe thee. Lette the people reioyſe and bee glad, for that thou iudgeſt the folke rygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſlye, and gouerneſt the nacions vpon earthe. Lette the people prayſe
<pb facs="tcp:5778:64"/> thee, Oh God, lette all people prayſe thee. God, euen our owne god, geueth vs his bleſſyng, that the earthe m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e bring forth her encreaſe. God bleſſeth vs, and lette all the endes of the world feare hym.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>¶ Agaynſte Antechriſt purſuynge and kyllyng the holy ones of God and defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng the miſteries of Goddes woorde. <bibl>Pſal. 79.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>OH God the heathen haue inua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thyne herytage, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple haue they defyled, and made Ieruſalem an heape of ſtones. The deade bodyes of thy ſeruauntes haue they geuen vnto the foules of the ayre to bee deuoured, and the fleſhe of thy holy ones vnto the beaſtes of the land Theyr bloude haue they ſhed lyke wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter on euerye ſyde of Ieruſalem, and there was no manne to burye theim, wee are become an open ſhame vnto oure enemyes, a very ſcorne and veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion vnto theim that are round about
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:5778:64"/> vs Lorde: howe longe wylte thou bee angry, ſhall thy gelouſye burne lyke fyre for euer? Powre oute thy indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacion vpon the Heathen that know thee not, and vpon the kyngdomes: that call not vpon thy name, For they haue deuoured Iacob, and layde waſt his dwellynge place. Oh, remembre not oure olde ſynnes, but haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye vpon vs, and that ſoone: for wee are come to greate myſery Helpe vs, Oh God, oure ſauyoure for the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of thy name. Deliuer vs and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geue vs oure ſynnes for thy names ſake. Wherfore ſhall the Heathen ſaye, where is nowe theyr God? Lette the vengeau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of thy ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes bloud that is ſhed, bee openly ſhewed vpon the Heathen in oure ſyghte. Lette the ſorowful ſighing of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> priſoners come before thee, &amp; acordyng to the ſtrength of thyne arme, preſerue thoſe that are apoynted to dye. And for the blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemye wherewith oure neyghbours
<pb facs="tcp:5778:65"/> haue blaſphemed thee, rewarde theim Oh Lorde: ſeuen folde into theyr bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome. So wee that bee the people and ſhepe of thy paſture, ſhall geue thee thankes for euer, and wyll alwaye bee ſhewynge forthe thy prayſe more and more.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>¶ A prayer and yeldynge of thankes for that wee bee redemed by Chriſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eternall deathe. <bibl>Pſal. 86.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>BOwe downe thyne eare, Oh Lorde, and heare me: For I am confortles and poore. Kepe my ſoule, for I am gyltleſſe. Oh my God helpe thy ſeruaunte that putteth his truſte in thee. Bee mercyfull vnto me, Oh Lorde: for I call dayly vpon thee. Comforte the ſoule of thy ſeruaunte, for vnto thee Oh Lorde, dooe I lyfte vp my ſoule. For thou Lorde art good and gracious, and of great mercy vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all theim that call vpon thee. Geue eare Lorde vnto my prayer, and pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:5778:65"/> my humble deſire. In the tyme of my trouble I call vpon thee, for thou heareſt me. Amonge the goddes there is none like vnto thee. Oh Lord, there is not one that can doo as thou dooeſt All nacions whome thou haſte made, ſhall come and worſhyp before thee, Oh Lorde, and ſhall glorifie thy name For thou arte great, thou dooeſt won<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derous thynges: thou arte God alone Leade me in thy waye, oh Lorde that I may walke in thy truthe. Oh lette my hearte bee lyghte in fearynge thy name. I thanke thee, oh Lord my god and wyll prayſe thy name for euer. For great is thy mercy towarde me, thou haſte delyuered my ſoule from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nethermoſte hell. O God the proude are ryſen ayenſt me, and the congrega<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion of the myghtye ſeketh after my ſoule, and ſet not thee before their eies But thou, oh Lorde God, arte full of compaſſion, and mercye, longe ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng, great in goodneſſe and truthe.
<pb facs="tcp:5778:66"/> Tourne thee O Lorde: vnto me, haue mercye vpon me, geue thy ſtrengthe vnto thy ſeruaunt, and helpe the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of thyne handmayd, Shewe ſome to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vpon me for good, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they whiche hate me maye ſee it: and bee aſhamed becauſe thou Lorde haſte helped me, and comforted me.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>¶ When wee bee cleane put oute of all comforte, wee may praye with the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet in the perſone of Chriſte. <bibl>Pſal. 88.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>OH Lorde God my ſauyoure, I crye day and nyght before thee Lette my prayer entre into thy preſence: enclyne thyne eare vnto my callyng. For my ſoule is full of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and my lyfe draweth nye vnto hel I am counted as one of theim, that goo downe vnto the pytte. I am euen as a manne that hathe no ſtrength. I am founde amonge the deade, lyke vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to theim that lye in the graue. Which bee out of remembraunce and are cut
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:5778:66"/> awaye by thy hande. Thou haſte dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen me into the lowe pytte, into dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe out of whiche can no man wade Thy diſpleaſur lyeth harde vpon me and thou vexeſt me with all thy flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. Thou haſte put awaye myne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quayntaunce farre fro me, and made me to bee abhorred of theim. I am ſo faſte in pryſone, that I can not gette forthe. My ſyghte fayleth for verye trouble, Lorde I call dayly vpon thee, and ſtretche out my handes vnto thee Dooſt thou ſhewe wonders amongſt the deade? Can the phiſycions rayſe theim vp agayn: that they may prayſe thee? Maye thy louyng kyndneſſe bee ſhewed in the graue, or thy faythful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in deſtruccyon? Maye thy won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derouſe woorkes bee knowen in the darke, or thy ryghteouſneſſe: in the lande where all thynges are forgotten Vnto thee I crye, Oh Lorde, and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth my prayer before the Lord why putteſt thou awaye my ſoule?
<pb facs="tcp:5778:67"/> Wherfore hydeſt thou thy face from me? My ſtrengthe is gooen for very miſery, with fearfulneſſe doo I beare thy burdens. Thy wrathfull diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure gooeth ouer me: the feare of thee oppreſſeth me. They come rounde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute me dayly lyke water, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe me together on euery ſyde. My louers and frendes haſte thou put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye frome me, and tourned awaye myne acquayntaunce.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>¶ A bewaylyng of our corrupte nature and of the miſerie of this lyfe, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſynne. <bibl>Pſal. 93.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>LORDE, thou art our refuge from one generacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to an other Before the mountaynes were brought forthe, or euer the earth and the worlde were made: thou arte God euerlaſtyng and worlde without ende. Thou iourneſt menne to deſtruccyon agayne, thou ſayeſt come agayne: ye chyldren of menne. For a thouſande
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:5778:67"/> yere in thy ſyght are but as yeſter day that is paſte, &amp; lyke as it were a nyght watche. Aſſone as thou ſcatreſt theim they are euen as a ſlepe, and fade a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye ſodenly lyke graſſe. In the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng it is grene and groweth vp, but in the euenyng it is cut doune and wy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thered. For wee conſume away in thy diſpleaſure, and are afrayed at thy wrathfull indignacion. Thou ſetteſt our miſdedes before thee, and oure ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete ſynnes in the ſyght of thy coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce. For when thou arte angry, all our daies are gone. Wee bring our yeres to an ende, as it were a tale that is tolde. The dayes of our age are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout .iii. ſcore yeres and ten, &amp; though men bee ſo ſtronge that they come to foure ſcore yeres, yet is theyr ſtrength then but laboure and ſorowe: ſo ſone paſſeth it awaye, and wee are gone. But who regardeth the power of thy wrath? thy fearefull and terrible diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure? O teache vs too nombre
<pb facs="tcp:5778:68"/> oure dayes, that wee may applye our heartes to wyſdome. Tourne thee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne (O Lorde) at the laſte, and bee gracious vnto thy ſeruauntes. Oh ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſfye vs with thy mercye: and that ſone: ſo ſhall wee reioyce and bee glad all the dayes of oure lyfe. Comforte vs agayne, nowe after the tyme that thou haſte plaged vs, nnd for the yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res wherein wee haue ſuffered aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie. Shewe thy ſeruauntes thy woorke, and theyr chyldren thy glorie And the glorious maieſtie of the Lord oure God bee vpon vs. Proſper thou the woorke of oure handes vpon vs, proſper thou oure handye woorke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>¶ A ſanctificacion of the Lordes name for that he made all thynges, and all bee in his hande. <bibl>Pſal. 95.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>OH come lette vs prayſe the Lorde lette vs heartely reioyſe in the ſtrength of oure ſaluacyon. Let vs come before his preſence w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſgeuyng, and ſhewe ourſelfes glad
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:5778:68"/> in hym with pſalmes. For the Lorde is a greate God, and a greate kyng a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all goddes. In his hande are all the corners of the earth &amp; the ſtrength of the hyls is his alſo. The ſea is his, for he made it and his handes prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the drye lande. Oh come lette vs woorſhip and bowe doune ourſelues let vs knele before the Lorde our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker. For he is oure God, and wee are the people of his paſtur, and the ſhepe of his handes. To day yf ye wyl heare his voyce, harden not your heartes as when ye prouoked me in time of temp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tacion in the wylderneſſe, where your fathers tempted me: proued me, &amp; ſaw ray woorkes. Fourty yeres long was I greued with this generacion, and ſaied, they euer erred in theyr heartes, they verely haue not knowne my wai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es. Therfore I ſaied vnto theim in my wrath, that they ſhould not entre into my reſte.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>¶ Whyles wee ſeme to bee in the myd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des
<pb facs="tcp:5778:69"/> of tribulacion and forſaken of men yea and of God alſo. <bibl>Pſal. 102.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>HEare my prayer (O Lorde) and lette my crying come vnto thee Hyde not thy face frome me in the tyme of my trouble. Inclyne thine eares vnto me, when I call, heare me, and that ryghte ſone. For my dayes are conſumed awaye, lyke as it were a fyre brande. My hearte is ſmytten downe and wythered lyke graſſe, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I forgette to eate my breade. For the voyce of my gronyng my bones wyll ſcarſe cleue to my fleſhe. I am become lyke a pellicane in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wylderneſſe, and lyke an hole in the broken walle. I wake, and am euen as it were a ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe, ſytting alone vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe top Myne enemyes reuyle me all the daye longe. they laugh me to ſcorne and are ſworne together agaynſte me. I eate aſhes with my breade: and myngle my drynke with wepyng. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> becauſe
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:5778:69"/> The children of thy ſeruauntes ſhall cotinue, and their ſede ſhall proſpere in thy ſighte.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>¶ A merie thankeſgeuyng for all the benefites conferred vnto vs by Chriſt <bibl>Pſal. 103.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>PRayſe the Lorde, oh my ſoule &amp; all that is within me, praſe his holy name. Prayſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord oh my ſoule, and forgette not all his benefites whiche forgeuethe all thy ſynnes, and healeth all thyne infirme<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties. Whiche ſaueth thy life from de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtruction, and crouneth thee with mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cie and with louyng kyndenes. Whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che ſatiſfieth thy deſyre with good thynges, makyng thee, young and lu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſty as an egle. The Lorde executeth righteouſnes and iudgemente for all theim that ſuffre wrong. He ſhewed his waies vnto Moſes, and his wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes vnto the children of Iſraell. The Lorde is full of compaſſion and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, long ſufferyng and of great good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes.
<pb facs="tcp:5778:70"/> He will not alwaie bee chydyng, neither will he kepe his anger for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. He hath not delte with vs after our ſynnes, nor rewarded vs acor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to oure wyckednes. For looke how high the heauen is in compariſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the earthe: ſo greate is his mercye alſo towardes theim that feare hym, looke how wyde the eaſt is from the weſt: ſo farre hath he ſette oure ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes from vs. Yea like as a father pit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tieth his owne children, euen ſo is the Lorde mercifull vnto theim that fear hym. For he knoweth whereof wee bee made, he remembreth that wee are but duſte. That a manne in his tyme is but as graſſe, and flouriſheth as a floure in the felde. For as ſone as the wynde gooeth ouer it: it is gone and the place thereof knoweth it no more But the mercyfull goodneſſe of the Lorde endureth for euer, vpon theim that feare hym, and his righteouſnes vpon their chyldrens chyldren. Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mely
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:5778:70"/> to ſuche as kepe his couenaunte and thynke vpon his commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes to dooe theim. The LORD hath prepared his ſeate in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and his kyngdom ruleth ouer all. Prayſe the Lorde ye his angelles, ye that bee mightie in ſtrength, fulfillyng his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundemente that menne maie haue the voyce of his woordes. Praiſe the Lorde all ye his hoſtes ye ſeruauntes of his y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dooe his pleaſure. Oh ſpeake good of the Lorde all ye his woorke: in euery place of his dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Praiſe thou the Lorde o my ſoule.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>¶ An other geuyng of thankes and prayſe. <bibl>Pſal. 104.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>PRayſe the Lorde o my ſoule, O lorde my God thou art become excedyng glorious, thou art clo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thed with maieſtye &amp; honoure. Thou deckeſt thyſelf with light as it wer w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a garment: y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſpredeſt out the heauen like a curtain. Thou volteſt it aboue with waters, thou makeſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cloudes
<pb facs="tcp:5778:71"/> the chariottes, and gooeſte vpon the wynges of the wynde. Thou makeſt thy angelles ſpirites, and thy mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters flames of fyre. Thou haſt laied the earth vpon her foundacion, that it neuer moueth at any tyme. Thou couereſt it with the depe like as with a garment: ſo that the waters ſtande aboue the hilles. But at thy rebuke thei flie, at the voyce of thy thoundre thei are a fraied. Then are the hylles ſeen alofte, and the vallies beneth in their place, whiche thou haſt appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for theim Thou haſt ſette theim their boundes whiche thei maie not paſſe, that thei turne not again to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the earth. Thou cauſeſt the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les to ſpryng vp among the valies, &amp; the waters to runne among the hilles that all beaſtes of the felde maie haue drynke, and that the wilde aſſes maie quenche their thriſte. Aboue vpon the hilles, haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foules of the aire their inhabitacion, &amp; ſyng among the brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:5778:71"/> Thou watreſt the hilles from a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>boue, the earth is filled with the fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctes of thy woorkes. Thou bryngeſte forth graſſe for the cattell, and grene herbes for the ſeruice of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne. Thou bryngeſt fode out of the earth, wyne to make glad y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hearte of manne, oyle to make hym a cherfull countenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and brede to ſtrength mannes hearte. The trees of the Lord are full of ſap euen the trees of Libanus, whiche he hath planted. There make the birdes their neſtes, and the firre trees are a dwellyng for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtorke. The hilles are a refuge for the wylde gootes, and ſo are the ſtony rockes, for the conyes. Thou haſt appointed the moone for certain ſeaſons. The ſonne knoweth his gooyng doune. Thou makeſt der<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keneſſe that it maie bee night, where in all the beaſtes of the foreſte dooe moue, yea and the young lions, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che roare after their praye, and ſeke their meate at GOD. But when the
<pb facs="tcp:5778:72"/> ſunne dooeth ariſe, thei gette theim awaie together, and lie theim doune in their dennes. Then gooeth manne forth to his woorke, and to tille his lande vnto the euenyng. Oh Lorde how manifolde are thy workes, right wyſely haſt thou made theim all. yea the earthe is full of thy riches. So is this greate and wyde ſea alſo, where in are thynges creapyng innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, bothe ſmall and greate beaſtes. There goo the ſhippes ouer, &amp; there is that leuiathan, whom thou haſte made to take his paſtime therin Thei wayte all vpon thee that thou maieſt geue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meate in due ſeaſon. When thou geueſt it the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei gather it, when thou openeſt thy hande, thei are filled with good. But when thou hideſt thy face, thei are ſorofull. If thou takeſt awaie their breath, thei dye, and are turned agayne to their duſte. Agayne when thou letteſte thy breathe gooe forthe, thei are made, and ſo thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neweſt
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:5778:72"/> the face of the earth. The glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riouſe maieſtie of the Lorde endureth for euer, and the Lorde reioyſeth in his woorkes. The earth trembleth at the looke of hym, he dooeth but touch the hilles, and thei ſmoke, I wil ſing vnto the Lorde, as long as I lyue, I will prayſe my God, whyle I haue my beeyng. Oh that my woordes mighte pleaſe hym, for my ioye is in the Lorde. As for ſynners thei ſhall bee conſumed out of the earthe, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vngodly ſhall come to an ende, but prayſe thou the Lorde, oh my ſoule.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>¶ A halowyng and prayſyng of the Lorde that he meruelouſly anaunſeth his, as well in heauen as in earthe. <bibl>Pſal. 113.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>PRaiſe the lorde (o ye ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of the Lorde) prayſe the name of the LORDE. Bleſſe the name of the Lorde, frome this tyme forthe, for euer more. The Lordes
<pb facs="tcp:5778:73"/> name is worthy to bee prayſed, from the riſyng of the ſunne vntill the goo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yng doune of the ſame. The Lorde is high aboue all nacions, and his glory is aboue the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Who is like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lorde our God, that hath his dwellyng ſo highe, whiche humbleth hymſelf, to beholde that is dooen in heauen and in earth. Whiche taketh vp the ſimple out of the duſt, and lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the poore out of the mire. That he maie ſette hym among the princes euen among the princes of his people Whiche maketh the baren woman to kepe houſe, and to bee a ioyfull mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther of children.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>¶ A commendacion of the Lordes mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cie that he hath vouchſaue to call vs Gentiles and Heathen perſones vnto his faith. <bibl>Pſal. 117.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>PRayſe the Lorde all ye Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiles laude him all ye people. For his mercifull kindnes is euer more and more towarde vs, and the trouth
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:5778:73"/> of the LORDE endureth for euer. Prayſe the euerlaſtyng.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>¶ A praier that God himſelf maie lede rule, teache, and directe vs in his way in his preceptes and in his Goſpell, and that he maie kepe vs from the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctryne and tradicions of menne. <bibl>Pſalm. 119.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>BLeſſed are thoſe that bee vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waie, whiche walke in the lawe of the Lorde. Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are thei that kepe his teſtimonies and ſeke hym with their hole hearte. Whiche walke in his waies &amp; dooe no wickedneſſe. Thou haſte geuen ſtreight charge, to kepe thy commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dementes. Oh that my waies were ſtabliſhed to kepe thy ſtatutes, ſo ſhould I not bee confounded. Wyle I haue reſpecte vnto all thy commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dementes, I will thanke thee with an vnfained heart. Becauſe I am lerned in thy iudgementes of thy righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe I will kepe thy ſtatutes, oh for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake me not vtterly. Wherewithall
<pb facs="tcp:5778:74"/> ſhall a young manne clenſe his waie euen by rulynge hymſelfe after thy woorde. Wherefore with my whole hearte dooe I ſeke thee. Lette me not goo aſtraie oute of thy commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, thy woordes haue I hidde in my hearte that I ſhould not ſynne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee. Prayſed bee thou o Lorde Oh teach me thy ſtatutes. With my lippes will I bee tellyng oute all the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of thy mouth. I haue as greate delite in the waie of thy teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies as in all maner of riches. I will excerciſe myſelf in thy commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes, and haue reſpecte vnto thy fote pathes. My delite ſhalbee in thy ſtatutes, I will not forget thy woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. Oh dooe well vnto thy ſeruaunt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I maie liue and kepe thy woordes. Open thou myne iyes, and ſo ſhall I eſpy out wounderous thynges in thy law, I am a ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth. Hide not thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes fro me. My ſoule breketh out, for the verie ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:5778:74"/> deſyre y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I haue alwaie vnto thy iud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gementes. Thou rebukeſt the proude curſed are thei y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> depart from thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes. Oh turne fro me ſhame and rebuke, for I kepe thy teſtimoni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es. Princes alſo ſitte &amp; ſpeak againſt me, but thy ſeruaunte is occupied in thy ſtatutes In thy teſtimonies is my delighte, thei are my cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſailers. My ſoule cleaueth to the duſt, but quicke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou me a cordyng to thy woorde. I knowlaged my waies, &amp; thou herdeſt me. Wherefore teache me thy ſtatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. Make me to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de the waie of thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes, and ſo ſhall I talke of thy wounderous workes My ſoule melteth awaie for verie he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenes. Sette me vp a cordyng to thy woorde. Take fro me the waie of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng, and graunt me thy lawe, I haue choſen the waye of trouthe, thy iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gementes haue I laied bee for me. I ſtycke vnto thy recordes, Oh Lorde confounde me not.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:5778:75"/>
               <p>I will runne in the waie of thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes, when thou haſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted my hearte. Teache me oh lorde the waie of thy ordinaunces, and I ſhall kepe it vnto thende. Geue me vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng and I ſhall kepe thy lawe Yea I ſhall kepe it w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my hole hearte Leade me in the path of thy commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dementes, for that is my deſire. En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline my hearte vnto thy teſtimonies. and not to coueteouſnes. Oh turne a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>waie myne iyes, leſt thei behold vani<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie, and quicken me in thy wais. Sta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bliſhe thy woorde in thy ſeruaunte, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I maie feare thee. Take awaie the re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>buke that I am afrayed of. For thy iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes are amiable. Beholde my delite is in thy commaundementes. Oh quicken me in thy righteouſnes. Let thy louyng mercie come vnto me Oh Lord, and thy ſauyng helth a cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding to thy worde. That I maie geue aunſwere vnto my blaſphemers, for my truſt is in thy woorde. Take not
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:5778:75"/> the woorde of trouth vtterly oute of my mouth, for my hope is in thy iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes. So ſhall I alwaie kepe thy lawe: yea for euer &amp; euer. And I will walke in thy libertie, for I ſeke thy commaundementes. I will ſpeake of thy teſtimonies euen before kynges, &amp; will not bee aſhamed. My delite ſhal bee in thy commaundementes whiche I loue. My handes alſo will I lifte vp vnto thy commaundementes whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che I loue and my talkyng ſhalbee of thy ſtatutes. Thynke vpon thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunte, as concernyng thy woorde, wherin thou haſt cauſed me to putte my truſte. For it is my confort in my trouble, yea thy woorde quickenethe me. The proude hath me greately in deriſion, yet ſhrynke not I from thy lawe, I remembre thyne euerlaſtyng iudgementes, oh Lorde, and am co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted. I am horribly affride for the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, that forſake thy law. Thy ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes are my ſonges in the houſe of
<pb facs="tcp:5778:76"/> my pylgrimage. I rhynke vpon thy name, Oh Lorde, in the right ſeaſon and kepe thy lawe. And I praye thee let this chaunce vnto me that I may kepe thy commaundementes. Thou arte my porcion Oh LORDE, I am purpoſed to kepe thy law I make my humble peticion in thy preſence, with my whole hearte, Oh bee mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyfull a cordyng vnto thy woorde. I call myne owne waies to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and turne my fete into thy recordes. I make haſte and prolonge not the tyme, to kepe thy commaundementes The congregacions of the vngodlye haue robbed me, but I forgette not thy lawe. At midnighte ſtande I vp to geue thankes vnto thee, for the iudgementes of thy ryghteouſneſſe. I am a compaignion of all that feare thee, and kepe thy commaundemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. The earthe, Oh Lorde, is full of thy mercie, teach me thy ſtatutes Oh Lorde thou haſt dealte frendely with
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:5778:76"/> thy ſeruaunte, a cordynge vnto thy woorde. Teache me thy kyndeneſſe, nourtour and knowlage, for I beleue thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes. Before I was troubled, I went wrong, but now I kepe thy woorde. Thou art good and frendly, wherefore of that thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes teach me thy ſtatutes. The proud imagin lies vpon me, but I kepe thy commaundementes with my whole hearte. Their hearte is congeled as a lou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p of fat, but my delighte is in thy lawe. It is good for me that I haue ben in trouble, that I maie learne thy ſtatutes. The lawe of thy mouthe is dearer vnto me, then thouſandes of golde &amp; ſiluer. Thy handes haue made me &amp; faſhioned me, geue me vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, that I maie learne thy commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dementes. Thei that feare thee, will bee glad when thei ſee me, becauſe I put my truſt in thy woorde. I knowe Oh Lorde, that thy iudgementes are right, and that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> of verie faithfulnes
<pb facs="tcp:5778:77"/> haſte cauſed me to bee troubled. Oh let thy mercifull kyndnes bee my con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forte, a cordyng to the prom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt made vnto thy ſeruaunt. Let thy louyng mercie come vnto me, that I maie liue, for thy lawe is my delite. Let the proude bee confounded, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che handle me ſo falſely. But let ſuch as feare thee, and knowe thy teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nies, be at one with me. Let my heart bee vndefiled in thy ſtatutes that I bee not aſhamed. My ſoule longethe for thy ſauyng helthe, for my truſt is in thy woorde. My iyes long ſore for thy woorde, ſayng, Oh when wylte thou conforte me? For I am become like a bottell in the ſmoke, yet dooe I not forget thy ſtatutes. How many are the daies of thy ſeruaunt? when wilt thou bee auenged of mine aduer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaries? The proude haue dygged pit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes for me, whiche are not after thy lawe. All thy commaundementes are true, thei perſecute me falſely, but bee
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:5778:77"/> thou my helpe. They haue almoſte made an ende of me vpon earthe, but I forſake not thy commaundemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. Oh quycken me after thy louyng kyndneſſe, and ſo ſhall I kepe the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordes of thy mouthe. Oh Lorde thy woorde endureth for euer in Heauen. Thy trouthe alſo remayneth frome one generacion to an other, thou haſte layde the foundacyon of the earthe, and it abydeth. They contynue this daye a cordyng to thyne ordynaunce, for all thynges ſerue thee. If my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyght were not in thy awe, I ſhoulde peryſhe in my trouble. Wherfore I wyll neuer forgette thy commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes for with theim thou quycke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt me. I am thyne, helpe me. For I ſeke thy commaundementes. The vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>godly laye wayte for me, to deſtroye me, but I conſyder thy teſtimonies. I ſe that all thynges come to an ende but thy commaundement is exceding broade. Oh what loue haue I vnto
<pb facs="tcp:5778:78"/> thy lawe, all the daye longe is my tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng of it. Thou thoroughe thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundemente, haſte made me wyſer then myne enemyes, for it is euer by me. I haue more vnderſtandyng then all my teachers, for thy teſtimonies are my ſtudye. Yea I am wyſer then the aged, for I kepe thy commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes. I refrayne my fete from eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye euyll waye, that I maye kepe thy woordes. I ſhrynke not frome thy iudgementes, for thou teacheſt me. Oh howe ſwete are thy woordes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my throte? Yea: more then hony vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to my mouthe. Thoroughe thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes I get vnderſtanding: therfore I hate all falſe wayes. Thy woord is a lanterne vnto my fete, and a lyghte vnto my patthes. I haue ſworne and am ſtedfaſtly purpoſed to kepe the iudgementes of thy ryghtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe. I am troubled aboue mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: quicken me, oh Lorde: a cordyng vnto thy woorde. Lette the free ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:5778:78"/> of my mouth pleaſe thee, oh lord and teache me thy iudgementes. My ſoule is alwaye in my hande, yet dooe not I forgette thy lawe. The vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye haue layde a ſnare for me, but yet ſwarue not I from thy commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes. Thy teſtimonies haue I clay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med as my heritage for euer, and why they are the very ioye of my hearte. I apply my heart to fulfyll thy ſtatutes alway, euen vnto the ende, I hate the vngodlye, but thy lawe dooe I loue. Thou arte my defence and ſhelde, my truſte is in thy woorde. Away fro me ye wycked. I wyll kepe the commaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dementes of my God. Oh ſtablyſh me a cordynge vnto thy woorde: that I maye lyue, and lette me not bee dyſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted of my hope. Holde thou me vp: and I ſhal bee ſafe, yea and I ſhal euer bee talkynge of thyne ordinaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Thou treadeſte downe all theim that depart from thy ſtatutes, for they ymagyne but deceyte. Thou putteſte
<pb facs="tcp:5778:79"/> awaye all the vngodlye of the earthe lyke draffe, therfore I loue thy teſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies. My fleſh trembleth for feare of thee, and I am affrayed of thy iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gementes. I deale with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thyng that is lawfull and ryghte. Geue me not ouer vnto myne oppreſſoures. Bee thou ſuertie for thy ſeruaunte, to doo hym good: that the proude dooe hym no wronge. Myne eyes are waſted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye with lookynge for thy healthe, and for the woorde of his ryghteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Goo to, deale with thy ſeruaunt a cordyng vnto thy louyng mercy, and teache me thy ſtatutes. I am thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunte. Gh graunte me vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I may know thy teſtimonies. It is tyme for thee, Oh Lorde: laye to thyne hande, for they haue deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thy lawe. For I loue thy commaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dementes, aboue golde and preciouſe ſtone. Therfore holde I ſtrayghte all thy commaundementes: and all falſe wayes I vtterly abhorre. Thy teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:5778:79"/> are wonderfull, therfore doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth my ſoule kepe theim. When thy woorde gooeth forthe, it geueth lyght and vnderſtandyng euen vnto babes. I open my mouthe and drawe in my breathe, for I deſyre thy commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes. Oh: looke thou vpon me, and bee mercyfull, as thou vſeſt to dooe vnto thoſe that loue thy name. Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my gooynges after thy woorde, that no wyckedneſſe raygne in me. Delyuer me frome the ſclaunders of menne, ſo ſhall I kepe thy commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes. Shewe the lyghte of thy countenaunce vnto thy ſeruaunt, and teache me thy biddynges. Myne eyes guſhe out with water, bycauſe menne kepe not thy lawe. Ryghtuouſe arte thou: Oh Lorde, and true is thy iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gemente. The teſtimonies that thou haſte commaunded: are exceadynge ryghtuouſe and true. My zeale hathe euen conſumed me, becauſe myne en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes haue forgotten thy woordes.
<pb facs="tcp:5778:80"/> Thy woorde is tryed vnto the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſte, and thy ſeruaunte loueth it. I am ſmal, &amp; of no reputacion, yet dooe I not forget thy commaundementes. Thy rightuouſneſſe is an euerlaſting ryghtuouſneſſe, and thy lawe is true. Trouble &amp; heuineſſe haue taken holde vpon me, yet is my delight in thy com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundementes. The ryghtuouſneſſe of thy teſtimonies is euerlaſtyng, Oh graunt me vnderſtandyng: and I ſhal lyue. I call with my hole hearte, heare me: Oh Lorde. I wyll kepe thy ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes. Yea: euen vpon thee, I dooe calle, helpe me: and I ſhall kepe thy teſtimonies. Early in the mornynge doo I cry vnto thee, for in thy woorde is my truſte. Myne eyes preuente the myghte watches, that I myghte bee occupyed in thy woordes. Heare my voyce, Oh LORDE, a cordynge vnto thy louyng kyndneſſe, quycken me a cordynge as thou arte wonte. They draw nygh, that of malyce per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:5778:80"/> me, and are farre from thy law Be thou nygh at hande alſo, oh Lord for thy promyſes are faythful. As con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cernyng thy teſtimonies. I haue kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen euer ſythens the beginning, that thou haſte grounded theim for euer. Oh conſider myne aduerſitie, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuer me, for I doo not forget thy law Mainteyn thou my cauſe, and defend me: quycken me, a cordynge vnto thy woorde. Health is farre from the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, for they regarde not thy ſtatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. Greate is thy mercy Oh Lorde, quycken me as thou arte wonte. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny there are that trouble me, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue me, yet dooe not I ſwarne frome thy recordes. It greueth me when I ſee that the tranſgreſſoures kepe not thy lawe. Conſyder, Oh Lorde, howe I loue thy commaundementes, and quicken me with thy louyng kyndnes Thy woorde is true for euer, all the iudgementes of thy ryghtuouſneſſe, endure for euermore. The tyrauntes
<pb facs="tcp:5778:81"/> perſecute me withoute cauſe, but my hearte ſtandeth in awe of thy woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, I am as glad of thy woorde, as one that fyndeth greate ſpoyles. I hate and abhore lyes, but thy lawe do I loue. Seuen tymes a daye dooe I prayſe thee, becauce of thy ryghtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe iudgementes. Great is the peace that they haue whiche loue thy lawe: and they are not offended at it. Lorde I looke for thy ſauynge healthe, and dooe after thy commaundementes. My ſoule kepeth thy recordes, and lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueth theim exceadynglye. I kepe thy commaundementes and teſtimonies: for all my wayes are before thee, Let my complaynte come before thee, Oh LORDE, geue me vnderſtanding a cordyng vnto thy woorde. Lette my ſupplicacion come before thee: delyuer me, a cordyng vnto thy promyſe. My lypes ſhal ſpeake of thy prayſe, ſeyng thou haſte taughte me thy ordinaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Yea, my tongue ſhall ſynge thy
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:5778:81"/> woorde. For all thy commaundemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes are ryghte, lette thyne hande helpe me: for I haue choſen thy commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes. I longe for thy ſauynge healthe, Oh Lorde: and in thy lawe is my delyght. Oh let my ſoule lyue and prayſe thee, that thy iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes may helpe me. I gooe aſtraye, lyke a ſhepe that is loſte, ſeke thy ſeruaunte, for I dooe not forgette thy commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>¶ When wee are brouſed and humbled in heart, and contrarywyſe the worlde reioyſeth and triumpheth. <bibl>Pſal. 130.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>OVte of the depe call I vnto the: Oh Lorde, LORD heare my voyce. Lette thyne eares conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der well, the voyce of my complaynte If thou Lorde, wylte bee extreme to marke what is dooen amyſſe, oh Lord who maye abyde it? But there is mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cye with thee: that thou mayſte bee feared. I looke for the Lord, my ſoule
<pb facs="tcp:5778:82"/> doeth wayte for hym, &amp; in his woorde is my truſte. My ſoule dooeth paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently abyde the Lorde, frome the one mornyng to the other. Let Iſrael truſt in the Lorde, for wyth the Lorde is mer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ye, and plentuous redempcyon. And he ſhall redeme Iſraell from all hys ſynnes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>¶ To bee delyuered from bloude ſoup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, that buſye theimſelues to plucke vs from the way of God bothe by force and crafty meanes, and whiche labour to abolyſhe Goddes woorde. <bibl>Pſal. 140.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>DElyuer me Oh Lorde, from the euyll menne, preſerue me frome the wycked menne whiche ima<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyne myſchefe in theyre heartes, and ſtyrre vp ſtryfe at all ſeaſons. They ſharpen theyr tongues lyke a ſerpente adders poyſone is vnder theyre lyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes. Kepe me, oh Lorde, from the hand of the vngodly, preſerue me from the wycken menne, whiche are purpoſed
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:5778:82"/> too ouerthrowe my gooynges. The proude hath layde a ſnare for me, and ſpred a nette abrode with cordes, yea: and ſette trappes in my way. But my ſaiyng is vnto the Lorde, thou art my God, heare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> voyce of my prayer: oh Lorde. Oh Lorde God thou ſtrenth of my health thou haſt couered my head in the daye of battayle. Lette not the vngodly haue his deſyre. Oh Lorde, lette hym not haue his purpoſe, leaſte he bee to proude. Lette the miſcheft of their owne lyppes fall vpon the head of theim, that compaſſe me about Let hote burnyng coles fall vpon theim, lette theim bee caſt into the fier, &amp; into the pyt, that they neuer ryſe vp again A man full of woordes ſhall not proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per vpon the earthe, a malicyous and wycked perſon ſhall bee hunted away and deſtroied. Suer I am y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Lorde wyll auenge the poore, and mainteine the cauſe of the helpleſſe. The rightu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſe alſo ſhall geue thankes vnto
<pb facs="tcp:5778:83"/> thy name, and the iuſte ſhall contynue in thy ſyghte.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>¶ That GOD may kepe vs that wee ſynne not with our tongue, neither ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe our ſynnes as hypocrytes dooe. <bibl>Pſal. 141.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>LOrd, I call vpon thee: haſte thee vnto me, and conſider my voice When I cry vnto thee, lette my prayer bee ſette forth in thy ſyght, as incence, and let the lyftyng vp of my handes bee an euenyng ſacrifyce, Set a watch: Oh Lorde, before my mouth yea a watche at the dore of my lyppes Oh, lette not myne heart bee enclined to any euyll thyng, to bee mynded as the vngodly or wycked menne, leaſte I eate of ſuch thinges as pleaſe theim Lette the ryghtuouſe rather ſmyte me frendlye: and reproue me, ſo wyll I take it, as though he had poured oyle vpon my heade, it ſhall not hurte my heade, but I wyll praye yet for theyr wyckedneſſe. Theyr Iudges ſtumble
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:5778:83"/> at the ſtone, yet heare they my woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. that they bee ioyfull. Oure bones lye ſcatered before the pytte, lyke as when one graueth and dyggeth vp the grounde. But myne eyes looke vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to thee, Oh Lorde God: in thee is my truſte, caſte not out my ſoule: kepe me frome the ſnare which they haue laid for me, and frome the trappes of the wycked dooers. Lette the vngodlye falle into theyr owne nettes together, vntyll I bee gooen by theim.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>¶ That wee maye bee led forthe of the pryſon of diſtreſſe, of ſynnes &amp; of death vnto the prayſe and glorie of God, that wee bee no longer preſſed vpon earth. <bibl>Pſal. 146.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>I Crye vnto the Lorde with my voyce, yea euen vnto the Lorde dooe I make my ſupplicacion. I poure oute my complaynte beefore hym, and ſhewe hym of my trouble. When my ſpirite is in heuyneſſe, for thou knoweſt my pathe, in the waye
<pb facs="tcp:5778:84"/> wherin I walke, haue thei priuely laid a ſnare for me. I tooke vp my ryghte hand, and ſe: there is no man that wil know me. I haue no place to flee vnto no man careth for my ſoule. Therfore doo I cry vnto thee: Oh Lord, and ſay thou arte my hope and my porcion in the lande of the lyuyng. Conſider my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaint, for I am brought very low, oh delyuer me frome my perſecuters: for they are to ſtronge for me. Bryng my ſoule out of pryſon, that I maye geue thankes vnto thy name. Whiche thing yf y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> wilt graunt me, then ſhal y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryghteouſe reſorte vnto my company</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>¶ When wee fynde no merites in vs, no ryghteouſnes of oure owne, but all thynges deſperate. And again remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre howe God frome the begynnyng of the worlde hathe wrought wonders in his ſainctes, and hathe neuer forſaken ſuche as call vpon hym, thus may wee praye. <bibl>Pſal. 143.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>HEare my prayer Oh Lorde, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyder my deſyre, anſwere me for
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:5778:84"/> thy trouth and r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hteouſnes ſake, and entre not into iudgement with thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uaunte: for in thy ſyghte ſhall no man lyuing bee iuſtified. For the enemye perſecuteth my ſoule, he ſmyteth my lyfe downe to the grounde, he layeth me in the darkneſſe as the dead men of the world. Therfore is my ſpirite vex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed within me, &amp; my hearte within me is deſolate. Yet dooe I remembre the times paſt, I muſe vpon all thy woor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes. Yea I exerciſe my ſelfe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> woor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes of thy handes. I ſtretche forthe myne handes vnto thee, my ſoule cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vnto thee, out of the thyrſty lande. Heare me Oh Lorde, and that ryghte ſone, for my ſpirite waxeth faint, hide not thy face from me, leaſt I bee lyke vnto theim that gooe downe into the graue. Oh lette me heare thy louyng kyndneſſe bee tymes in the mornyng, for in that is my truſte, ſhewe thou me the waye that I ſhoulde walke in,
<pb facs="tcp:5778:85"/> for I lyfte vp my ſoule vnto thre. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuer me (Oh Lorde) frome myne ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes, for I reſorte vnto thee. Teache me to dooe the thynge that pleaſeth thee, for thou arte my God: lette thy louyng ſpirite leade me forth vnto the lande of ryghtuouſneſſe. Quycken me Oh Lorde, for thy names ſake: and for thy ryghtuouſnes ſake, bryng my ſoule out of trouble. And of thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſcatter myne enemyes abroade, and deſtroye all theim that vexe my ſoule, for I am thy ſeruaunte.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>¶ A thankeſgeuing, that albeit wee be vile, yet by the vertue of God wee bee ſtronge againſte all ſtraunge chyldren that is to ſaye, ſuche as bee not choſen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the inheritaunce of God. <bibl>Pſal. 144.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>BLeſſed bee the Lorde my refuge, whiche teacheth my handes to warre, and my fingers to fyght My hope and my caſtle, my defence, and my delyuerer, my ſhylde, in whom
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:5778:85"/> I truſt whiche gouerneth the people that is vnder my power. Lorde what is ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, that thou haſt ſuche reſpecte vnto hym? or the ſoonne of manne, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou ſo regardeſt hym? Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne is like a thyng of naught, his tyme paſſeth awaie like a ſhadowe. Bow thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, oh Lorde, &amp; come doune, touche the mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taines that thei maie ſmoke again. Sende forth lightenyng &amp; ſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter theim, ſhote oute thyne arowes, &amp; conſume theim. Sende doune thyne hande from aboue, deliuer me, &amp; take me out of the great waters, from the hande of ſtraunge children. Whoſe mouth talkyeth of vanitie, and their righte hande is all falſhed. That I maie ſyng a newe ſong vnto thee, oh God, and ſyng prayſes vnto thee v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon a ten ſtrynged lute. Thou that geueſt victorie vnto kynges, and haſt deliuered Dauid thy ſeruaunt from the perill of the ſwerde. Saue me and deliuer me from the hande of ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge
<pb facs="tcp:5778:86"/> children, whoſe mouth talketh of va<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nitie, and their right hande, is a righ hande of falſhed, that oure ſoonnes maie growe vp like young plantes, a that oure daughters maie bee as the poliſhed corners of the temple. That our garmentes maie bee full and ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſe with all maner of ſtore, that our ſhepe maie bryng forth thouſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and hundreth thouſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>des, in our vilages. That our oxe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maie bee ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to laboure, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there bee no miſchaunce ne decaie, and no complainyng in our ſtretes. Happy are the people that bee in ſuche a caſe. Yea bleſſed are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple, whiche haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde for their god</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>¶ A praiſyng of God for his meruay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous mercy, &amp; the eternal raigne of his clemencie, whiche prouideth for al his creatures, and in eſpeciall for ſuche as feare hym. <bibl>Pſal. 145.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>I Will magnifie thee, Oh God my kynge, I will prayſe thy name for euer and euer. Euery
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:5778:86"/> daie will I geue th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nkes vnto thee, and prayſe thy name for euer and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. Greate is the LORDE, and meruelouſe worthy to bee prayſed, there is no ende of his greatnes. One generacion ſhall prayſe thy woorkes to a nother, and declare thy power. As for me I ſhall bee talkyng of thy worſhippe, thy glory, thy prayſe, thy wounderous woorkes. So that men ſhall ſpeake of the mighte of thy merueylouſe actes, and tell of thy greateneſſe. The memoriall of thyne aboundaunt kyndeneſſe ſhall bee ſhe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wed, and menne ſhal ſyng of thy righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teouſneſſe. The LORDE is graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and mercifull, long ſufferynge, and of greate goodnes. The Lorde is louyng vnto euery manne, &amp; his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy is ouer all his workes. All thy wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes praiſe thee oh Lord, &amp; thy ſaintes geue thankes vnto thee. Thei ſhewe the glory of thy kyngdome, and talke of thy power. That thy power thy
<pb facs="tcp:5778:87"/> glorie &amp; mightines of thy kyngdome, mighty bee knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto menne. Thy kyngdome is an euerlaſtyng kyngdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and thy dominion endureth through oute all ages. The Lorde vpholdeth all ſuche as ſhould fal, and lifteth vp all thoſe that bee doune. The iyes of all waite vpon thee, and thou geueſt thei their meate in due ſeaſon. Thou openeſt thy hande, and filleſt all thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges liuyng with plenteouſnes. The Lorde is righteous in all his wayes and holy in his woorkes. The Lorde is nigh vnto thei that call vpon hym ſo that the call vpon hym faithfully. He fulfilleth the deſire of theim that feare hym, he hearethe their crie and helpethe theim. The Lorde preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth all theim that loue hym, but ſcat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terethe abrode all the vngodly. My mouth ſhall ſpeake the prayſe of the Lorde, and let all fleſhe geue thankes vnto his holy name, for euer &amp; euer. Prayſe the euerlaſtyng.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:5778:87"/>
               <head>¶ A prayſe of God, that in onely God the euerlaſtyng kyng wee oughte to truſt &amp; not in princes, in power, in wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedome, or in the rſghteouſnes of the e<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lementes of this worlde. <bibl>Pſal. 146.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>PRayſe the Lorde, oh my ſoule, whyle I leue will I praiſe the Lorde. Yea as long as I haue any beeyng, I will ſyng prayſes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my God. Oh put not your truſt in princes, nor in any childe of manne, for there is no helpe in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For when the brethe of manne gooeth forthe, he ſhall turne again vnto his earth and ſo all his thoughtes periſhe. Bleſſed is he that hath the God of Iacob for his helpe, &amp; whoſe hope is in the lorde his God. Whiche made heauen and earthe, the ſea, and all that therein is. Whiche kepeth his promiſe for euer Whiche helpeth theim to righte that ſuffre wrong, whiche fedeth the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie. The Lorde louſeth menne out of priſone, the Lorde geueth ſight to the blynde. The Lorde helpeth theim vp
<pb facs="tcp:5778:88"/> that are fallen, the Lorde loueth the righteous. The Lorde careth for the ſtraungers, he detendeth the father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, and the wydowe. But the waie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vngodly turneth he vpſide doune The Lorde thy God, oh Syon, he is kyng for euermore, &amp; throughout all generacions. Prayſe the euerlaſtyng</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>¶ A prayſyng of the Lordes name. <bibl>Pſal. 147.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>PRayſe ye the Lorde, for it is a good thynge to ſynge prayſes vnto oure God. Yea a ioyfull and a pleaſaunte thynge it is, to bee thankefull. The Lorde ſhall buylde vp Hieruſalem, and gather together the outcaſtes of Iſraell. He heale the the tontrite hearte, and byndethe vp their woundes. He telleth the noum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtarres, and calleth theim all by their names. Greate is our Lorde, and greate is his power, yea his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome is infinite. The Lorde ſettethe vp the mieke, and bryngeth the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:5778:88"/> doune to the ground. Oh ſyng vnto the Lorde with thankeſgeuyng ſyng praſes vpon the harpe vnto our God. Whiche couerethe the heauen with cloudes, prepareth rayne for the earth, and maketh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> graſſe to growe vpon the mountaines. Whiche ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth fodre vnto the cattel, and fiedeth the young rauens that call vpon him He hath no pleaſure in the ſtrengthe of an horſſe, neyther delighteth he in any mannes legges. But the Lordes delighte is in theim that feare hym, and putte their truſte in his mercye. Prayſe the Lorde Oh Hieruſalem, prayſe thy God, oh Sion, for he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth faſt the barres of the gates, and bleſſeth the children within thee. He maketh peace in thy borders, and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth thee with the flour of whete. He ſendeth forth his commaundemente vpon earth, his woord runneth ſwif<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tly. He geueth ſnowe like wolle, and ſcattereth the hore froſte like aſhes.
<pb facs="tcp:5778:89"/> He caſteth forth his iſe like morſels, who is able to abyde his froſt? He ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth out his woorde and melteth thei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> He bloweth with his wynde, and the waters flowe. He ſheweth his worde vnto Iacob, his ſtatutes &amp; ordinaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces vnto Iſraell. He hath not dealte ſo with all the Heathen, neither haue thei knowelage of his lawes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>¶ A prayſyng of God from all his crea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures, firſt heauenly and then earthly. <bibl>Pſal. 148.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>OH prayſe the Lorde of heauen, prayſe hym in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heigh. Praiſe hym all his angels, praiſe hym all his hoſte. Prayſe hym ſunne and moone, prayſe hym all ye ſtarres and light Prayſe him all ye heauens and ye waters, that bee vnder the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s Let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prayſe the name of the Lorde for he ſpeake the woorde &amp; thei were made He hath made theim faſte for e<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer and euer. He hath geuen theim a lawe whiche ſhall not bee broken.
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:5778:89"/> Praiſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde vpon earth ye whale fiſſhes, and all depes. Fire and hayle ſnow and vapoures, wynde &amp; ſtorme fulfillyng his woorde. Mountaines and hilles, frutefull tries and all Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dres. Beaſtes and cattel, wormes and fethered foules, kynges of the earthe and all people. Princes &amp; all iudges of the worlde, young menne and mai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dens, olde menne and children, let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> preyſe the name of the Lorde. For his name only is excellent, &amp; all his praiſe aboue heauen and earth. He exalteth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> horne of his people, all his ſaintes ſhall prayſe hym, the children of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the people that ſerueth hym</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>¶ A prayſyng of God in hymſelf that he is holy and halowyng, ſtrong and ſtrengthyng, greate &amp; makyng greate. <bibl>Pſal. 150</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>OH prayſe the Lorde in his ſanc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuary, praiſe hym in the firma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of his power: Praiſe hym in his noble actes, prayſe hym in his
<pb facs="tcp:5778:90"/> excellente greateneſſe. Prayſe hym in the ſounde of the trumpet, praiſe hym vpon the lute and harpe. Prayſe him in the ſymbales &amp; daunce, prayſe hym vpon the ſitynges and pipe. Prayſe hym vpon the well tuned ſymbales, prayſe hym vpon the loude ſymbales lette euerye thyng that hath breathe prayſe the Lorde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>¶ Againſt the enemie of the trouthe. <bibl>Pſal. 35.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>STirue thou with thei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, oh lorde that ſtriue with me, fight thou againſt thei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that fight againſt me. Laie hande vpon the ſhylde and ſpere, &amp; ſtande vp to helpe me. Draw out thy ſwerde and ſtop the waie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt theim that perſecute me, ſaye vnto my ſoule, I am thy helpe. Lette theim bee confounded &amp; put to ſhame that ſeke after my ſoule. Let theim be turned backe &amp; brought to confuſion that imagyne miſchief for me. Lette theim bee as the duſt before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wynde
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:5778:90"/> and the angell of the lorde ſcateryng thei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Let their waie bee darke &amp; ſlippe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry, &amp; the angel of the lore to perſecute thei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For thei haue preuily laied their net to deſtroy me w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out a cauſe. Yea &amp; made a pit for my ſoule, whiche I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer deſerued. Let a ſodain deſtruction come vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnwaers, and the net y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei haue laied preuily, catche them ſelues, that thei maie fall into their owne miſcheif. But let my ſoule bee ioyfull in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde, and reioyſe in his help. Al my bones ſhal ſaie, lorde who is like vnto thee? Whiche deliuereſte the poore from thoſe that are to ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g for hym. Yea the poore and niedy fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his robbers. Falſe witteneſſe are ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen vp, and laie to my charge, thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that I knowe not. Thei rewarde me eiuill for good, to the greate dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comforte of my ſoule. Neuertheleſſe when thei were ſicke I putte on a ſecke clothe. I humbled my ſoule w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> faſtyng, &amp; my prayer turned into my
<pb facs="tcp:5778:91"/> boſome. I behaued myſelf as though it had been my frende or my brother. I went heuely as one that mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>neth for his mother. But in myn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie thei reioyſe, and gath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heim to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. Yea the verie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againſte me vnwaers, makyng mowes at me, and ceaſſe not. With the greydie and ſcornefull hypocrites thei gnaſhed vpon me with their tech Lorde when wilte thou looke vpon this? Reſtore my ſoule from the wyc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked rumoure of theim, my dearlynge from the lions. So will I geue thee thankes in the greate congregacion &amp; praiſe thee among muche people. Oh let theim not triumphe ouer me, that are myne enemies cauſeles. Let theim not wyncke with their iyes that hate me with out a cauſe. And why? their communyng is not of peace, but thei imagin falſe woordes againſt the out caſtes of the lande. Thei gape vpon me with their mouthes, ſaiyng there
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:5778:91"/> there, wee ſee it with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur iyes. This thou ſeeſt, Oh Lorde, holde not thy toungue then, god not farre from me O Lorde. A wake Lorde and ſtande <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p, auenge thou my cauſe my God &amp; my Lorde. Iudge me Oh Lorde my God a cordyng to thy righteouſnes, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thei triumphe not ouer me. Oh let thei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not ſaie in their heartes, there there, ſo would wee haue it, let theim no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſaie wee haue ouercome him. Let theim bee put to confuſion and ſhame that r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>yſe at my trouble. Let theim bee clo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed with rebuke &amp; diſhonour that hoſte themſelues againſt me. Let <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> alſo bee glad and reioyſe, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uoure my righteouſe dealyng. Yea let theim ſaie alwaie Bleſſed bee the Lorde whiche hath pleaſur in the proſperitie of his ſeruaunte. And as for my toungue, it ſhalbee talkyng of thy righteouſnes, and of thy prayſe, all the daie long.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <pb facs="tcp:5778:92"/>
               <head>¶ This pſalme bycauſe it is all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Euangelicall, and teachethe the contempt of this worlde, wee haue put it at the ende to thintent y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in al our tri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bulacion and in the pryde of the wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked wee maie conforte ourſelues. Let no daie paſſe thee, but thou reade this. <bibl>Pſal. 37.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>FRet not thy ſelf at the vngodly bee not thou enuious againſte the eiuill dooers. For thei ſhall ſone bee cut doune like the graſſe, and bee withered euen as the grene berbe Put thou thy truſt in the Lorde, and bee dooyng good, ſo ſhalt thou dwell in the lande, and verily it ſhall fiede thee. Delight thou in the Lorde, and he ſhall geue thee thy heartes deſyre, Commit thy waie vnto the Lorde, ſet thy hope in hym, and he ſhall brynge it to paſſe. He ſhall make thy righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe as clere as the light, and thy iuſte dealyng as the none daie. Holde thee ſtill in the lorde, &amp; abide paciently about hym. But greue not thy ſelf at
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:5778:92"/> one that hath proſperitie, and liuethe in abhominacion, Leaue of fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wrath let goo diſpleaſure, let not thy gelow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſye moue thee alſo to dooe eiuill. For wicked dooers ſhalbee roted out, but thei that paciently abide the lorde ſhal enherite the lande. Suffre yet a litle while, and the vngodly ſhalbee cleane goon, thou ſhalt looke after his place and he ſhall bee awaie. But the meke ſpirited ſhall poſſeſſe the earthe, and haue pleaſure in muche reſt. The vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly laieth waite for the iuſte, and gnaſheth vpon hym with his tiethe. But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde laugheth hym to ſcorne for he ſeeth that his daie is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng. The godly drawe oute the ſwearde, and bende their bowe to caſte downe the ſimple and poore, and to ſle ſuche as goo the right waie. Neuertheleſſe their ſwearde ſhall goo through their owne hearte and their bowe ſhall bee broken. A ſmall thyng that the righte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous hath, is better then greate riches
<pb facs="tcp:5778:93"/> of the vngodlye. For the arme of the vngodly ſhalbee broken, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde vpholdeth the righteouſe. The Lorde knoweth the daies of the godly, and their enheritaunce endureth for euer. Thei ſhall not bee confounded in the perilous tyme, &amp; in the daies of derth thei ſhall haue inough. As for the vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>godly thei ſhall periſhe, and when the enemies of the Lorde are in their flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wres thei ſhall conſume. Yea euen as the ſmoke ſhall thei conſume a waie The vngodly boroweth and payethe not again, but the righteouſe is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull and liberall. Suche as bee bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of hym, ſhall poſſeſſe the lande, &amp; thei whom he curſeth ſhall bee roted out. The Lorde ordreth a good man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes gooyng, and hath pleaſure in his waie. Though he fall he ſhall not bée hurte, for the Lorde vpholdeth hym with his hande. I haue been younge and now am olde, yet ſawe I neuer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> righteous forſaken, nor his ſede to
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:5778:93"/> ſeke theyr breade. The ryghteouſe is euer mercyfull, and lendeth gentlye therfore ſhall his ſede bee bleſſed. Flee frome euyll, and dooe the thyng that is good, ſo ſhalte thou dwell for euer, For the Lorde loueth the thynge that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ryghte, he forſaketh not his ſain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctes, but they ſhall bee preſerued for euer, as for the ſede of the vngodlye: it ſhall bee roted oute. Yea the rygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſe ſhall poſſeſſe the lande, &amp; dwell therin for euer. The mouth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teouſe is exercyſed in wyſdome, and his tongue talketh of iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. The lawe of his God is in his heart, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhall not his footeſteppes ſlyde. The vngodlye ſeeth the ryghteouſe, and gooeth aboute to flee hym. But the Lorde wyll not leaue hym in his handes, nor condempne hym when he is iudged. Hope thou in the Lorde, and kepe his way, and he ſhall ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote thee, that thou ſhalte haue the lande by enherytaunce, and ſee: when
<pb facs="tcp:5778:94"/> the vngodlye ſhall peryſhe. I myſelfe haue ſent the vngodlye in greate po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, and floryſhyng lyke a grene baye tree, but when I wente by, lo: he was gooen. I ſoughte hym, but he coulde no where bee founde. Kepe innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye: and take hede vnto the thynge that is ryghte, for that ſhall brynge a manne peace at the laſte. As for the tranſgreſſours: they ſhall peryſhe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and the vngodlye ſhall bee rooted oute at the laſte. The helpe of the ryghtuouſe cometh of the LORDE, he is theyre ſtrength in the tyme of trouble. The Lorde ſhalt ſtande by theim, and ſaue theim. He ſhall delyuer theim from the vngod<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye, and helpe theim, becauſe they put theyr truſt in hym.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="prayers">
            <pb n="98" facs="tcp:5778:94"/>
            <head>¶ <hi>CERTAINE PRAI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> ſhorte and of dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers ſortes.</head>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ The prayer of Moſes at the remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng of the tentes. <bibl>Nume. 10.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Iſe vp Lorde, lette thyne enemyes bee ſcatered, and lette theim that hate thee: flee before thee. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the arke reſted, he ſayde. Retourne LORDE vnto the mul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>titude of the Hooſte of Iſraell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ The prayer of Aaron and Moſes, for theyre ſyſter Mari: ſtryken with the lepre. <bibl>Nume. 12.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>OH I beſech thee my LORD putte not the ſynne vpon vs, whiche wee haue fooliſhly com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mitted, that this woman bee not as one that came foorth deade out of her mothers wombe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:5778:95"/>
               <head>¶ The prayer of Moſes vnto the Lord that he mought paſſe vp into the lande of beheſte. <bibl>Deut. 3.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>OH Lorde God, thou haſte be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goone to ſhewe vnto thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunte thy greatneſſe and thy moſte mighty hande, for there is none other God either in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or in earth, that can dooe thy woorkes, and bee compared to thy ſtrengthe. Lette me gooe therfore ouer: and ſee the good lande that is beyonde Iordane that goodly hyghe countrye, and Lybanon</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Eſay. 33.</head>
               <p>THe Lorde ſhall bee oure captain the Lorde ſhall bee our lawe ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. The Lorde ſhall bee oure Kyng, and he hymſelfe ſhall bee oure ſauyoure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Eſay. 45.</head>
               <p>I Am he, I am he ſayth the Lorde that for mine owneſelues ſake dooe away thyne offences, and forget thy ſynnes, ſo that I wyll ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:5778:95"/> thynke vpon theim. Put me now in remembraunce (for wee wyl reaſon together) and ſhewe what thou haſte for thee, to make thee quyte.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Eſay. 45.</head>
               <p>TOurne vnto me: all ye coaſtes of the earthe, ſayeth the Lorde: ſo ſhall ye bee ſaued. I am the God, and there is els none. I ſweare by my ſelfe, out of my mouth cometh the woorde of ryghteouſneſſe, &amp; that may no man tourne, but all knees ſhal bowe vnto me, and all tongues ſhall ſweare vnto me ſaiyng. Verely in the Lorde is my righteouſneſſe &amp; ſtrength To hym ſhal men come, but all they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thynke ſcorne of hym, ſhal bee confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded, And the hole ſede of Iſrael ſhall bee iuſtified, and prayſed in the Lorde</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Eſay. 53.</head>
               <p>SEke the Lorde whyle he maye bee founde. And call vpon hym while he is nigh. Let y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vngodly man forſake his wayes: and the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryghtuouſe
<pb facs="tcp:5778:96"/> his ymaginacyons, and tourne agayne vnto the Lorde: ſo ſhal he bee mercyful vnto hym, and to our God for he is redy to forgeue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Hie. 10.</head>
               <p>THere is none lyke vnto thee, oh Lorde. Great arte thou &amp; great is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of thy power. Who woulde not feare the? Or what kyng of the Gentiles woulde not obey thee For among all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyſe men of the gen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyles, &amp; in all theyr kyngdomes there is none y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> maye bee lykened vnto thee.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Hie. 10.</head>
               <p>NOwe I knowe (oh Lorde) that it is not in mannes power, to order his owne wayes, or to rule his owne ſteppes and gooynges. Therfore chaſten thou vs, oh Lorde: but with fauour &amp; not in thy wrathe: bryng vs not vtterly to naught.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Hie. 14.</head>
               <p>WE knowlage (Oh Lorde) all oure miſdedes, &amp; the ſinnes of our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:5778:96"/> for wee haue offended thee. Bee not diſpleaſed (oh LORDE) for thy names ſake, forgette not thy louyng kindneſſe. Remembre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trone of thy glorie: breake not thy couenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſte made with vs. Are there any amonge the goddes of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, that ſendeth rayn: or geueth the ſhowers of heauen? Dooeſt not thou it oh Lorde God, in whom wee truſt? Yea Lorde, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> dooeſt all theſe thinges.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Hie. 16.</head>
               <p>OH Lorde my ſtrength, my power and refuge in tyme of trouble.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Hie. 31.</head>
               <p>I Wyll plant my lawe, ſayth the Lorde: in the inwarde partes of theim: and write it in their hear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, and wyll bee theyr God, and they ſhall bee my people. And frome thence forth ſhall no manne teache his neigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>boure or his brother, and ſaye knowe the Lorde. But they ſhall all know me frome the loweſte vnto the hygheſte,
<pb facs="tcp:5778:97"/> ſayeth the Lorde. For I wyll forgeue theyr miſdedes: and wyl neuer remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber theyr ſynnes any more. Thus ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Lorde whiche gaue the ſonne to bee a lyghte for the daye, and the mone &amp; ſtarres to ſhyne in the nyghte Whiche moueth the ſea, ſo that the floudes therof waxe fearce, the Lorde almyghty is his name.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Eze. 33.</head>
               <p>AS truely as I lyue, ſayeth the Lorde, I haue no pleaſur in the death of the wycked, but muche rather that the wycked tourne frome his waye and lyue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Micheas. 7.</head>
               <p>WHere is there O Lorde, ſuche a God as thou? that pardoneſt wyckedneſſe, and forgeueſt the offences of the remnaunt of thyne he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytage? He kepeth not his wrathe for euer. And why? his delyght is to haue compaſſion, he ſhall tourne again and bee mercyfull vnto vs. He ſhall putte
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:5778:97"/> doune our wickednes, and caſt all our ſinnes into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> botome of the ſea. Thou ſhalt kepe thy truſte with Iacob, and thy mercy for Abraham, as thou haſte ſworne vnto our fathers longe agoo.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Eccleſi. 36.</head>
               <p>HAue mercye vpon vs, oh Lorde, thou God of all, haue reſpecte vnto vs, ſhewe vs the lyght of thy mercyes, &amp; ſende thy feare among the Heathen and ſtraungers, whiche ſeke not after thee, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may know there is no God but thou, that they may ſhewe thy wonderous woorkes. Lyfte vp thyne hande ouer the outlan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyſhe heathen, that they maye learne to know thy myght and power. Lyke as y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> arte halowed in vs before theim: ſo bryng to paſſe that thou mayſt bee magnified in theim alſo before vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they maye knowe thee, lyke as wee knowe thee. For there is none other God, but thou onely, oh Lorde renew the tokens, and chaunge the wonde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſe
<pb facs="tcp:5778:98"/> woorkes. Shewe thy hand and thy ryghte arme gloriouſly. Rayſe vp thy indignacion, and powre oute thy wrathe. Take awaye the aduerſarie and the ennemye. Make the tyme ſhorte: remembre thy couenaunte, that thy wonderouſe woorkes maye bee prayſed. Lette the fyer of the wrathe conſume theim, that lyue ſo careleſſe: and lette theim peryſhe that dooe thy people hurte. Smyte in ſunder the heades of the Prynces, that bee oure enemyes: and ſaye there is none other but wee. Gather thy lytle flocke toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther agayne, that they maye knowe there is none other God but onely y<hi rend="sup">u</hi>: that they may ſhewe thy wonderous woorkes, and bee thy people and heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, lyke as from the begynnyng. Oh Lorde, haue mercye vpon the people y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath thy name, &amp; vpon Iſrael, whome thou haſt likened to a fyrſt borne ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne Oh bee mercyfull vnto Iſrael the cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of thy ſanctificacion, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> citie of thy
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:5778:98"/> reſte. Fyll Syon with thy vnſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vertues, and thy people with thy glorie. Geue wytneſſe vnto thy crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, whom thou madeſt from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynnyng: and raiſe vp the prophecies that haue been ſhewed in thy name. Reward thou theim that wayte for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> that thy Prophetes maye bee founde faythful. Oh Lorlde, heare the prayer of thy ſeruauntes, a cordyng to the bleſſyng of Aaron ouer thy people, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all they whiche dwell vpon the earthe maye knowe, that thou art the Lorde the eternall GOD, whiche is from euerlaſtyng.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Eccleſi. 41.</head>
               <p>OH death: howe bytter is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce of thee to a man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſeketh reſte, and comfort in his ſubſtaunce and richeſſe, vnto the man that hath nothing to vere hym, &amp; that hath proſperitie in all thynges, yea to hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yet is able for to receyue meate oh death how acceptable &amp; good is thy
<pb facs="tcp:5778:99"/> iudgement vnto the nedefull, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hym whoſe ſtrengthe fayleth, and that is nowe in his laſte age, and that in all thynges is full of care and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, vnto hym alſo that is in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payer, and hath no hope nor pacyence Bee not thou afrayde of deathe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member theim that haue been afore thee, and that come after thee, for this is the iudgement of the Lorde: ouer al fleſhe. And why wouldeſt thou bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte this pleaſure of the hygheſt? Whether it bee ten, an hundreth, or a thouſande yeares, deathe aſketh not howe longe one hathe lyued.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="Psalms">
            <head>
               <hi>PSALMES OF DAVID</hi> againſt tirauntes and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutours of Goddes woorde.</head>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>¶ That all ſuch as lyue in Satans bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage may come to the knowlage of the faythe in Ieſus Chriſte.</head>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:5778:99"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>ORD helpe, for there is not one ſaincte more, ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry fewe faithful are there amonges the chyldren of menne euery man telleth lyes to his nyghboure, they dooe but flatter with theyr lyppes &amp; diſſemble in their heartes Oh y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Lord would roote out all diſceytfull lyppes, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tongue that ſpeaketh proude thynges Whiche ſaye our tongue ſhoulde pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle, wee are they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ought to ſpeake who is Lorde ouer vs? Nowe for the troubles ſake of the oppreſſed, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the complaint of the poore: I will vp (ſayth the Lorde) I will helpe theim, &amp; ſette theim at reſt. The woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of the Lorde are pure woordes, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as the ſiluer, which from earth is tryed and purifyed .vii. tymes in the fyer. Kepe theim therfore (oh Lorde) &amp; preſerue vs from this generacion for euer. And why? when vanite and ydel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe getteth the ouerhand amongſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5778:100"/> chyldren of menne, all are full of the vngodlye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>¶ For rulers and for comon peace. <bibl>Pſal. 20</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>THe Lorde mought heare thee in tyme of trouble, the name of the God of Iacob myght defend thee, and ſend thee helpe from the ſan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctuary, and ſtrengthen thee out of Sy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on. Remembre wil he all thy offringes and accept thy brent ſacrifice. He ſhal graunt thee thy heartes deſyre, &amp; ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyll all thy mynde. We wyl reioyce in thy helthe: and triumphe in the name of the Lorde oure God, for the Lorde wil perfourme al thy peticions, Now know I that the Lorde helpeth his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted: and wyll heare hym frome his holy heauen, mighty is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> helpe of his ryght hand. Some put theyr truſt in charettes and ſome in horſes, but wee wil remembre the name of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord our God. They are broughte downe: and fallen: but wee are ryſen &amp; ſtande
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:5778:100"/> vp ryghte. Saue Lorde and helpe vs: Oh kyng when wee call vpon thee.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>¶ Agaynſte the ennemyes of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, tyrauntes: heretiques, and ragyng wolues. <bibl>Pſal. 83.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>HOlde not thy tongue oh God, kepe not ſtyll ſylence: refrayne not thy ſelfe Oh God. For lo, thyne enemies a hurly burly: and they that hate thee: lyfte vp theyr heade. They ymagine craftely agaynſte thy people, and conſpire agaynſt thy ſecre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes. Come (ſaye they) lette vs roote theim oute frome amonge the people, that the name of Iſrael maye bee put out of remembraunce. For they haue caſte theyr heades together with one conſent and are confederate agaynſte thee. The tabernacles of the Edomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and Iſmaelytes the Moabytes &amp; Haparenes: Gegal, Amon &amp; Amalech the Phyliſtins with theim y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dwel at Tyre. Aſſur alſo is ioyned with theim
<pb facs="tcp:5778:101"/> and helpe the chyldren of Loth. But too thou vnto theim as vnto the Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dianytes, vnto Gyſera, and vnto Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin by the brooke of kyſon. Whiche peryſhed at Endor, and becam as the donge of the earth. Make theyr pryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces lyke Oreb and zeb: yea make all theyr prynces lyke zebea and Salmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, whiche ſayde we wyl chalenge vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to vs the houſes of God. Oh my god make theim lyke a whele, and as the ſtouble before the wynde, Lyke as a fyre that burneth vp the woode, and as the ſlame that conſumeth the mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taynes. Perſecute theim euen ſo with thy tempeſt, and make theim afrayed with thy ſtorme. Make theyr face a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed, oh Lorde, that they may ſeke thy name. Lette theim bee confounded and vexed euer more &amp; more, let theim bee put to ſhame &amp; peryſhe. That they may knowe that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> art alone, that thy name is the Lord, and that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> only art the moſt hygheſt ouer all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth. Am<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="testament_and_prayers">
            <pb n="105" facs="tcp:5778:101"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>THE TESTAMENT</hi> of Moſes. <bibl>Deuterono<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mii the .xxxii. cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piter.</bibl>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Arken heauens what I will ſpeake, let the earthe heare the woordes of my mouthe, lette my doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trynegather and waxe in to rayne my ſpeache maye flowe as the dewe, as the ſhower vpon the graſſe, and as the droppes vpon the blades of corne, for I will call on the name of the Lorde. Geue ye magnifi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cence and bountifull prayſe vnto our God, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> woorkes of God bee parfecte &amp; al his waies are iudgementes. The Lorde is faithfull and without all in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iquite, iuſt and right. Thei haue offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded hym. Thei that were not his chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren haue offended hym in filthines. Thou croked and peruerſe generaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on dooeſt yelde theſe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde, thou
<pb facs="tcp:5778:102"/> fooliſhe &amp; vnwiſe people? Is not he thy father whiche hath poſſeſſed thee and made thee, &amp; created thee? Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre the olde daies, conſidre eche gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racion. Aſke thy father &amp; he ſhal ſhew thee, thy aunceſtres and thei ſhall tell thee, when the moſte high Lorde deui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded the people, when he ſeuered y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren of Adam, he ordained the endes of peoples, a cordyng to the nombre of the children of Iſraell. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> part of the Lorde, is his people, Iacob is the corde of his enheritau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. He fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de hym in a deſerte lande, in a place of horroure, and hughe wilderneſſe. He compaſſed hym aboute &amp; taught hym and kepte hym as the ball of his iye. Like as the Egle prouokyng her bir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des to flie and flickeryng vpon theim caſteth abrode her wynges &amp; taketh vp her birde &amp; beareth it vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her ſhul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ders. Onely the Lorde was his guyde &amp; there was not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hym any ſtraunge God. He did ſet hym vpon an highe
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:5778:102"/> lande y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhould eate the frutes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feldes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhould ſucke hony of the rocke, &amp; oyle of the moſte harde ſtone. Butter of the kyne &amp; milke of yewes with the fatnes of lambes &amp; wethers (of the children of Baſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.) And the go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, with floure of wheat, &amp; to drinke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blode of the grape moſte pure. The beloued was encraſſat and winched a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gain, engroſſed, fatted, ſpredde abrode He forſoke god his maker &amp; departed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god his ſauiour. Thei prouoked hym with ſtraunge goddes &amp; ſtirred hym to anger in their abhominacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s Thei did ſacrifice to deuels &amp; not to god, to goddes whiche thei knew not New and freſh goddes came whiche their fathers worſhipped not. The god y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> begatte thee, thou haſt forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou haſt forgotten the Lord thy crea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>toure. The Lorde ſawe it and was ſtirred to wrathe, for their ſoonnes &amp; doughters haue prouoked hym &amp; he ſaid. I wil hide my face fro the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der
<pb facs="tcp:5778:103"/> the endes of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for it is a croked generacion &amp; the children are vnfaith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full. Thei haue prouoked me in hym that was no God and haue angred me with their vanities. And I will prouoke theim by thei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that is not my people by the fooliſh Gentiles I will anger theim. The fire burned in my furie and it ſhall brenne to the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſte of helle, and it ſhall deuoure the earth with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> frute therof, and it ſhal brenne the foundacions of the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines. I will gather eiuilles vpon theim and myne arowes I wil finiſh vpon theim. Thei ſhall bee conſumed with famyne and the birdes ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure them with moſte bitter bityng I will ſende vpon theim the tieth of wylde beſtes drawyng theim with fu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie vpon the earthe, and of ſerpentes Without ſhall the ſwearde make ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uoke of theim, and within the young man and alſo the vjrgin, the ſuckyng childe with the aged manne, &amp; I ſaied
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:5778:103"/> Wher bee thei? I will cauſe that the memorie of theim ſhall ceaſe among menne. But for becauſe of anger of their enemies I haue differred it, leſt perchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce their enemies would waxe proude and ſaie. Our hande is puyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſante and mightie and not the Lorde hath dooen all theſe thinges. The peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple is without counſail and without prudence, would God thei were wiſe and vnderſtode and foreſawe the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. How one hath perſecuted a thou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſande, and twoo hath put to flighte ten thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de? It is not bycauſe their God hath ſolde theim and the Lorde hath encloſed theim, for our God is not as their goddes, and our enemies bee iudges. Of the vineyarde of the Sodomes is their vine, and of the ſuburbes of Gomorra. Their grape is the grape of Galle and the cluſtre is moſte ſower. The gall of dragons is their wyne and venim of aſpes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanable. Bee not theſe thynges laied
<pb facs="tcp:5778:104"/> vp with me &amp; ſealed among my trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures. Myne is the vengeaunce and I will paie theim in tyme, that their fore maie ſlide. The daie of perdicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is at hande, and the tymes haſten to bee preſente. The Lorde ſhall iudge his people, and in his ſeruauntes he will haue pitie. He ſhall ſee that their hande is enfeabled, and thei alſo that were kepte in, fainted, and the reſte were conſumed &amp; he ſhall ſaie. Wher bee their goddes in whom thei had confidence? Of whoſe ſacrefices thei did eate the fate &amp; dranke Libamine wine Let them riſe &amp; helpe you, and in your neceſſitie protecte you. Beholde that I am alone and there is none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God but I. I ſhall kyll and I ſhall make aliue. I ſhall ſtrike and I ſhall heale, and there is none that can pluke oute of my hande. I will lifte vp my hande to heauen and ſaie: I liue for euermore. If I make ſharpe as, the lightenyng my ſwearde and
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:5778:104"/> my hande take iudgemente, I wyll take vengeaunce vpon mine enemies and I wil acquite them that hate me I will make myne arowes dronken with their blode &amp; my ſwearde ſhall deuoure their fleſhe. Of the blode of the ſlain and of the captiuite of the barchedde of his enemies. Comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de ye Gentiles his people, for the blode of his ſeruauntes he will reueng, and he will yelde vengeaunce vpon their enemies, and he will bee mercifull to the lande of his people.</p>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>¶ The prayer of the Centurio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <bibl>Matth. 9.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>LOrde I am not worthy that thou ſhouldeſt entre vnder the roofe of my houſe, but onelye ſpeake with a woorde of thy mouth and I ſhall bee healed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>¶ The praier of the thefe on the croſſe <bibl>Luke .xxiii.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>LORDE remembre me whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou commeſt into thy kyng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:5778:105"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>A TABLE OF</hi> 
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> the contens of this booke.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Praiers for the ſynnes of the people.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>¶ The prayer of Moſes to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde for the ſynnes of the people. 1.</item>
                  <item>¶ An other prayer of Moſes to the ſame. 1.</item>
                  <item>¶ For the ſynne of the people what tyme thei murmured, a praier of Mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes. 1.</item>
                  <item>¶ An other of Moſes and Aaro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the people. 1.</item>
                  <item>¶ For the ſtubbernes of the people y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true preacher on this wiſe as Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes did, maie make his prayer vnto God. 2.</item>
                  <item>¶ The prayer of Salomon in the de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dicacion of the temple of Hieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 2</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5778:105"/>
                  <item>¶ A prayer of Eſdras for the ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the people. 3.</item>
                  <item>¶ The prayer of Nehemias for the ſynnes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people before the lorde 4</item>
                  <item>¶ A confeſſion and ſolemne prayer of the Leuites and of the churche for ſynnes with a reherſall of the benefi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of God. 5.</item>
                  <item>¶ A prayer of the churche for ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. 9</item>
                  <item>¶ Another for ſynnes. 9</item>
                  <item>¶ The lamentacion of Hieremy for the ſynnes of the people. 10.</item>
                  <item>¶ The prayer that Baruche preſcry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bed vnto the captiues in Babilon for their ſynnes. 11.</item>
                  <item>¶ The prayer of Daniel y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophete for his owne ſynnes and for the ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the whole nacion. 14.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Prayers in tyme of ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſitie, and for a man<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes owne ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</head>
               <list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5778:106"/>
                  <item>¶ The prayer of Iacob to bee deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered from his brother Eſau. 16.</item>
                  <item>¶ The prayer of Ioſua that tyme y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people fled in the battaill. 16.</item>
                  <item>¶ A prayer and an open confeſſion of the people of Iſraell to bee deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from their enemie. 17.</item>
                  <item>¶ The prayer of Samſon vnto god that he might reuenge hym, againſte the Philiſtines. 17.</item>
                  <item>¶ In warres againſt Turkes &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uadoures, the prayer of kyng Aſa 17</item>
                  <item>¶ An other of kyng Ioſaphat. 17.</item>
                  <item>¶ The prayer of Nehemias what tyme the Heathen defied hym. 18.</item>
                  <item>¶ If God ſende thee trouble either for a puniſhemente of thy ſynnes or to proue thy pacience therwith, praye thus. 18.</item>
                  <item>¶ The prayer of Manaſſes kyng of Iuda, when he was in priſone, for re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſſion of ſynnes, and for goddes fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uoure and deliueraunce. 19</item>
                  <item>¶ The prayer of Iudith for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liueraunce
<pb facs="tcp:5778:106"/> of her countree frome the tyraunte. 20.</item>
                  <item>¶ An other praier of Iudith whiles ſhe wente aboute to fle the enemie Holofernes. 21.</item>
                  <item>¶ The prayer of Mardocheus in the purſute of Haman for all the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes nacion. 21.</item>
                  <item>¶ The prayer of quine Heſter for her and all her countree menne. 22.</item>
                  <item>¶ The oracion and bleſſyng of Iob in his moſte greuous aduerſitie and loſſe of goodes. 24.</item>
                  <item>¶ A prayer that wee maie bee deliue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red from our aduerſaries. 24.</item>
                  <item>¶ The prayer of Eſaye whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple were ſore plaged. 24.</item>
                  <item>¶ An other prayer of Hieremie. 26.</item>
                  <item>¶ An other of Hieremie. 26.</item>
                  <item>¶ A prayer of Hieremie vnder the perſone of Chryſte, whiche euerye Chryſten maie ſaie in tyme of aduer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſitie. 26.</item>
                  <item>¶ A prayer of Hieremie in the daye
<pb facs="tcp:5778:107"/> of trouble, and in the deſtruction of Hieruſalem. 27.</item>
                  <item>¶ The praier of Suſanna when ſhe was in daunger to be rauiſhed of the twoo elders. 28</item>
                  <item>¶ An other prayer that ſhe made when ſhe ſhould haue been ledde to death. 28.</item>
                  <item>¶ The praier of Ionas whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was as yet in the fiſhes bely. 28.</item>
                  <item>¶ The prayer of Iudas Machabe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us when he ſhould encountre with his enemies. 29.</item>
                  <item>¶ The praier of the preeſtes againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tiraunt that he might not proſpere againſt the holynes of God. 29.</item>
                  <item>¶ The prayer of Nehemias and the préeſtes for the people oppreſſed of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Heathen. 30.</item>
                  <item>¶ The prayer of Eleazar when he was drawen to execucion and redye to dye. 30.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>keſgeuinges and
<pb facs="tcp:5778:107"/> prayſes vnto GOD of the Fathers.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>¶ The ſong of Moſes and the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſraell for their deliueraunce from Pharao. 31.</item>
                  <item>¶ The forme of bleſſyng the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Iſraell. 32.</item>
                  <item>¶ Anna thankyng the LORDE of his benefite, on this maner ſingeth to God. 32.</item>
                  <item>¶ For the benefites receiued at gods hande, the prayer of Dauid. 33.</item>
                  <item>¶ A ſong that Dauid ſong vnto the Lorde in the daie that the Lorde deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered hym oute of the hande of his enemies. 35.</item>
                  <item>¶ A bleſſyng of Tobias the elder, wherewith he bleſſed the Lorde in the ende of his life. 37.</item>
                  <item>¶ The thankeſgeuyng and ſong of Iudith for victorie and for the deliue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry of the countree from their enemy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es. 38.</item>
                  <item>¶ The bleſſyng of Seraphin. 39.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5778:108"/>
                  <item>¶ Thankynges. 39.</item>
                  <item>¶ An other of the ſame. 40.</item>
                  <item>¶ A bleſſyng with an admiracion of the meruelous counſailles of god 40</item>
                  <item>¶ The ſonge of thankeſgeuynge of Mary the virgyn. 41.</item>
                  <item>¶ The propheſie and geuyng of tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes of Zatharie. 41.</item>
                  <item>¶ The prayſe of the angelles at the birth of Chriſte. 42.</item>
                  <item>¶ Geuyng of thankes of Simio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 42</item>
                  <item>¶ Thankes of Paule for his conuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion vnto Chriſte. 42.</item>
                  <item>¶ A ſong of the triumphers ouer the beaſte. 42.</item>
                  <item>¶ A bleſſyng of the people by kyng Salomon. 43.</item>
                  <item>¶ The bleſſynges and prayers of S Ambroſe and Auſtyne. 43.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Praiers for ſuccoures and rele<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fes of life, for wiſedome for humilitie, and for other naturall gyftes.</head>
               <list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5778:108"/>
                  <item>¶ The requeſt of Iacob for ſuſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and relief of this preſent life. 45</item>
                  <item>¶ The praier of Anna vnto the lorde that ſhe might obtain a childe. 45.</item>
                  <item>¶ The prayer of Salomon for wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedome well to gouerne his people, daiely to bee praied of all princes and other rulers. 45.</item>
                  <item>¶ A prayer of Salomon for a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petency of life. 46.</item>
                  <item>¶ A prayer for obteynynge of wyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. 46.</item>
                  <item>¶ A prayer for mekeneſſe and the ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teinyng of chaſtitie. 47.</item>
                  <item>¶ The prayer of Ieſus the ſoonne of Siracke, in neceſſitie and for wyſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome. 47.</item>
                  <item>¶ The praier of Abacuc the prophet for ignorauncies. 49.</item>
                  <item>¶ The prayer of oure Lorde Ieſus whiche he taughte his deciples. 49</item>
                  <item>¶ A prayer of the faithefull congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacion y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei maie ſpeake the woord of God boldely. 50.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5778:109"/>
                  <item>¶ A praier of Chriſt vnto his father for his litle ones, whiche truſt and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe theimſelues vpon hym. 50.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Certain Pſalmes pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked forth miete for dai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly prayers vnto GOD.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>¶ To bee deliuered from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vngodly that wee periſhe not with theim that endeuour by al meanes to withdraw vs from the waie of trueth, and that all good menne, maie continually bee enuironned with goddes proteccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 52</item>
                  <item>¶ To eſcape goddes wrathe and to obtain his mercie, ſo ſhalt thou praie with Dauid. 53.</item>
                  <item>¶ If thou bee falſely belied, and ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligned of thine aduerſary, acuſtome thyſelf to that prayer of Dauid whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che he ſong to the Lorde vpon the woordes of the ſoonne of Iemini. 54</item>
                  <item>¶ A ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctifiyng for the mercy of God ſhewed vs in temptacions, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities
<pb facs="tcp:5778:109"/> and for the meruelous ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion, and deſtruccion of our aduer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaries. 55.</item>
                  <item>¶ A lamentacion and waylyng vnto God, whyte antichryſte triumphethe and ſleeth the holyones of God, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuteth the Goſpell. 56</item>
                  <item>¶ That wee bee not wrapped in the blyndnes of the wycked, and that we periſhe not for euer. 58.</item>
                  <item>¶ That the heauenly father wil not ſuffre vs to ſhrynke at ſo mighty ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries and ſo cruelly purſuynge, whyle wee bee full of all pleaſures of the worlde, ſo wee maie praye with the prophete prayng in the perſone of Chryſte. 58.</item>
                  <item>¶ With muche affiaunce of hearte vpon God a prayer for ſynne and for the grauntyng of his holy ſpirite, for it is not poſſible but God will heare vs a cordyng to chriſtes promiſe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſpell. 59</item>
                  <item>¶ In the affliccion or paſſion bothe
<pb facs="tcp:5778:110"/> of the ſpirite and of the fleſh, ſo maie wee praye with Chriſte and with the godly. 60.</item>
                  <item>¶ A ſainctifiyng of god, for that the earthe is full of his mercie, and that by his mighty woorde he wroughte all thynges. 62.</item>
                  <item>¶ A ſtabliſhemente of the mynde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuche as ſklander vs that wee againe vpbraide not theim, whiche thyng is a greate gifte of God. 63.</item>
                  <item>¶ For remiſſion of ſynnes and of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill luſtes that floue in vs. 64</item>
                  <item>¶ A godly prayer agaynſte the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. 65.</item>
                  <item>¶ That beeyng lightened with god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des grace wee maie knowe here in earth the waie that ledeth to god whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che is a ſure confidente vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god and charite towardes the neighbour. 66.</item>
                  <item>¶ Agaynſte Antichriſte, purſuynge and killyng the holy ones of god and defylynge the miſteries of Goddes woorde. 66.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5778:110"/>
                  <item>¶ A prayer and yeldyng of thankes for that wee bee redemed by Chryſte from eternall death. 67.</item>
                  <item>¶ When wee bee cleane putte out of all conforte, wee maie praye with the prophete in the perſone of Chriſt 68.</item>
                  <item>¶ A bewaylyng of our corrupte na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and of the miſerie of this life by reaſon of ſynne. 69.</item>
                  <item>¶ A ſainctificacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the lordes name for that he made all thynges and all bee in his hande. 70.</item>
                  <item>¶ Whiles we ſeme to bee in the mid<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des of tribulacion &amp; forſaken of men yea and of God alſo. 71.</item>
                  <item>¶ A mery thankeſgeuyng for all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nefites co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ferred vnto vs by chriſt. 73</item>
                  <item>¶ An other geuyng of thankes and prayſe. 74.</item>
                  <item>¶ A halowyng and prayſyng of the Lorde, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he meruaylouſly auaunceth his as well in heauen as in earth 76.</item>
                  <item>¶ A co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendacion of the Lordes mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy that he hath voucheſaue to call vs
<pb facs="tcp:5778:111"/> Gentiles and Heathen perſones vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his faith. 76.</item>
                  <item>¶ A prayer that God hymſelf maie lede, rule teache, and directe vs in his waie, in his preceptes and in his goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, and that he maie kepe vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the doctrynes &amp; tradicions of menne. 77.</item>
                  <item>¶ When wee are bruſed and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in hearte, and contrarywyſe the worlde reioyſeth and triumpheth. 85</item>
                  <item>¶ To bee deliuered from bloudſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, that buſy theimſelues to plucke vs from the waie of God, bothe by force and crafty meanes, and whith labour to aboliſhe godes woorde. 85.</item>
                  <item>¶ That God maie kepe vs that wee ſynne not with our toungue, neither excuſe oure ſynnes as hypocrytes dooe. 86.</item>
                  <item>¶ That wee maie bee ledde forth of the priſone of diſtreſſe, of ſynnes and of deathe to the prayſe and glory of God, that wee bee no longer preſſed vpon earth. 87.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5778:111"/>
                  <item>¶ When wee finde no merites in vs no righteouſnes of our owne, but all thynges deſperate. And again remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bre how God frome the begynnynge of the worlde hathe wroughte won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in his ſainctes, and hath neuer forſaken ſuche as call vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym, thus maie wee praye. 87.</item>
                  <item>¶ A thankeſgeuynge that all bee it wee vile, yet by the vertue of GOD wee bee ſtrong agaynſte all ſtraunge children, that is to ſaie ſuche as bee not choſen to the inherytaunce of God. 88.</item>
                  <item>¶ A prayſynge of God for his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailes, mercy, and the eternall raigne of his clemencie, whiche prouidethe for all his creatour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, and in eſpeciall for ſuche as feare hym. 89</item>
                  <item>¶ A praier of God, that in onely god the euerlaſtyng kynge wee oughte to truſt and not in princes, in power, in wyſedome, or in the righteouſnes of the elementes of this worlde. 91.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5778:112"/>
                  <item>¶ A prayſyng of the lordes name. 91</item>
                  <item>¶ A praiſyng of God from all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures firſt heauenly &amp; then earthly. 92</item>
                  <item>¶ A prayſynge of GOD in hymſelf that he is holy and halowyng, ſtrong and ſtrengthyng, greate, and making great. &amp;c. 93.</item>
                  <item>¶ Againſt the enemie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trouth 93</item>
                  <item>¶ A pſalme whiche bycauſe it is all together euangelicall, and teacheth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt of this worlde wee haue put at thende, to the intent in all our tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulacion &amp; in the pride of the wycked wee maie conforte ourſelues. 95.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Certain praiers ſhorte and of diuers ſortes.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>¶ The prayer of Moſes at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouyng of the tentes. 98.</item>
                  <item>¶ The prayer of Aaron and Moſes for their ſiſter Mari ſtriken with the lepre. 98.</item>
                  <item>¶ The prayer of Moſes to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde that he moughte paſſe into the lande
<pb facs="tcp:5778:112"/> of beheſt.</item>
                  <item>¶ Other twoo ſhorte prayers.</item>
                  <item>¶ Sixe ſhorte prayers.</item>
                  <item>¶ Foure ſhorte prayers. 100.</item>
                  <item>¶ An inuocacion to God for the aide of the faithfull for the vengeaunce of the vnfaithfull miſcreauntes and for manifeſtacion of hymſelf to bee the ſelfſame God that all the prophetes hath preedicate &amp; ſhewed before. 101</item>
                  <item>¶ An exortacion to die gladly for it is the iudgemente of the Lorde ouer all fleſhe. 102</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>PSALMES OF DAVID</hi> agaynſte tyrannes and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutoures of Goddes woorde.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>¶ That all ſuche as liue in ſatans bondage maie come to the knowlage of faith in Ieſus Chriſte. 103.</item>
                  <item>¶ For rulers and comon peace. 103.</item>
                  <item>¶ Againſt the enemies of the people of God, tyrannes, heretikes, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyng
<pb facs="tcp:5778:113"/> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ues. 104</item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> The teſtament of Moſes. 105</item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> The prayer of the Centurio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 108.</item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> The prayer of the thefe on the croſſe. 108.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprinted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n London by Richard Grafton</p>
            <p>Cum priuilegio ad imprimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ſolum.</p>
            <p>Theſe bookes are to bee ſolde at the Weſte doore of P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>s in London. By Wyllyam Tylotſon.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5778:113"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
